>> Hi, everyone.
My name is Neil Desai, and I'm a
WatchKit Frameworks Engineer,
and I'm really excited to talk
about the life of a watchOS app
today.
So, watch apps have a phenomenal
capacity to be simple yet
incredibly powerful.
Well-designed watch apps have
the potential to be the ultimate
companion on your user's wrist.
Now, let's imagine your user for
a second.
What are they asking for when
they want to use your watch app?
Maybe they want to quickly
glance at some information, or
complete a simple task.
We think about great watch apps
that are designed to help your
user accomplish their goals in a
simple, quick way so that the
technology disappears and the
user can go about their day and
have an enhanced experience, all
because of your app.
So, today we're going to design
an app that I've been working on
in watchOS 3.
We're not ready to ship it just
yet, but we'll get to take
advantage of some of the new
capabilities and enhancements in
watchOS 4 to take our app to the
next level.
Today, we're going to talk
through four different additions
in watchOS 4 that can help
design our app.
We're going to talk about some
new things, such as our new
Unified Process Runtime.
We're going to get some great
performance improvements in our
app, and I'm going to show you
how to do so in watchOS 4.
We're going to talk through our
new Frontmost App State.
We're going to take advantage of
this state and build an amazing
experience for our user.
Also, we're going to talk about
some new improvements we've made
to Background App Refresh, and
how we can take advantage of
them.
And lastly, we're going to talk
about some new background modes
that are available in watchOS 4,
and take advantage of one of
them in our app.
So, let's get started and dive
right into our new Unified
Process Runtime.
So, we've designed a
single-process architecture that
will help your apps become even
faster and more responsive to
your user.
So, let's now just revisit some
of the history of where we came
from and where we're now at,
today.
So in watchOS 3, your apps UI
lived in the app process, which
we managed for you, and your
code lived in the watch
extension, so we had two
separate processes, in this
case, that lived on the system.
So, we changed things internally
and unified our process runtime,
so now the UI and your extension
code all get executed from the
same process.
And now, you might be wondering,
why exactly did we do this?
So ultimately, we wanted to
improve the performance of all
WatchKit apps on watchOS 4, so
users could have an even better
experience with your apps.
And, I'm really happy to say,
we've accomplished our goals.
We can see touch latency
improvements of almost up to
twice as fast in some cases.
So, from the moment a user
actually touches the screen, to
when your code gets called into,
we've seen a dramatic
improvement.
Also, for example, we've seen
dramatic frames-per-second
improvements when tied to
general pan gestures, and we
expect launch performance to
also improve.
And now, since we just have one
process to manage your UI and
your extension code, we now have
upped the memory limits to
account for this.
And, you might be wondering,
there's a lot of architecture
that we did internally, so what
do you all have to do to change
your apps to adopt this new
mechanism?
And, the great thing is that
there are actually no changes
required at all.
So, you'll be happy to hear that
all existing native WatchKit
extensions in the App Store
today will get this behavior as
soon as your user upgrades to
watchOS 4.
This new Unified Process Runtime
is completely backwards
compatible.
As long as your app is built
with watchOS 2 or later, you
don't have to anything else.
So, this means the app we're
going to improve today doesn't
need to change in Xcode, or on
the App Store.
It just works.
So now, let's talk about our new
Frontmost App State.
On the watch, a user many times
uses an app in a matter of
seconds, and then they put their
wrist down and expect the app to
finish up whatever task needs to
be finished.
Many times, a user wants to
raise their wrist again and see
your app has finished doing
whatever it needs to, and they
want it to feel like magic.
And, users shouldn't have to
keep their wrist up, for your
app to have to finish doing
whatever task it needs to
finish, and this is a really
common pain point for our users.
So, we thought a lot about all
the different ways we could give
you all more runtime to help
finish your tasks for your user,
and today, we're introducing a
collection of new capabilities
we call the Frontmost App State
to help you design experiences
for this case.
So, without further ado, let's
talk about our app.
So, the app is called Apple Pie
Me, and let's see how it looks.
So, it's a food delivery service
where you can get apple pies
delivered wherever you are, so
an apple pie a day keeps the
doctor away, right?
I think so, at least, I really
hope so, because I eat an apple
pie every single day, and
they're delicious.
And, I'm pretty busy, and I
always just want to quickly
order my apple pie, and get it
delivered wherever I am.
And, most importantly, I want to
tap the order button and then
simply put my wrist down and go
about my day.
In watchOS 3, it was a bit
difficult to build a perfect
experience, but with watchOS 4,
I'm going to show you how to
surprise and delight your users
using our new Frontmost App
State.
So, to help explain the
Frontmost App State, we're going
to talk through what exactly
application state means on the
watch, what does the term
frontmost mean, the enhanced
capabilities that you're going
to receive, and lastly, we're
going to walk through
architecting our Apple Pie Me
app.
So, let's say our user decides
to launch our app.
So here, the app is foreground,
the screen is on, and the
application state, in this case,
is active.
So now, let's say our user
decided to go back to the watch
face.
So, in this case, the app is
actually in the background and,
for instance, your application
might be running for a
complication update, for
example.
And now, let's say our user
decides to go back to our app.
So, we're active in foreground
again, and now the user's using
the app, but then they decide
they want to put their wrist
down.
So, the screen turns off, and
your app is no longer foreground
because of this.
However, since your app was the
last thing used, it's the
frontmost app, so when the user
raises their wrist again, your
app will be what they see,
instead of the watch face.
During this time, we think of
your app as the frontmost app.
So now, when your app is
frontmost in this way, the
application state will be
background, and you might be
wondering how exactly, or how
long does the app stay frontmost
for?
So, it's going to be two minutes
for all apps.
However, if there is an
expectation by your user to see
your app next when they raise
their wrist, then you can use a
new API to extend this timeout
to be eight minutes.
So, for example, if you're a
ride-sharing app in the middle
of a ride, then you might want
additional time in the frontmost
state, because there's a
reasonable expectation that the
user wants to see your app the
next time they raise their
wrist.
However, in many cases, if you
forget to turn this off when
it's not needed, you can
unwittingly annoy your user and
leave them with a subpar
experience.
So, always just make sure to
turn it off, to reset the time
back to two minutes when you no
longer need this experience.
So, let's jump into code to see
how we might enable the extended
timeout.
So, it's really simple.
It's a Boolean property on our
WKExtension, and when we want
eight minutes, we can set it to
be true, and when we want to go
back to the default of two
minutes, we just set it to be
false.
So, there's one other point I
wanted to mention.
If the user raises their wrist
and views your app, then the
timeout is reset, regardless if,
if you use the frontmost
extended API or not.
Essentially, if the user is
still interested in using your
app, your app will stay
frontmost.
So, now we know what frontmost
means, but what does this all
really mean?
Like, what exactly does this new
state give us?
Well, we're going to get some
enhanced capabilities.
So, we're going to change the
notion of how we get our
WatchConnectivity resumes, and
our NSURLSession resumes.
So, our transfer and
connectivity is now improved.
We'll also change a little bit
about our task completions.
>> And then, we're also going to
allow haptics to be played in
this frontmost state.
And lastly, we're going to get a
frontmost notification, so we
can handle this via the user
notifications framework, and
choose the right experience.
So, let's dive right in.
So, for WatchConnectivity, we've
changed the way our background
transfers work, so when you use
on the phone, update application
context, transfer user info, or
transfer file, the request, when
you send it from the phone to
the watch, it'll just go right
through, wake up your app on the
watch, and then just deliver
your payload.
And, there's one point I wanted
to mention in relation to
WatchConnectivity, is that send
message won't work when you're
frontmost, but the screen's off,
because your application state
is background.
So, just always make sure that
call is reachable first, and
then that can allow you to send
the message.
And, along the same vein as
WatchConnectivity, we're also
going to change the notion of
our resumes for NSURLSession.
So, when we have a background
download, for instance, and the
system's downloading it for us,
and then when the system is
finished, it's going to
automatically wake up our app,
if we're in the frontmost state,
and deliver the data right to
our application.
And, of course, with
NSURLSession, there is actually
two major parts.
There is the resume, when the
system has actually completed
downloading whatever it is you
need, but then there's also the
initiation of a download in the
background.
So, in most cases, this will
occur immediately, also, and in
very rare cases, it could get
delayed up to 10 minutes, but
it's a very rare situation.
If you've ever used
NSURLSession, which probably
almost everyone has here, for a
background transfer, this is a
really big deal on the frontmost
state.
To reliably depend on the
initiation and the resume of our
connectivity is really going to
change the design landscape for
the watch, and also, in
addition, with our
WatchConnectivity and getting
requests right from our phone.
So, another thing is, a lot of
times, a user might put their
wrist down, and in that moment,
your application goes into the
background, but you might need
to finish up a task.
So, say you need to close a
database, or do something else.
So, you can just use the
NSProcessInfo class to perform
expiring activity API to get up
to 30 seconds when foreground
initiated, and up to 10 seconds
when background initiated.
So, for example, for background
initiated, maybe you're running
in a complication for an update,
and you just need a little extra
time to get done.
So, you can just use the
NSProcessInfo class to get some
additional time.
And now, when you're frontmost,
and you use that API, then
you'll get increased priority by
the system.
So, because the system believes
that your app is more important
to the user, because it's still
in the frontmost state, the
priority by the system will get
increased, so you're more likely
to get the runtime that you need
to finish up whatever task you
need to do for your user.
And, another benefit of being
frontmost is, you can now play
haptics, so when you have
runtime for another reason, you
can easily just play a haptic.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> So, sometimes haptics can get
a little confusing here or
there, so let me just dive in
and talk to you about, so if
haptics, if you play a haptic,
and let's say some audio is
playing out a speaker, then only
the audio from a haptic will
play, and it ducks what's
currently playing.
If audio is playing out of
Bluetooth headphones and the
screen is on, then the haptics
will play, and if the screen is
off, then just the audio will
play, because that makes the
most sense for your user.
And so lastly, the other benefit
of being frontmost is, when you
receive a remote or local
notification via the user
notifications framework, you'll
then get called into, and then
you can decide the right
experience for your user.
So, maybe you want to just
update your UI, and play the
notification like normally, you
can have that choice, now.
And so, you'll get called into,
when you just override the
function userNotification
willPresent notification
withCompletionHandler.
And, the key of all these
benefits, and this can really
change the design landscape, but
the best part about all this is
it's free, so if your app gets a
WatchConnectivity or
NSURLSession resume, your app
will now get additional runtime.
If your app implements the
willPresent notification
callback, you'll now get that
for free in the frontmost state.
Also, if, for example, you want
to use a NSProcessInfo
performExpiringActivity API to
complete a task on
applicationWillEnterBackground,
you'll get some additional
priority by the system.
You can change nothing in
watchOS 4, and your current,
native application will
automatically be more glanceable
and actionable by default.
And, with the Unified Process
Runtime we talked about earlier,
your application will be even
more responsive.
But, we want you all to take it
a step further.
Your apps can now leap forward
in functionality if you take
these new behaviors into
account.
You need to architect your apps
for this experience.
So now, let's talk through the
Apple Pie Me app, and get
started architecting our app
using these new capabilities.
So, let's revisit some of the
design goals for the app from
the perspective of our user.
So, here we are at a timeline of
our user, and really, the user
just wants to order apple pie,
and then they want to eat apple
pie, and sometimes in between,
they just want to view the
status of their order.
So, it's a pretty simple app
from the user's perspective.
But now, let's break down the
problem from our app's
perspective.
So, when that Order button is
pressed, then we're going to
send that order to our server,
and eventually, when the
restaurant has received the
request properly, and we know
that the pie is cooking, we're
going to send a push
notification.
And then, we also want to tell
our user when a courier is on
the way, and when a courier is
outside.
So, let's break this down some
more, and take it step by step.
So, we're at the Receive Order,
and how exactly do we do this?
Once the user taps the Order
button, what exactly should we
show?
We're going to be sending the
order to our server here, and
can't guarantee it'll come back
immediately, no matter what.
And, do we show something like
this, maybe a Loading indicator?
So, sometimes Loading indicators
do make sense to your user, but
in this case, it's actually
pretty confusing.
I might see this, and I might
think, "Oh, I need to hold my
wrist up.
How long do I have to hold my
wrist up?"
This isn't really a great
experience on the watch.
But instead, we could actually
show something like this.
So, hey, we'll tap you when the
pie's ready.
So, the user knows they can just
drop their wrist and go about
their day.
So, now we know at the Receive
Order screen, we know we just
want to show this new UI
immediately, so now let's break
this down into its separate
components.
So, we want to use NSURLSession
and post the order to our
server, and we also want to
extend the timeout, and then
just update our UI.
And lastly, there are times when
our server might not be
responsive, or something could
have gone wrong, and we need to
handle that case.
So, we need a mechanism that
allows us to schedule something
around, let's say, five minutes
from now.
And, we also need something that
doesn't depend on the network,
or something that, regardless of
frontmost or not, should alert
our user.
We also need something that we
can cancel later on, and so, if
you're thinking about a local
notification, then you'd be
absolutely right.
So, we could just show a local
notification that says, "Oh no!
Something went wrong."
And then, the user can easily
just tap on the Reorder button
and get another apple pie, or
they could just tap on the App
icon and go into the app and see
what went wrong.
So, let's just add that last
step, and now, let's just jump
into some code and see how this
can be done.
So, here we are at our IBAction
for when the Order button is
actually pressed, and then we
just want to grab our background
session, and then we're going to
want to post the order to our
server.
And then, because there's a
reasonable expectation that the
user wants to see our app the
next time, because they just
pressed the Order button, then
we're just going to extend our
frontmost timeout.
And then, we're going to trigger
that just-in-case scenario, our
fallback local notification, and
then we're just going to want to
reload some new UI.
Great. So now, we've received
the order, and eventually we're
going to send a push
notification for when the pie is
cooking.
So now, let's say our user puts
their wrist down sometime after
we've received the order.
So, right before we send that
notification, we expect to be in
the Frontmost App State, but
really, we, the developer, we
don't really need to know too
much about when the user puts
their wrist down, or raises it
up.
The next event that's really
just important is our push
notification, to just alert our
user that their pie is cooking.
If the app is frontmost, we'll
get our willPresent notification
callback we talked about
earlier.
Otherwise, if we're not
frontmost, the user just gets a
notification like normally.
And so, let's jump back into
some code and see what we can
do.
So, here we're just going to
override our user notification
center, willPresent notification
withCompletionHandler.
And then, the first thing we
want to do is, we just want to
make sure that we cancel our
local notification.
And then, we just want to reload
our new UI, and then, because we
did that, we want to just tap
our user, so they know to raise
their wrist.
And lastly, we want to call the
completionHandler and finish up.
And, I wanted to point out for
the completionHandler, it
actually takes a UNNotification
PresentationOptions, and so
that's the options of alert,
badge, or sound.
And, in this particular case, we
actually don't want a
notification to appear on top of
our app, because we've already
tapped the user, and we've
updated our UI, so instead,
we're just calling
completionHandler with none of
the options, so essentially
we're just going to be consuming
the notification, and then,
because the tap comes in, the
user would raise their wrist.
So, we just tap the user, and
they might see something such as
the following.
So, great, their pie is coming.
It's about 12 minutes away.
It's cooking in the oven.
So, here's where we were, and
now let's go back to our
timeline.
So, now we know our pie's
cooking at the restaurant.
And now, let's say we want the
user to be able to raise their
wrist and see as up to date of
an ETA as possible.
So, as soon as the user raises
their wrist, we will, of course,
ask for the most up-to-date ETA,
and this means that the next
time the user raises their wrist
again, we'd expect them to see
that up-to-date ETA.
Great. So, we handled our push
notification.
We now have a mechanism for
updating our ETAs, and now we
just want to send a push
notification again for when the
courier is on the way.
And, if we receive this push in
willPresent, then we're just
going to tap our user again, and
then maybe we might want to add
a map and an updated ETA showing
either where we are, or where
the courier is.
And, let's say, after we sent a
push notification for our
courier is on the way, the user
decides to maybe raise their
wrist.
So now, the user would see the
map and where their courier is,
and the app would provide a
great, glanceable experience.
And next, we can just send
another push for when our
courier is outside.
And then, if we're still in the
frontmost state, we can easily
just play another haptic like
before, and update our UI to
show that the courier is right
outside.
And, at this point, let's just
make sure to disable our
frontmost timeout extended API,
since we expect our user to be
eating apple pie now, instead of
actually just using our app.
So, let's take a look at our
overall timeline.
So, here's our whole flow, and
it all looks great, but let's
try to challenge our assumptions
as much as possible.
Now, what happens if the user
decides to go back to the watch
face?
So, we're no longer frontmost in
that case, but does that really
change anything?
Not really, right?
Let's take it through our app
code again.
So, we use the background
NSURLSession to post the order
to our server, so if, right
afterwards, the user decided to
go back to the watch face, we
know that that will continue,
and then properly post the order
to our server.
And then, we just send a push
notification for all the
different stages.
So, even if we're not frontmost,
the user just gets a regular
notification.
And so, here we are at our
overall timeline.
So, we've handled the cases when
our server wasn't working
properly with the local
notification, and we've worked
through how to use some of the
new Frontmost App State to
provide a great experience to
our user.
And, the best part about all of
this is that our app works great
with or without the Frontmost
App State.
And so, we've now gone through
the Frontmost App State, and our
Unified Process Runtime, and how
it affects our app.
So, let's just now take some
time to revisit Background App
Refresh, which was introduced
last year, and see what
improvements we've added, and
how we can apply it to Apple Pie
Me.
So, let's just go through a
brief overview.
So, in watchOS, the system wakes
your application by handing it a
task, and the system has a
limited number of these to hand
out, so just make sure to make
the best use of each one you
get.
And, when the system wants to
wake your app, it gives you one
or more of these tasks, and then
you can do any work you'd like
in the background, and you just
make sure to hold this task for
as long as you're doing work.
And, the way in which the system
will deliver these tasks to you
is when you implement your
handle background tasks callback
on your WKExtension delegate.
And so, when you finish your
background work, you just return
the task to the system by
calling setTaskCompleted.
So, we've changed a little bit
of the API, so let's walk
through that now, now that we
have a good, conceptual
overview.
So, before, we would implement
our handle background tasks, and
then we would switch case on all
of the different tasks.
So, in this example, we have a
WKApplicationRefresh
BackgroundTask, and then, let's
say we perform whatever
functions we need to, to get our
app up to date, and then we just
want to schedule a snapshot.
And so, we use the
scheduleSnapshotRefresh, and we
use a preferred date.
And then, we just call
setTaskCompleted.
And, the important thing here
that was a little tricky was, it
was really important to call
setTaskCompleted after you
actually scheduled a snapshot
refresh, because if you called
it before, then, like I
mentioned, you're actually, by
calling setTaskCompleted, you're
returning the task to the
system, and no snapshot would
then be scheduled.
So, this was a little bit
cumbersome, and not the best
experience.
So now, all you have to do is
just call a new function that
says
setTaskCompletedWithSnapshot,
and you set it to be true when
you want that snapshot, and set
it to be false when you don't.
And so, for all tasks, the
default is just to take a
snapshot immediately.
However, for snapshot, just make
sure to remember that there's a
special call to setTaskCompleted
with a snapshot.
So, let's take a look at that.
So, here it is, again, we're
implementing our handle
background task, and this time,
we just have a
WKSnapshotRefreshBackgroundTask,
so we're just going to call
setTaskCompleted with a restored
default state, and then our
estimatedSnapshotExpiration.
So, this is really great, and
it's very simple to use, but I
actually want to point out one
cool trick.
So now, you can actually use
setTaskCompletedWithSnapshot on
your snapshotTask.
So, what that does is it will,
of course, take a snapshot
immediately, and then it'll
actually schedule a snapshot an
hour from now, if you set it to
be true.
So, essentially what this means,
if you just keep calling
setTaskCompletedWithSnapshot as
true, you're going to set up a
one-hour cadence, and it's
really easy to constantly make
sure that your app is up to date
every hour.
And, if you want more custom
data behavior, for example, then
just make sure to call
setTaskCompletedWithSnapshot
false after scheduling your
snapshot refresh, because if you
call it with true in this case,
then we're actually going to
replace your previously
scheduled snapshot, and just
replace it with one an hour from
now.
So, if you do want that custom
behavior, just make sure to set
it to be false.
So, another important thing for
our handle background tasks is
how we actually update our
complications.
So, in watchOS 3, we actually
soft deprecated on our
CLKComplicationDataSource, our
getNextRequestedUpdateDate, our
requestedUpdateDidBegin, and our
requestedUpdateBudgetExhausted.
So now, in watchOS 3, I should
say, if you implemented handle
background tasks, these just
wouldn't get called into, and
now they're just fully
deprecated, so they won't get
called into at all.
So, if you want to update your
complications, again, just make
sure to handle background tasks,
and then just call
scheduleBackgroundRefresh with
whatever date you want to update
your complication.
And so, last year, a lot of
times complications can be tied
to some sort of networking task,
and so last year, we guided you
all to essentially, basically
just schedule a background
refresh, and then that way you
would schedule it maybe for,
let's say, 15 minutes from now,
if you wanted a complication
update by 7:45.
So, essentially you would
schedule that background
refresh, and then you would get
woken up around 7:30 to get that
NSURLSession, and then you could
trigger that, and then by 7:45,
you would have enough time to
update your complication.
But now, with some new
NSURLSession APIs, we can
actually just reduce a step
here, and the reason we had
these steps was really because
we wanted to ensure we gave
enough background running time
to our NSURLSession.
But now, with some new API in
URLSessionTask, we can actually
just set an earliest begin date.
So, when we actually call the
download task, we can actually
just set on that task our
variable, earliestBeginDate, so
that way, we're telling the
system, "Hey, we don't need this
right now, we just need this at
whenever date we've specified."
And so now, we can actually just
reduce that step.
So, here in our schedule
background refresh, we probably
also just want to kick off our
URLSession task, and set it up
with the earliest begin date,
and so that way the system, on
our behalf, will actually just
trigger that NSURLSession around
7:30 p.m., and then when that
resume comes back, we can update
our complication at 7:45 p.m.
So now, let's talk about how we
can actually incorporate some of
the Background App Refresh
things we just talked about into
our app, Apple Pie Me.
So, here's that timeline we
looked at earlier.
So now, let's just focus in on
the Pie's Cooking notification.
So, if you remember, the code,
before, it looked a lot like
this.
We implemented
userNotificationCenter,
willPresent notification with
CompletionHandler, and then we
just cancelled those fallback
local notifications.
We updated our UI.
We then played a haptic, and
called our completionHandler.
And now, the great thing is,
once you call that
completionHandler, your app will
get suspended, and you will get
called into via handle
background tasks with a snapshot
task, and then your reason for
that snapshot would be app
backgrounded.
So now, when you have an ETA you
can share, you can just make
sure your snapshot looks as up
to date as possible in the doc.
And then, another thing I wanted
to point out from before was, if
you remember, we actually used,
when the user raised their
wrist, we then kicked off an
NSURLSession to then grab the
most up-to-date ETA.
And so now, with that new API we
just talked about on our
URLSessionTask, we can actually
just even schedule an ETA for
some time from now.
So, let's say, for example,
maybe our pie's coming in 12
minutes, and we just want to
schedule an ETA, like a refresh,
around, let's say, like, eight
minutes from now, for example.
So, let's think about our
overall timeline once again.
This was a really simple app,
actually.
It was just, we had an Order
button, and then we were able to
eat pie.
And then, but, it was actually
really powerful under the
surface in our app code, and so
we were able to take advantage
of our NSURLSession resumes, our
haptics in conjunction with our
frontmost notifications.
We're also taking advantage of
our Background App Refresh, as
well as we were able to schedule
NSURLSession ETA requests.
So, creating a great watch app
that delivered you apple pies
was certainly possible before,
but now with watchOS 4, you can
take a huge leap forward and wow
your users.
So now, let's dive into some of
our new background modes.
So, in watchOS 3, we introduced
our workout session as a
background mode, and now we
actually have audio recording
sessions, and then we also have
navigation sessions.
So, let's dive right into our
audio recording session.
So, in watchOS 3, you could
record audio, but it would,
essentially the API would
present a modal presentation
that would show our UI, and then
the user could then stop the
recording, and then that file
would get delivered to you all,
the developer.
However, now you can actually
just use your own UI, so you can
build the exact recording
experience you want in watchOS4.
And, the important thing is, now
it can be background running
but, of course, it's foreground
initiated and background
running, just like our workouts.
And then, your app will stay
frontmost while it's recording,
and what's great about that is,
you actually have the ability to
play haptics.
So, let's say, for example,
you're an app that wants to
detect what sort of song is
playing around you.
You could easily just press the
Record button.
The user would put their wrist
down.
You could detect what's playing,
and then you could easily tap
your user, so they know that,
hey, you detected what song it
was, and then you could show
that to your user.
And then, what's also great is
that, just like workout
sessions, it's a background
running mode, but the heart rate
sensor is not going to be on, so
there's actually less battery
life impact because of this.
And, another thing I wanted to
mention is, if for some reason
the user decides to go back to
the watch face, for instance,
we're going to show that
Microphone icon at the very top,
so that way the user knows that
something's recording, and then
they can also tap on that icon
and get launched right back to
the app.
So, for playback, in watchOS3.1,
we introduced AVAudioPlayer, and
so now, for recording, all you
need to use is AVAudioInputNode
via AVAudioEngine, or
AVAudioRecorder, and then our
AVAudio recording for
permissions.
And, there's a whole bunch of
formats that are now supported.
And so, let's talk about some of
our locations background mode.
So, just like audio recording
and our workout sessions, it's
foreground initiated, and then
just background running.
And, of course, you're going to
be frontmost while in session.
So, one thing to note is, you
must call startUpdatingLocation
while your app is in the
foreground, and you should also
just make sure to set
allowsBackgroundLocationUpdates
to true only when the navigation
session has actually begun, and
then set it to be false when
it's not.
So, if you recall, for Apple Pie
Me app, we actually had two
users.
We had myself, the person that
was about to eat that awesome
apple pie, and then we actually
had a courier that was going to
bring it to us.
So, in this case, we might
actually just want to build a
companion driver app for that
driver, so that way they can
easily be navigated on their
wrist to our destination.
And, the great thing is, you can
even play haptics while in
session, so now if, for example,
for a right turn or a left turn,
you could play a different
haptic, or maybe when a user has
missed a turn, for example.
And, I'm really excited about
this one, because, like, for
example, transit apps that, you
could imagine, you want to, just
right before the stop you're
about to get off at, the user
could be easily tapped, and then
they could know, oh, I need to
go to the doors, and so I can
get off at the next stop.
So, we're really excited about
our new Unified Process Runtime,
our new enhancements to
Background App Refresh, and our
new background modes, and I
especially am really excited
about the new Frontmost App
State.
And, we think the design
landscape will change in a
really unique way on watchOS.
So, I challenge you all to
design apps for the new
Frontmost App State.
Think through the enhanced
capabilities, and design
experiences where the
interactions are just two
seconds.
And so, we went through how to
use NSURLSession, haptics, and
frontmost notifications, but
that only really scratches the
surface.
With the enhancements to watch
connectivity and task
completions, you could design
even more powerful interactions
that are incredibly simple to
use.
And so, I'm really excited to
see how you all take advantage
of these new capabilities.
So, if you want more information
about this session or any other
session, feel free to go to
developer.apple.com, and then we
have some great related
sessions.
There's a great one tomorrow for
planning a great Apple Watch
experience.
I highly recommend checking it
out.
I'm super excited for that one.
And, I hope you all have a great
WWDC.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]