My name is Gregory Hughes and
I'm really excited to have the
opportunity to speak to you
today about a super important
and interesting topic.
The accessibility of media and
games.
At Apple, we strive to surprise
and delight all of our customers
regardless of their abilities
and disabilities.
We envision a world where users
like Patrick are able to do what
they love and love what they do,
without being hindered by
technology.
We want to make sure that users
with disabilities can experience
the same surprise, delight,
magic moments and most
importantly fun when using our
devices.
As part of that vision, your
apps play a key role.
You play such an important part
in helping us to deliver an
inclusive, accessible and fun
platform for all of our users.
During our conversations today,
we're going to be talking about
four categories of disabilities.
Visual disabilities, which are
those pertaining to sight.
How much a user can see, in some
cases, the users that can't see.
Motor disabilities, which are
disabilities pertaining to how a
user interacts physically with
the device, whether they can
hold the device at all, how to
use a keyboard or mouse.
Hearing disabilities, which are
those pertaining to how much
somebody can hear and in some
cases the complete inability to
hear.
And lastly, disabilities related
to cognition.
And these are displays that
affect how somebody thinks when
using your game.
How much they can remember from
the original instructions you
gave them.
Or what type of UI works best
for them.
So, while talking about these
disabilities, today we're going
to break everything down into
three key sections.
First, I'm going to present how
to make your media and videos
more accessible in your
applications.
We'll then build on some of
those topics and talk about how
to make your games more
accessible.
How do you think about
accessible design in gaming.
And this is really interesting.
As we talk about this, it's
really easy to sit back and say,
"My game can't be made
accessible."
And one thought experiment that
we often go through is let's
start from a point where we
think it can be done.
Let's assume that somebody
that's blind can use my video
editing app, or somebody with
cerebral palsy can play my
first-person shooter game.
The challenge and the fun part
is then figuring out how that
can be done.
And so, try to keep that in mind
as we're going through some of
these specific cases and general
cases for adding accessibility
to your games.
And then last, we're going to
show a demo game that we made,
that highlights some of these
accessible design concepts.
And we'll give you some ideas on
how you can implement them in
your own app.
So, first, the accessibility of
media and video.
And generally, the most
straightforward one that people
think about is the accessibility
of images.
And anyone that's worked in
accessible design will always
say, always add alt text.
But it's not quite that simple
in all cases.
For example, if we take a look
at this image on the screen.
You might describe this as
"Woman sitting in a hammock
playing a guitar."
An equally good description
might be "Person playing guitar
with custom artwork drawn using
a marker."
Equally, you could describe this
as "Image demonstrating the use
of the camera's aperture to make
the foreground blurry while
keeping the subject in focus."
So, the important part when
trying to describe your images,
trying to populate that alt
text, is thinking about how this
image is used in your
application.
What's the context for the image
and what's it conveying to the
user?
Once you can think about that,
you can then create a really
good, clear and concise
description for users that might
not be able to see the image.
So, for images we always want
developers to think about clear,
concise descriptions that convey
the same information that
somebody, that a sighted user
market get.
For audio, we're generally
thinking about disabilities
pertaining to hearing.
How does somebody that can't
hear, or has difficulty hearing
perceive the audio in your
application?
For audio, there are generally
two categories of audio that we
see in apps.
The first is spoken audio.
And this could be something like
a recording of the "I Have a
Dream" speech.
Or it could be a podcast that
you play back in your app.
But regardless, when dealing
with spoken audio you want to
think about in the context of
your application how can you
provide somebody that can't hear
that spoken audio access to the
same information.
So, this is generally some way
of providing a transcript.
This could be a popup that shows
up in your app to show a
transcript.
In the case of many great
podcasts, they have online
transcripts that somebody who's
deaf could go and read to get
the same contextual information
that is conveyed in the podcase.
So, it really how and why you're
using this spoken information
for how you're going to adapt it
to somebody that can't access it
through hearing.
The next way that audio is used
in apps are for sound effects or
ways to convey information.
So, for example, in a game, you
might convey where an enemy is
by audio on the left side or the
right side of the user.
And in these cases, you want to
think about how can you provide
that same information either
through visual or haptic
feedback to the user.
So, again it's thinking about if
somebody can't hear this audio,
which is really easy to
simulate, you can just mute your
device, how can we convey the
same information in our game or
application to such a user.
So, for audio, we are always
thinking about how to convey the
same information, what is an
alternative way of conveying
that.
The last part of media and video
is thinking about video, which
is kind of the combination of
images and audio.
So, if you're not familiar,
video has three key tracks,
sometimes called media groups.
The first is a visual track.
This is kind of the moving
pictures that we see.
The next is the audible track.
This is the track that contains
all the sound, the sound
effects, the spoken dialogue.
And last is what's called the
legible track.
And this one most people are
familiar with.
I know most people are familiar
with it because we intro'd this
with a closed-captioned video.
But you've probably also seen
closed captions in the gym or
the airport.
And legible tracks can be more
than just closed captions.
They can also be subtitles for
users that don't understand the
language.
They could also be closed
captions as I said, but another
term for closed captions is SDH,
or subtitles for the deaf and
hard of hearing.
Subtitles for the deaf and hard
of hearing are different than
normal subtitles and subtitles
for translation.
Subtitles for the deaf and hard
of hearing can include lots more
information about the content.
So, they might include things
like what song is playing.
Was there a loud crash in the
other room, or in some cases,
even the absence of sound.
So, it will just say silence if
that's important to
understanding what's happening.
So, again it's taking a step
back and thinking about if I
didn't have the ability to hear
this video, what information
needs to be conveyed to such a
user.
And so, for the most part, this
is, you're playing back videos,
it's working with your content
providers and making sure
they're aware that you want a
closed-captioned track created.
And in some cases, a subtitle
track.
But it's always thinking about
closed captions and thinking
about users with hearing
impairments and providing
information.
Playing this back is really
simple in your apps.
If you're using AVKit, on iOS or
macOS, you don't have to do
anything.
As long as your content creator
put the track in the video, it
will playback appropriately,
based on the user's settings.
If you're working a little bit
lower level at AVFoundation, you
will need to do a little bit of
work to let a user select which
captioning track they want to
see.
So, if you're the lower level as
I said at the AVFoundation
level, you will need to first
get all of the media group for
the legible tracks again, we
said closed captioned subtitles
are the legible tracks.
You'll then need to do a little
bit of pruning, because this can
be a really big list.
And you want to exclude forced
subtitles and auxiliary
subtitles from that list.
Then you' have a final list of
all of the tracks that should be
displayed to a user and you'll
iterate over them and just add
them to some kind of menuing, or
some kind of other UI that
you're displaying to a user.
If you're working even lower
level than AVFoundation, if
you're taking responsibility for
drawing your own video,
rendering each frame, playing
back your audio, you'll also
then be responsible for
rendering captioning content.
And depending on what content
you're playing, there can also
be legal regulations that you
have to honor, system settings
for the user has for how they
want closed captions to be
displayed.
In order to do this, we have a
great framework called Media
Accessibility.
And this allows you to get all
of those user options for things
like foreground color,
background color, font size,
font choice and other things
along those lines.
So, that you can render captions
the way they look everywhere
else in the system.
That's where most people stop,
right?
Most people are aware of closed
captions, they work with their
content creators.
Make sure they add a captioning
track.
And it's easy to overlook the
audible track.
It's easy to say, for somebody
that can't see, there's already
audio there, we don't need to do
anything else.
But if you think about watching
your favorite movie, or a TV
show that you watch regularly.
If you couldn't see what's
happening, yes, there's audio
but in a lot of cases it doesn't
convey everything that's
happening.
So, there's a technology to
solve that and it's called Audio
Descriptions.
And this is a secondary audio
track the user can select that
contains not only all the normal
narration, not only all the
normal speech and sound effects,
but also narration for what's
happening.
Now most people have never
experienced this.
So, I want to play a short clip
of that intro video, that
includes the audio description
track.
[ Laughter ]
>> I have so much that I've
always wanted to express.
I'm like a volcano.
I'm like Pelee or Mount Etna.
>> Arm the track for recording.
>> I'm about ready to erupt.
>> He dances to a logic session
as titles appear.
Designed for Patrick L.
Designed for everyone.
An Apple logo appears.
>> So, as you can see, this
audio description track is
really important for somebody
that can't see the content.
And maybe not critical in this
short video clip, but it can be
really important when you're
watching a movie or a TV show to
understand what's happening.
And it's mixed correctly with
all of the other audio in the
video.
So, again the key part here just
like captions is working with
your content creators to make
sure, where appropriate these
audio description tracks are
created and rendered with the
video.
Playing them back, just like
captions you will get for free,
as long as you're using AVKit.
Again, just like captions if
you're working lower level than
AVKit, at the AVFoundation
level, you'll need to do a
little bit of work, and almost
the same work.
First you'll need to get the
media group for the audible
tracks.
Instead of pruning this time,
we're going to look for just the
track.
We're still pruning but instead
of excluding tracks this time,
we're going to get just the
primary audio tracks.
And we'll then iterate over
those to add them to a menu or
some other UI where the user can
select them.
So, for video we now have a
complete story.
We've thought about users who
are blind, users who are deaf
and how they interact with our
content.
And how they consume our videos.
So, we talked about images, make
sure you add a clear and concise
description to your images.
Audio, make sure that you're
adding an alternative way for
users to access the audio.
And video, make sure you're
working with your content
creators to create
closed-captioned tracks, audio
description tracks and that
application will support the
playback of these correctly.
Now, I'd like to hand it over to
my colleague Charlotte, who's
going to build on some of these
concepts and talk about how they
can be applied to games and how
you can make some extraordinary
games that are accessible to
users with disabilities.
Thanks.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you.
Thanks. I'm Charlotte Hill and
today I'm going to talk to you
about accessible games.
When you create a game, you want
to make something that your
users will get lost in.
You don't want them to get
pulled out of that experience
because of difficulties
interacting with your software.
Today I'm going to talk to you
about accessible games and how
to make a game that's fun to
play for everyone.
Earlier, we saw a video of
Patrick and how he uses
VoiceOver on his iPhone and his
Mac.
VoiceOver users like Patrick do
a lot of things with their
phones, including playing games.
When you're developing your
game, think about VoiceOver
users like Patrick with
different abilities and
disabilities and how they'll be
able to interact with your game.
Let's say I'm designing an app
based on the Four in a Row game.
This is a two-player game, where
each player takes turns dropping
colored tokens into slots on a
vertical 2D gameboard.
The goal is to get four of your
tokens in a line and block the
other player from doing so.
How can I design it to be
accessible from the ground up?
Today, we're going to talk about
how I can make my game
accessible thinking about four
areas of accessibility; vision,
motor, hearing, and cognition.
These cover huge spectrum of
abilities, but we'll focus on
some key points in each category
and how they relate to Four in a
Row, and likely your game as
well.
First, let's think about vision.
In the context of our game, the
key areas we'll focus on are
color, motion, dynamic type, and
VoiceOver support.
One of the key visual elements
of this game is the
differentiation between the two
player's tokens.
Here, one player is green and
the other is red.
These colors can be really hard
to distinguish for someone who
is colorblind, or doesn't see
color at all.
Here's what the same colors may
look like to someone who has a
type of colorblindness.
Let's take a look at how some
other apps differentiate without
color in their games.
In Causality, the characters are
defined by the colors of the
stripes of their helmets.
So, take a look at their
helmets, and then this is what
it looks like in the colorblind
mode.
You can go back.
So, they've added these shapes
that go along with the colors to
help distinguish between the
characters in their color
colorblind friendly mode.
We can build off that idea and
use shapes as well as colors in
our game.
Now, let's talk about how we'll
use motion in our game.
And you may want to close your
eyes for a second if you get
motion sickness.
Okay, so this is the really cool
animation I wanted to do in the
background of my game.
Not at all distracting.
I think it will be a big hit.
OK you can open your eyes.
Some people experience motion
sicknesses from these kinds of
animations.
Motion sickness happens when
some of your senses tell you
you're moving, but others don't.
When you're using your phone,
your eyes see motion, but you
don't feel it in your muscles,
or your inner ear.
Motion sickness from computers
is actually really common.
In one study, 70% of adults
reported motion sickness while
playing a game.
In my Four in a Row game, I'll
make another background with
less motion to follow the reduce
motion setting on iOS.
This doesn't have to be a static
image, just tighten up the
physics of the motion so there
is less motion overall.
You can find out more about
designing for reduce motion on
the WebKit blog.
Another accessibility setting to
design for is dynamic type.
Dynamic type or larger text
sizes for users with low vision
lets users go beyond the
standard text sizes to something
that's easier for them to read.
Your game should support the
standard text sizes as well as
an accessibility text sizes,
which go up to accessibility
extra, extra, extra-large.
We'll want to test set out our
game with some different text
sizes to make sure our layouts
accommodate them.
You can learn more about making
your app work with dynamic type
at the Dynamic Type Session and
Labs on Friday.
So, we've done a lot to make our
game more accessible for sighted
users with vision problems, but
what about low vision or blind
players.
A lot of players may be playing
your game using VoiceOver, the
screen reader that comes built
in on all your Apple devices and
let's players who are blind hear
everything that's on screen.
Here's an example of how
VoiceOver works.
On my phone, I'm going to swipe
across the screen to move the
different elements and hear
VoiceOver read them to me.
Then I'll tap on the screen and
hear what's under my finger, and
then I'll double tap to press an
element, in this case open an
app.
>> Dock, phone.
Phone.
>> So, when it's moving through
those elements you saw the
little square going.
It also says what it is.
And so, that way a VoiceOver
user can hear everything that's
on their screen.
If you're using AppKit or UIKit
without a lot of custom
controls, your game should
already work pretty well with
VoiceOver.
If you do have custom controls
or images, you can use the
accessibility API to finish
making your app accessible.
For example, in my game I have
these tokens that are custom
views.
And I want VoiceOver to say the
right thing when it lands on
them.
Let's go with player A and
player B.
I can use these strings of the
accessibility label property to
label these elements.
Now, when VoiceOver lands on a
token it will say its name
properly.
And you can learn more about
that in the What's New in
Accessibility Talk that was just
on the screen before that.
It's going to be available
online and they went into some
more detail about using the
accessibility API.
So, for vision we thought about
three key points for our Four in
Row game.
First, we used shapes and
colors.
So, there's more than one type
of indicator for players who are
colorblind.
We provided alternate
experiences for reduced motion
and dynamic type.
And we made sure all of our
elements were accessible and
labeled for VoiceOver.
When you're designing a game for
iOS or macOS you're usually
thinking about players swiping
on a screen or typing on a
keyboard.
However, your players may be
playing your game using
assistive technologies like
Touch Accommodations, the
Accessibility Keyboard,
Alternative Inputs, and Switch
Control.
Some of your players might have
difficulties with fine motor
skills like from arthritis that
make it difficult for them to
accurately swipe and tap in your
game.
These players may use the Touch
Accommodations and Accessibility
Settings to make it easier for
them to interact with their
phone.
However, it's still a good idea
to think about how you can make
it easier to swipe and tap in
your game.
In my Four in a Row app, players
tap on a column to drop in their
token.
I want to make sure these
targets are large and clearly
defined, so it's easy for users
to hit them.
The Human Interface Guidelines
recommends a minimum area of 44
by 44 for topical elements.
If you're designing a game for
macOS, players might be using
the Accessibility Keyboard to
play your game.
Instead of typing on a physical
keyboard, players use the
trackpad, mouse or dwell control
to select keys on screen.
Your game should just work with
the Accessibility Keyboard, but
you may have to provide some
options for keys.
If your game requires pressing
and releasing multiple keys at
the same time, offer an option
for just pressing a single key
instead, or allow a press and
hold so players can use sticky
keys.
You can hear more about the
Accessibility Keyboard in the
What's New in Accessibility
Talk.
Other players may be playing
your game through alternative
external inputs like braille
displays, HID controllers, and
external keywords in iOS.
These are great options for
players who have difficulties in
motor skills, or repetitive
strain injuries.
Supporting keyboards for things
like typing could be
straightforward in your game,
but you may have to do a little
extra.
For example, in Four in a Row,
we needed to implement a
selection mechanism for players
to be able to select a column
using a keyboard.
Other players might be playing
your game using Switch Control,
an assistive technology
available on macOS, iOS and
tvOS.
Switch Control lets you control
your device with one or more
switches which are like buttons
that can be pressed by a hand, a
head, or another body part.
When you're using a single
switch, Switch Control scans all
items on screen and then you can
tap your switch when it lands on
the item you want.
So, here Switch Control is on
and it's scanning everything in
Sushi Go, and then when it lands
on my sushi, I tap my switch.
And I select my sushi.
So, the good news is that if you
already made your game
accessible using the accessibly
API for VoiceOver, which is used
by players who are blind, it
should also work with Switch
Control.
That means that games like Sushi
Go can be played with just a
single button.
In my Four in a Row app, I added
a cool erase gesture that clears
the board when a user swipes in
a zigzag.
However, this could be really
difficult for players who are
using Switch Control or Touch
Accommodations.
So, I'll put an option on my
settings to use buttons instead
of these gestures, so Switch
users can use that instead.
When designing for players with
difficulties of motor skills,
you want to make sure that your
targets are clearly defined and
easy to hit.
Try to provide for different
inputs in your game, like
testing it out with Switch
Control or HID controller.
Provide options for custom
gestures so your game is still
playable with a single switch.
Players in my game might be deaf
or hard of hearing and I want to
make sure they're not missing
out on any of the experience by
providing captions and alert
options.
In my Four in a Row game, I want
to have a single player mode
where the AI speaks taunting
remarks throughout the game to
increase the competition.
However, my players may be deaf
or hard of hearing.
Grim Fandango is a complex
adventure app with a lot of
dialogue, but it lets users pick
between just speech, just text,
and speech with text.
I'll use the techniques Greg
described earlier to add audio
to my game.
Accessibility Settings let your
players customize the
environment to fit their needs.
In Grim Fandango, there's also
different sliders for adjusting
the different types of volume in
the game.
And this is a great option for
players who are hard of hearing,
because that way you can select
what you want your music volume
to be versus what you want the
volume to be for any speech, for
example.
Depending on your game, you
might also want to offer sound
effect options, so players with
hearing loss in one range can
select sound that's in a
different range.
In my Four in a Row game, I want
to use sounds that fill the
spectrum, so more people can
hear them.
I also want my sound effects to
be really noticeable for all
players.
So, I'll combine them with
screen flashes or haptics on
supported devices.
Deaf or hard of hearing players
will enjoy your game a lot more
if you provide captions for any
text.
Depending on your sound effects,
you'll want to try to use full
spectrum sounds, or add audio
options so players can select
what sounds work best for them.
Try using multiple ways of
getting player's attention, like
screen flashes or haptics.
Some of my players might have
cognitive and neurodevelopmental
disorders like ADHD, autism, or
dementia.
These cover a wide spectrum and
so it will be really helpful to
get feedback from my users about
what challenges they encountered
while playing Four in a Row.
However, there are some key
areas I can focus on while
developing my game, such as
options for audio and visuals,
providing help and tutorials,
supporting Guided Access, and
offering different game modes.
When we looked at Grim Fandango,
one great option was the
combination of voice and text.
This is a great option for
players to comprehend better
when there's a mixture of sound
and visuals in the game.
I'll make sure to provide an
option like that in Four in a
Row.
Another thing I want to provide
in my game is easy access to the
instructions.
For players with attention or
memory problems, it can be
really difficult to remember
instructions or rules they
encountered when they first
played the game.
Solivad [assumed spelling] has a
ton of versions of solitaire and
it can be hard to remember all
their nuances, but they all have
a rules button available from
the same screen where you play
the game.
I'll do the same thing in Four
in a Row, and add a button to
the game playing screen, so
players can get back to the
rules.
Some of my players will want to
play my game through Guided
Access.
Guided Access offers players
another way to experience your
app.
A parent or caretaker can set up
restrictions on the game so the
Guided Access user can just
focus on what's really important
to enjoy playing the game.
For example, in Four in a Row, I
have this Auto Play button
that's a little confusing, it
lets the phone play against
itself and so players who
stumble across it might not know
what happened or how to get back
to just playing the game.
In Guided Access, a caretaker
could put a restriction around
that button so that way the
Guided Access user can just
enjoy the game without worrying
about accidentally pressing it.
If your game has things that it
would make sense to restrict,
you can use custom restrictions
in the accessibility API.
These are used in setting up
Guided Access in an app.
And then when the player plays
them, those things are hidden or
locked, so they can't
accidentally use them.
You may also want to provide
different modes in your game.
Real Racing has different
options for drivers that lets
players focus on one aspect of
the game at a time.
Depending on your game it might
make sense to use different
levels instead, but you want to
make sure you're not preventing
players from completing your
game.
I want Four and a Row to be
timed, so players really feel
the pressure when making their
move.
However, a timed version could
be a lot less fun for a lot of
players, including those with
cognitive disabilities.
So, I'll add another option for
an untimed mode in the game as
well.
I've added leaderboards to Four
in a Row, but I have to think
about what ranking means to my
players.
I have diverse set of players
playing my game in many
different ways, and I don't want
it to feel unfair.
I'll create leaderboards for the
different modes that you can
play my game in so that way
players in the untimed mode can
compete against each other
without worrying about what
times the players in the timed
mode are achieving.
Cognitive accessibility covers a
wide range of users, and there's
a lot you can do in your game.
Use multiple methods for
providing content like speech
with captions.
Make instructions and tutorials
easy to access while playing the
game.
Support Guided Access so players
can focus on just what's
important to enjoy the game.
And offer different game modes
or levels, each with their own
leaderboards, so players can
compete fairly.
OK, so now I want to show you
some of the Accessibility
Settings we did in our game.
So, I have my game running in
the simulator right now with the
Accessibility Inspector.
And I found the Accessibility
Inspector in Xcode under
Developer Tools.
And there's a lot you can do
here.
And I'm not really going to go
into it because there's a really
great talk in it last year.
But over here you can inspect
your app.
And so, it will tell you what
different accessibility
information it can get about the
things in your app.
Or you could run an audit which
is really helpful, because it
will just highlight some
different accessibility bugs you
might have in your game.
But, today we're going to look
at the settings tab.
And this is really cool, because
it lets you test different
accessibility settings without
leaving your game.
And I'm just doing this on the
simulator, but up here if you
have your phone plugged in, you
can actually pick your phone too
and so you could do it on device
and that way you don't have to
leave your game and like go into
settings and go back.
So, it's really handy.
So, one that we did was reduce
transparency.
And for that we just did a
simple black background to make
the gameboard really stand out.
We also supported different font
sizes for dynamic type.
So, there's a slider here and I
can just make the fonts bigger
or smaller.
And the next one is invert
colors.
And to know why we implemented
it the way we did, you have to
know a little bit about how it's
used.
So, invert colors is used by
players who have difficulty
reading dark text on a light
background because the
brightness of the background
interferes with their vision.
So, they'll use invert colors,
to make that light text on a
dark background instead.
Since our game is already like
that, we used the accessibility
API to tell it not to invert
colors for this screen.
So, when I do invert colors,
nothing happens.
But if I go to like settings,
which is normally white, it's
all black.
And then if I uncheck it, it
goes back to white.
So, we have a lot of different
settings here in this game that
we added for accessibility
reasons.
So, let's check that out as
well.
So, here's my Four in a Row app.
I can just tap on a column to
make a move.
But more exciting than the game
is the settings.
And we have a lot here.
So, first is volume.
We added different sliders for
the speech and the sound effects
because people who are hard of
hearing might want to emphasize
the speech over the sound
effects.
So, we could turn down the sound
We also have captions.
And so, those are just going
directly from the settings for
your phone.
And we have Differentiate
Without Color.
And if you noticed before, right
now it's all circles.
But when I turn on Differentiate
Without Colors, we made it so
now it's circles and triangles.
So, it's easier to tell apart
the different players.
So, we have a lot of other
settings here, but the one I
wanted to focus on was timing.
We added a Turn Time slider
which is great because that
gives players who have trouble
coming up their next move or
difficulty moving that quickly
some extra time to make their
move.
But for now, I'm going to turn
off the timed mode because I'm
going to be testing this out
with some assistive technologies
and the combination me using
them and talking about them is
going to slow me down a little
bit.
So, oh, yeah and I'm already
very close to losing.
So, I'm glad I turned that off.
Okay, so now I'm going to test
it out with VoiceOver.
And I have VoiceOver set up on
my accessibility shortcut.
So, I can just triple tap on
home and turn on voice over.
>> VoiceOver on.
Landscape.
Four in a Row.
Empty image.
>> So, it's labelled.
That's good.
And I can swipe through and hear
all the cells in the gameboard.
>> Move empty image, empty
image, empty image.
Winner, four question marks.
Actions of player B, image.
Player B image.
Actions available.
>> So, I can move to everything.
It's labelled, it's accessible,
but when I was testing this out
earlier in VoiceOver, I found it
just wasn't a really fun
experience.
It was too hard to move through
all the different slots on the
gameboard, keep track in your
head of which ones were filled
and which weren't and come up
with what your next move should
be.
So, I used something in the
accessibility API called the
Custom Action to improve that
experience.
I added an action that switches
you from moving by cell to
moving by column.
Let's do that.
>> Move by cell, move by column.
Column 3, 4 empty cells, 2
player A tokens.
>> So, that way VoiceOver can
move via column instead of by
cell and that makes it a lot
easier for me to just get a
sense of what the gameboard is
in.
And that technique I used for
making it move by column instead
of by cell was also really
helpful for Switch Control.
So, let me show you that.
I'm going to turn off VoiceOver
and switch over to Switch
Control.
>> Alert. Accessibility list
control button.
VoiceOver off.
>> OK, so now I have Switch
Control on and I have my switch
here.
And Switch Control is scanning
all the things, I'm sorry.
Switch Control is scanning all
the items on the screen and so
when I go into the gameboard,
it's going to, before it was
going by cell, and it was super
tedious to try to wait for it to
go through each cell to get to
the one that I wanted.
But now, when I go into the
gameboard, it's going by column
instead of by cell, which it did
originally, and so I was able to
use accessibility API to change
that experience to make it
better.
So now I can just press my
switch and make my move.
So, let me show you some other
things that we did.
Let me turn off Switch Control.
And right now, if you're
noticing I have my screen setup
to be a switch too.
And that's an awesome option for
testing, because that way you
don't need to set up a switch.
So, you're just, your phone
works as a switch.
Okay, so we also made it work
with a keyboard.
And so, I mentioned earlier for
that, you needed to do a
selection mechanism, so that way
when I hit the arrow keys, I can
move by column, and then just
press space to make my move.
So, providing these options for
these different assistive
technologies really broadens
into my audience.
It means a lot more people will
be able to play our game.
We were able to make a lot of
improvements to our game by
testing it out with different
assistive technologies and
accessibility settings.
When you're doing this, it can
be easy to fall into the trap of
following the letter of the law,
but not the spirit.
As well as being accessible, you
want your game to be fun to play
for everyone.
The accessibility API offers a
lot of great tools for improving
that experience.
Now, you may be thinking about
your own app and how you can get
started making it accessible.
The three things you can do the
minute you walk out of here are
to audit your app, test it out
with different accessibility
settings, and most importantly,
talk to assistive technology
users.
So, we already mentioned this
talk a little bit, but it's
really good.
So, you can learn more about
both auditing your app and
testing it with accessibility
settings and Auditing your Apps
for Accessibility talk from last
year.
It's really important to test
out your game with assistive
technologies, but you should
also try to talk to the users
who use them every day.
They'll have a firsthand
experience of what separates a
good experience from a great
experience.
And they'll probably have a lot
of ideas for how you can make
your game more accessible.
You can connect with
accessibility users and
developers at our get-together
tonight.
Designing your game for
accessibility really means more
people can enjoy it.
When you're designing for
accessibility think about how
accessibility is really a
spectrum.
So, you want to create these
different great experiences so
each player can find out their
own perfect fit.
At the end of the day, your game
will be stronger and richer,
because designing for
accessibility is really
designing for everyone.
You can find out more
information on and the developer
website.
You can see this session again,
and I think we have some notes
and information there.
There's a lot of other related
sessions going on this week and
there's more that you can see
online from some previous years.
Thank you and enjoy the rest the
conference.