>> All right.
Good afternoon everyone.
[ Clapping ]
My name's Pete Hare and I'm an
engineer on the App Store team
here at Apple.
Now you're probably here because
you're in one of a couple of
different groups.
Maybe you're here to find out a
bit more about integrating
in-app purchases into your
application and you want to know
a bit more about how to do it
securely and reliably.
Or maybe you're here to find out
about subscriptions and you want
to understand the process of
maintaining a subscription state
across multiple platforms in a
server environment, that kind of
thing.
Well whichever group you land
in, in-app purchases really
represents a new level of trust
between you and your users.
You see as soon a user is
handing over money in exchange
for digital content or services,
they're really entrusting you
with the responsibility of
delivering that in a reliable
and secure manner.
So today we're going to talk
about some techniques do that.
Firstly, we're going to discuss
receipt validation in greater
detail.
We talked on it a little bit
this morning in the what's new
session but we're going to go
into some details around how to
do this on the user's device.
We're also going to talk about
maintaining a subscription state
particularly on the server and
how to update multiple different
platforms based on that
subscription state.
Finally, we're also going to
touch on development in a
sandbox environment.
So how you can use these
technologies when you're
developing without actually
having to use your own money.
So I'm going to put up this
diagram.
This is what we looked at in
this morning's session.
This was the in-app purchase
flow.
So this is what you need to
implement in your application in
order to actually sell in-app
purchases.
In this particular session,
we're just going to really focus
on these last three points
though which I'm going to refer
to as processing transactions.
So this is when StoreKit
delivers a transaction to you
once a user's made a payment and
it's up to you to then process
that transaction and deliver the
content to the user who's paid
for it.
So I'm going to expand out these
three steps now and also
introduce an extra layer to this
which is to add your server into
the mix.
So this is how we can think of
it for this particular talk.
The process is going to start
with us receiving a transaction.
And this arrives by a StoreKit
on the user's device.
Then you make a choice as to
whether you want to validate the
receipt on the user's device or
up in the server.
From there, you can proceed to
inspect the contents of that
receipt and unlock content or
update a subscription state
based on that contents.
And finally the last step in the
process, to finish the
transaction back down on the
user's device.
Now you'll notice that the first
and last parts of this flow
occur on the device level only.
We don't allow transactions to
come in at the server level.
Now this is really important.
Even if you're using a service
side flow for receipt
validation, you still need to
make sure that you receive and
finish transactions on the
user's device.
Now this morning, we also
discussed the four different
types of in-app purchases.
If you're dealing with
consumable products or
non-consumable products, it's
quite likely that you'll do a
flow like this, which is the on
device flow.
This is where you can inspect
the receipt and unlock content
without sending anything up to
your server or requiring a
network request.
If you're dealing with
subscriptions, auto renewable
subscriptions in particular,
it's quite likely that you'll
have a situation like this where
you want to keep state on the
server side.
And you need to have a server
being able to update multiple
devices from there.
You can, of course, do both of
these techniques if you want.
But either way, the process
still starts at that same point
which is to receive transaction
on the device.
So let's dive now into each of
these steps to see what they
look like.
This is right at the start of my
application life cycle.
We have the did finish launching
with options delegate method on
the application and here we have
to register a transaction
observer for the SK payment
queue.
So you need the transaction
observer to be registered as
early as possible in the
application life cycle so that
you can start to receive the
updated transactions that come
through StoreKit.
Here I'm just adding the app
delegate itself as my payment
observer but you might add a
separate controller object to do
this for you.
It's really up to you.
What's important is that it's
happening right at the start of
the application life cycle but
once that's registered, you're
ready to start receiving
transactions through the updated
transactions call back.
So this is the updated
transactions call back in the
transaction observer.
And you receive an array of
transactions that you can
iterate through.
You can check the transaction
state on each of these.
And you want to look for a
transaction in the purchase
state.
So this is a transaction that
StoreKit deems appropriate for
you to go ahead and validate.
And then unlock content for.
So it's telling you that the
user has actually handed over
money.
So once you've got that
transaction in a purchase state,
you're ready to go ahead with
the next step in this diagram.
So let's firstly look at how to
do this validation of the
receipt on the user's device.
Now what is the receipt?
We talked about it a little bit
this morning but for those of
you who weren't there, the
receipt's really just like a
document.
Like a receipt you'd get at any
department store.
It's a proof of purchase that
really is an authentic document
that indicates they've bought
what they say they've bought.
So we've have this application
receipt which is a trusted
record of the app and any in-app
purchases that a user's made in
your application.
This particular receipt's stored
on the device.
And it's issued by the App
Store.
It's put there by StoreKit.
Now it's assigned an verifiable
document which means you can use
certificates to be able to check
that this document was actually
issued by Apple and put there on
the user's device to make sure
it's authentic.
Finally it's for your app on
that device only which means it
can't be shared across devices
or amongst other applications.
So when it comes receipt
validation, this is the process
of ensuring that this document
is an authentic document and not
some phony one that's someone
put there.
There's two ways to do this.
You can do this on the device,
which we're about to look at now
and of course, you can do this
by sending it up to your server
using the server-to-server
validation.
Now I just want to point out
here that if you're on the
user's device, it's really
important that you don't use
online validation directly from
the user's device because this
isn't a secure way of checking
at all.
If you're going to be doing it
directly on the device, you need
to use these checks we're about
to do now.
So what does the receipt look
like?
Let's take a look at the actual
document.
The receipt document.
We just take all that purchase
information about your
application including all the
in-app purchases and we wrap
that around certificates and
signatures in order to create a
document that you can check for
authenticity.
So it's a document that's stored
in the application bundle and we
provide an API for you to
actually get that document.
It's a single file.
And it contains all the purchase
data about the application and
also the in-app purchases that
have occurred.
And it also contains a signature
for you to be able to check for
authenticity.
To make sure it's issued by
Apple.
The document is based on a
series of industry standards.
So it's actually signed using
the public key cryptographic
standard 7, cryptographic
container.
It's encoded using an ASN.1 data
encoding.
And don't let the acronyms, the
daunting acronyms fool you.
These are actually very public
open standards and there's a lot
of information available online
for you to be able to actually
do these things.
One prebuilt technique that you
might recognize is actual
OpenSSL.
So OpenSSL is a framework that
not only provides the
functionality for secure web
traffic tunneling, it also
includes functions to be able to
read in the data encoding from
an ASN.1 payload and also check
the signing on a cryptographic
container like this.
Of course, you can use a
prebuilt solution like OpenSSL
or you could even roll your own,
you know, to read in this
particular data.
It's really up to you and your
business as to which solution
you use.
You see when it comes to
security and this particular
type of check, it's not a binary
choice.
It's not secure or not secure.
You know, security's a scale.
So you have to think about how
far down that scale you want to
go in order to verify these
purchases.
But either way, it starts by
reading in this encrypted data
for this document.
So you do that by using the API
I mentioned.
It's the AppStoreReceiptURL API
on the bend bundle.
That gives you an url that you
can just past through to a data
object and you can read in that
encrypted binary data to a
receipt object.
So now you've got that encrypted
binary data in memory ready to
act on.
A couple of tips if you do want
to use OpenSSL.
We're not going to go through
the whole process of using
OpenSSL in this talk but OpenSSL
doesn't actually ship with iOS.
You have to build it and include
it in your app yourself.
If you are building it, remember
to build as your own static
library for your application and
not a dynamic library.
If it was a dynamic library,
it's much easier for someone to
come along and switch out that
dynamic library with a phony one
than say, you know, messing with
the actual methods inside your
own application binary.
So a static library will mean
that that binary data's wrapped
up with your own application and
it's much harder for someone to
come along and switch out your
OpenSSL instance.
When it comes to the actual
certificate check, you can
download the Apple Root
certificate authority's
certificate from the Apple site.
And you can use that certificate
to actually perform that check
using OpenSSL to see that it is
a verified document from Apple.
If you are bundling in the app,
just one note here that be
mindful about the expiry date on
the actual certificate that
you're including with a bundled
application.
There is plenty of documentation
online for this.
In fact, we had a session here a
couple of years where we built
OpenSSL here on stage just in a
live demo and did these checks
here on stage.
So it's a much simple process
than you might think.
So I'd encourage you to check
out those previous sessions on
receipt validation to see how
that might be done.
When it comes to prebuilt
solutions, I'm sure some of you
in here have tried integrating
in-app purchases and probably
maybe go on Get Hub and found a
solution that's prebuilt that
can do a lot of these checks for
you.
Just remember when you're
downloading prebuilt solutions
that convenience comes at a
price.
And so reusing code like this
brings with it any bugs and
vulnerabilities.
And that's especially important
when it comes to transactional
APIs like StoreKit.
Can you imagine if every jeweler
around the country used the same
lock on their safe?
And then a single exploit was
found on that one particular
lock.
Suddenly every jeweler around
the country has their jewels
vulnerable to the same single
exploit.
So it's important for you when
you're doing this to know and
own the risks as you build it.
And remember that while you're
building these integrations with
StoreKit, it's your revenue
stream.
And so people who are building
these prebuilt solutions are not
as inclined to be worried about
your money as you are.
When you're verifying the
receipt -- the actual
certificate used to sign the
receipt, a couple of tips here.
You don't need to actually check
the expiry date of the
certificate used to sign the
receipt.
What do I mean by that?
Well, if you think about a
receipt that's encrypted at a
point in time, let's say two
years ago and then someone signs
it with a certificate that's
valid at the time.
Then that certificate expires a
little while later.
Just because the certificate's
now expired and we're in the
future, doesn't make the receipt
actually any less valid.
What's really important here is
not whether the certificate's
still valid right now, it's
really only important as to
whether it was valid at the time
the receipt was made.
So if you're going to compare
that date to anything, compare
it to a purchase date of a
transaction inside the receipt
to make sure it was valid at the
time of signing.
Let's take look inside the
actual payload of the receipt.
So this is the ASN.1 encoding
that I mentioned.
All this is, is really, a series
of types and values.
Much like dictionary.
You can just think about it as
keys and values like a
dictionary would have.
And you could read out these
particular values based on the
different types.
So now that you've verified that
the actual document is signed
using the right certificate from
Apple, you need to verify that
the application used to make
this receipt is the one the
user's running on.
So how do we do that?
To verify that this receipt's
for this application, there's
two particular types of
attributes.
Type 2 and 3, and they contain
the bundle identifier that this
receipt's for and also the
bundle version that this
receipt's for.
So what you need to do is
compare these two particular
attributes to hard coded ones
inside your application.
It's important to use hard coded
values here because of the same
principle I mentioned earlier.
If it's an info plist file, it's
much easier for someone to
switch out a plist file with
phony values to match a phony
receipt than it is to switch out
something to match hard coded
values.
But if you check these two
things against hard coded values
and they match then great.
You verified that the
application is correct.
The next step is to verify the
device that the user's on and
verify that this document
matches.
We do that using types 4 and 5.
It's a similar process but this
time, the one that we want to
check is attribute number 5.
Now attribute number 5 is
actually a SHA-1 hash of these
three values.
It's a SHA-1 hash of the bundle
ID, the device ID, we provide
APIs for the device ID.
And the third one is an opaque
value, which is really just the
attribute in type number 4.
Now the reason we do that, it's
a little bit of cryptographic
entropy.
A bit of secret salt that allows
that SHA-1 hash to change over
time, even the bundle ID and the
device ID aren't changing.
So it just makes this process a
little more secure.
And so accordingly, this SHA-1
hash is unique to this app on
the device.
And what you do is you create
that SHA-1 hash using your own,
you know, hard coded values.
The same technique that we did
before and you compare it to the
one in type number 5.
And if they match, then that's
it.
You verified that the device the
user's on matches the one the
receipt is for.
So now you've done those three
checks.
That's the process of validating
the receipt on the device.
You now know that this is a
document that you can trust when
you're reading out further
information from it.
So let's take a look at the next
step which is to actually update
state and inspect the contents
of these in-app purchases inside
the receipt.
Let's dive back into what the
payload of the receipt contains.
The receipt contains a specific
type, type 17 for every
transaction that occurs for this
user on this device.
Now in each type 17, the actual
payload is another ASN.1 encoded
container.
And inside of this, there's a
bunch of types and values that
are associated just for this
specific transaction in
question.
So we have things like a
quantity, a product identifier,
a transaction ID.
So these are values that you can
use to verify that a transaction
exists in the real world.
One more to call out while I'm
here is type 1708.
This is particularly important
if you're dealing with auto
renewable subscriptions.
This contains the expiry date
for a particular transaction for
a particular billing period.
And we'll come back to talking
about subscriptions in a bit.
If you want to know more
information about all the
different types that are
included here, I'd just
encourage you to check out the
Receipt Validation programming
guide online.
And we go through all the
different types that are
actually included in the
receipt.
But now that you can read all
these transactions, it's up to
you to use those to verify the
content that StoreKit's telling
you the user's bought.
So what you do is you take the
transaction that's appeared
through this updated
transaction's call at the
beginning of the process and all
you have to do is compare all
those values to the ones inside
the receipt.
So you can use things like the
transaction ID, the purchase
date, the product identifier
that it's saying the user
bought, and if you can verify
that there's a transaction that
matches then great.
You've got a proof -- a document
proving that the user actually
purchased it and money's
actually changed hands.
So you can trust the transaction
that StoreKit's telling you.
When you're dealing with
subscriptions a common question
at this point is does my user
have an active subscription.
Well one thing just to note
here.
Just remember that a valid
receipt is not the same thing as
having a subscribed user.
So there's a bit of confusion
sometimes.
If you can validate the receipt
that doesn't mean that the
user's actually paid anything.
You know every app has a
receipt.
It contains information about
original application purchases
even for free apps.
It's the data inside the
receipt.
These transactions that's going
to tell you about the
subscription state of the user.
Now how do we find out that
subscription state?
You could take those
transactions and you want to
group them together by the
original transaction ID field.
This field just contains that
first transaction ID for a
particular auto renewable
subscription that a user used.
You can kind of think of this as
being like a subscription ID
that you can use to reference
and group together these
transactions.
So you can grab those
transactions and you want to
look for the one that has the
latest expiry date.
Now this is an indication of the
latest transaction that's taken
place.
So if you see an expiry date in
the future, that's an indication
that the user's in the middle of
a billing period and they have
an active subscription.
Now if you find an expiry date
in the past, that's an
indication that there's been no
transaction since then.
So the user's subscription's
actually lapsed.
Now if you do find this, you can
do what we say -- what we call a
receive refresh request.
And this'll go fetch the latest
copy of the receipt just as a
double check and you can repeat
those steps of receipt
validation and check these steps
that we just called above to see
if any new transactions have
appeared.
Now there is one caveat when
you're maintaining a
subscription state on the device
like this.
We talked about, you know,
expiry dates.
And we've talked about purchase
dates.
Well if you're doing this purely
on the device, the only data you
actually have to compare these
to is the user system data.
So what's stopping the user from
just winding their clock back
and putting themselves into an
active subscription period?
Not a lot, unfortunately.
So if this is a problem for you,
it's probably likely that you're
going to need to look at some
kind of service side solution.
Maybe look at receipt validation
on your server or at least, some
check to actually get timed --
time and date from your server
to check it against.
When it comes to actually
refreshing the receipt like I
just mentioned, you can do this
if the receipt doesn't exist or
it's invalid or maybe you're
searching for that extra
transaction.
It will require a network
request because it goes and
fetches a new receipt from the
App Store.
And it will require sign-in from
the user which means that you
should be very careful about how
often you do this and avoid
continuous loops of validating
and refreshing.
If you're doing that example
that we just spoke about where
you're looking for that expiry
date, make sure that if you
don't find it that you don't
just keep refreshing the receipt
refresh request over and over
again because it'll keep
prompting the user to log in.
So just issue one of these
requests if you're going to do
it and this is what it looks
like in code.
You create an
SKReceiptRefreshRequest object.
You set a delegate on it and you
just kick it off using the start
method.
On mac iOS if you're developing
for the Mac, same principles
apply.
You can do this if the receipt's
invalid.
It'll require a network request
and it will prompt the user to
actually log in as well but in
this case, it's a little
different.
The API what you do is you exit
your application using the code
173.
And that looks like this.
So this'll exit your
application.
This will trigger StoreKit in
the background to go and
download a new receipt to the
Mac and then it'll prompt the
user to log in and launch your
app again.
Now at this point I just want to
touch on a couple of differences
here between restoring
transactions and refreshing the
receipt.
These can be sometimes be
confused.
These are two separate APIs.
So restoring completed
transactions which is an API we
looked at in the What's New in
StoreKit talk this morning, this
is an API on the SK payment
queue whereas the receipt
refresh request is its own
instance that you create and you
kick it off using the start
method.
And they accomplish slightly
different things.
So restoring completed
transactions causes all the
completed transactions that have
occurred for a user to appear
back on that updated
transactions call back for you
to be able to process.
Whereas the receipt refresh
request is really just used to
go and fetch that new receipt
document.
That encrypted binary code for
you to be able to check the
contents of.
And there's also a slight
difference to actually what they
include.
So when you're restoring
completed transactions, this
restores only non-consumerable
products and auto renewable
subscription products.
Whereas a receipt refresh
request has both of those but it
also includes also any
non-renewing subscription
entries in the receipt.
So you'll notice that consumable
products are absent from both of
these types of requests.
If you're dealing with
consumable product purchases,
they're just going to appear
both in the updated transactions
and on the receipt at the time
of purchase.
So you kind of have that one
chance to actually verify the
consumable product and it won't
be restored for either of these
calls.
Now one other tip for dealing
with receipts is if you're
looking to switch to
subscriptions, maybe you've got
a paid application and you want
to switch it to being a
subscription model, you can use
this type 19 value in the
application receipt.
This contains the original
application version.
So you can use this application
version that a user originally
downloaded as kind of a gate to
know as to whether you need to
provide a content based on a
paid app or based on a
subscription.
You know it's not a great
experience if you've paid for an
application and then suddenly
you lose access to that
functionality you paid for if
it's now a subscription model.
So use type 19 as a bit of a
gate to be able to supply that.
So once you've done this step,
that's the process of checking
the transaction and confirming
subscription state on the
device.
You can then go ahead to finish
the transaction.
So you've made the content
available to the user.
You've updated that subscription
state.
When it comes to finishing the
transaction, you have to
remember to finish all
transactions that come through
this flow but only do it once
you've made content available to
the user.
So maybe you're downloading
content associated with an
in-app purchase.
Make sure until that download's
completely finished before you
go ahead and finish the
transaction.
And this includes all auto
renewable subscription
transactions.
So these renewable transactions
that come in at the end of each
billing period, you still need
to finish all of these
transactions and handle them.
And if you don't, the payment
actually stays on the payment
queue and it'll keep reappearing
in the updated transactions call
back until you deal with it and
call finish transactions.
We also have specific logic
around subscription billing
retry.
So if you do have auto renewable
subscriptions, it's important
that you do finish these
transactions so that our
subscription billing retry logic
can continue to try and charge
user's credit cards if there's
any kind of billing error along
the way.
So this is quite important for
our end to know the state of all
these transactions.
This is what the API though
looks like.
It's just one line of code.
You can pass in that transaction
object that we received at the
start of the process to the
finish transaction method on the
SKPaymentQueue's default queue.
So that wraps up that device
flow of validating the receipt
and updating content on the
user's device.
Let's jump up now and look at
how this works in a service side
environment.
And to do this, let's just walk
through a bit of an example.
Let's say I have a user here and
it's using your application and
you've got a server there
powering your back end.
The process here starts, of
course, with receiving that
transaction and the update
transactions call back that we
saw.
From there, you could read in
that binary receipt data using
the API mentioned.
At this point it's still encoded
so we haven't done all these
checks yet with the certificate
or anything.
Instead of doing it on the
device, what we can do is take
that binary encoded receipt data
and send it up to your server.
From here, you can just
establish connection over to the
App Store server by this verify
receipt url.
And you pass that binary data
over to the App Store.
Now the App Store does all that
hard work of checking the
certificates and verifying all
this information.
And it responds with a receipt
validity status as to whether or
not this is a valid document
that you can trust.
So this is it again really in
textual form, the response is in
JSON.
And it returns that status as to
whether a receipt is valid or
not but one point to note here,
as I mentioned before, you
shouldn't ever use this
technique directly from the
user's device.
This is really only secure when
you're doing it from your server
to the App Store.
And that's the whole step of
validating a receipt on your
server.
It's a little simpler than on
the user's device.
Now let's take a look at how you
unlock content and inspect
transactions based on this
scenario.
Let's look at this example
again.
So let's say that you've sent
that binary data up to your
server.
You establish that connection to
the App Store and you send over
the binary data to the App
Store.
Now not only does the App Store
actually respond with the
validity of the receipt, the
response here actually includes
a decoded version of the latest
application receipt as well.
So this is a decoded version in
JSON that you can inspect and
look at all those transactions.
It's just the same consent that
you see on the user's device
when you decrypt it on the
device but this time it's a JSON
payload from the App Store and
you can just inspect all those
transactions.
Make decisions about whether to
unlock the content and then go
ahead and finish that
transaction back down on the
user's device again.
This is particularly useful
because you can then do things
like updating state across other
platforms that you might have
associated with your server.
So this is what that process
looks like, again, just in text
but the important point here to
call out is that you have to
remember to tell the device to
still finish the transaction if
you're using this technique.
So let's answer this question
again of unlocking subscription
features.
So does my user have an active
subscription.
It's exactly the same flow, you
know, here because we said that
this receipt contains all the
same information.
So you can group the
transactions that come back in
this receipt by the original
transaction ID.
That's that subscription ID
field.
And all you need to do is find
the transaction that has the
latest expiry date.
And if there's an expiry date in
the future that's an indication
that the user is in an active
subscription.
If there's not an expiry date in
the future, if it's in the past
somewhere well that means that
the subscription's unfortunately
lapsed.
And this is the latest copy of
the receipt.
So there's no way that you can
really do a receipt refresh
request from the server.
You've just got the latest copy
already.
So now we've unlocked content on
the server based on this
information.
As I mentioned, you still need
to remember to finish the
transaction back down on the
user's device again.
You'll hear me say finish
transactions a lot in this talk.
It's a really important point
that I want to drive home today.
So let's look specifically at
subscriptions for a little
while.
These scenarios have applied to
all in-app purchase types.
Now let's really talk about
maintaining subscription state
and particularly using that
service side flow.
So in this example, again, we
have an updated transactions
call being given to the user's
device.
And the user can read in that
binary receipt data into memory
on the user's device.
They send that information up to
your server.
Now this time, we're going to do
a little bit of a different
technique.
This is going to be a bit more
of a real world scenario here.
We're going to hold onto a copy
of the binary receipt data on
your server here and at the same
time, we'll send a copy of that
data over to the App Store to
achieve the technique that we
saw before.
So this will respond with the
latest copy of the receipt and
we can do that same technique of
finishing a transaction and
updating content across devices.
Now in this example, we're
dealing with an auto renewable
subscription.
So let's say that the user goes
offline for a bit and stops
using your app for a few days
which is a shocking thought, I
know.
But it can happen and if it does
happen and then the user happens
to have their subscription
renewed in the background during
this process.
The credit card's charged.
So a new transaction's taken
place somewhere.
And you don't know about it yet.
So the user jumps on, I don't
know your website.
And at this point, your server
doesn't have any new information
about the transaction that's
taken place in the background.
So in order for you to know this
information from your service
point of view, remember we're
holding on to that binary
receipt data on the server.
You can treat that data just
like a token.
And you can actually send it
back over to the App Store here
by that same request.
And as I mentioned before, not
only does this include the
decoded receipt data, this is
actually the latest copy of the
application receipt.
So this is latest copy is going
to contain any new transactions
that have occurred in the
background.
So you can find out about that
transaction that's occurred and
accordingly, give the user
access to your website again.
From there, you might want to
unlock content across multiple
devices.
But you do have to remember that
when the user does pick up that
original device again and come
back online, that will still
receive the transaction through
the updated transactions call.
And so you still need to handle
this and all the way through to
finishing the transaction.
So what we'd suggest is maybe
treat this as an opportunity to
update that binary receipt data
up on your server.
You're probably associating that
with a user's account for your
particular application.
And then remember to finish the
transaction back down on the
device again.
So even though your server
already knew about this
transaction, it's still
important to complete this flow
and finish that transaction
based on what I said before.
So for this technique, what
we're really doing here is we're
treating that receipt data much
like a token.
And we're using it to perform
multiple requests by storing it
on your server.
It's the same binary data that
can be used over and over again.
And it's quite useful for
propagating subscription state
across multiple devices and
platforms but still remember
that you have to process all the
updated transaction calls and
that means all the renewal
transactions that come through
for each billing period all the
way through to finishing the
transaction.
Now, as you can imagine, over
time if you're dealing with an
auto renewable subscription
particularly if it has a short
billing period, this transaction
receipt can grow quite large,
you know?
Every transaction that occurs
for a subscription appears on
the receipt.
So this document can grow quite
large over time.
And we've heard feedback that a
lot of you only real care about
the latest transaction.
You know I keep on saying you
check for the latest expiry
date.
Well a lot of you really only
care about that particular
transaction.
So we're enhancing this endpoint
today with a new query parameter
that you can include which is to
exclude old transactions from
this endpoint.
If you set this to true, the
verify receipt endpoint's just
going to respond with the latest
transaction for each
subscription.
So that's going to drastically
reduce the payload of that
request that's coming back from
the verified receipt endpoint.
And not only just save web
traffic but it's also just going
to mean saved processing time on
your server because you don't
have as many transactions to be
looping through.
Now this doesn't sound like a
lot but when you're dealing with
thousands or millions of users
like a lot of you do, this can
actually save quite a lot of
time.
So we think this is going to be
a great enhancement for those of
you're dealing with this
particular scenario.
Now this technique of status
polling --
[ Clapping ]
Thanks. This technique of status
polling really fits as a bit of
a server side tool.
So you can think about it as
sitting up here in this
particular diagram but you'll
notice I'm leaving that
particular flow of updating and
finishing transactions because
it's still important that you
handle all of these transactions
as you come through in a user's
device.
So let's stick on the subject of
subscriptions for a little bit.
Now we opened up auto renewable
subscriptions to many more
categories last year.
And we've seen great uptake and
heard great feedback from those
of you who have implemented
them.
And we've tried to offer
information about your users and
the behavior of them via the way
of things like iTunes Connect
reports.
You can find about how many
expirys you had and some of the
reasoning behind that but
there's been a lot of questions
that you've had that you haven't
been able to answer until now.
Particularly about individual
users.
So what are these questions?
Things like why did a particular
user's subscription expire?
Or will this user's subscription
be renewed as the end of this
billing period?
Will this user be downgraded at
the end of this billing period?
Have they elected to change that
subscription that they're
subscribed to?
Maybe they asked for a refund
from AppleCare?
What was the reason behind it?
Did they have a problem or is
just something that they wanted
to do?
Have they agreed to a price
increase that I've put in place?
Or will they just end their
subscription at the end of this
billing period?
How can I know this ahead of
time?
Or just simply what kind of
messaging do I need to tell my
user about their subscription?
How can I communicate to them
effectively and you know, with
things they need to know?
Now why are all these questions
really important?
Obviously to provide a great
experience for the user but can
you think about why these
questions are really important?
Well, it's because all these
questions are centered around
the user's renewal of their
subscription and so providing a
seamless experience in these
particularly scenarios, it's
really paramount to reducing
what we call subscription churn.
Subscription churn is just a
fancy way of saying losing
subscribers.
And the thing is when you lose
subscribers that's immediately
lost revenue for your business.
And not only is it lost revenue
for your business it's a lost
acquisition cost for each one of
those users as well.
Now we can think about
subscription churn as two
particular buckets.
We can talk about the
involuntary churn, which is the
case that the user hasn't even
elected to unsubscribe.
Maybe their credit card just
expired and it was an
involuntary action.
Now this is far too many users
fall into this particular
category.
There's also voluntary
subscription churn.
In the case that a user elected
to unsubscribe from your
application.
Maybe they asked for a refund
from AppleCare or they turned
off auto renew inside the
settings.
So we really want to empower you
with new tools to be able to
address both of these buckets
and we think we've got some
great new ways to do that today.
So we're announcing some new
tools to help reduce this
subscription churn.
Now to go through them, let's
walk through an example, again,
just to illustrate it.
So let's say a user here is
subscribed to your subscription
service.
It's a video subscription
service for this example.
You're using these techniques
with status polling like we said
before to poll the App Store to
find out the latest subscription
information about a user and
they're actively subscribed.
Everyone's happy.
Then the user goes offline for a
few days.
And during this particular time,
their subscription's renewed
again.
This is a similar example to
before, but, this time let's say
that the user's credit card's
expired.
And the App Store wasn't able to
charge them.
So there was some kind of
billing error that's happened
and the user comes along and
jumps on your website in order
to keep on watching videos.
Now at this point your server
does that status polling
technique that we talked about
but the App Store's going to
inform it that there's been no
transaction that's occurred
because there was a billing
error, right?
So your server does the only
thing that it can.
It informs the website that
subscription's actually expired
and the user, the poor user's
done nothing wrong.
Their credit card just expired.
They go over and begrudgingly
pull out their credit card.
They go and update their credit
card details in the App Store.
The App Store based on the new
credit card details is
successfully able to actually
charge that card.
So the user's gone to this
effort, everything looks good.
They jump back on your website
and then bah.
This happens.
Now at this point, your server
had no knowledge of the actual
transaction that's occurred.
The fact that that credit card
was able to be charged again and
so if this kind of thing happens
to you as a user, go to all that
effort.
You update your credit card
details and then you even see
money being taken off your
credit card and then you don't
get an immediate update of your
subscription state, you probably
just unsubscribe or you ask for
a refund straight away.
Now this happens far too
frequently.
So to address that today we're
introducing new server-to-server
notifications from the App
Store.
[ Clapping ]
So let's look at how that
scenario plays out now.
The user receives this
information that's something
happened.
There's been a billing error.
They go over and they update
their credit card details.
Now this time with the new
notifications, as soon as the
App Store is able to charge that
credit card it sends a
notification over to your server
with the latest transaction
that's occurred.
And you can use the payload of
that transaction to unblock the
user immediately and give them
access to using that website and
you've got happy users.
That's great.
So this is going to be awesome
for those of you who are dealing
with subscriptions on the server
side.
This is what it looks like in
practice.
You've got a status url in
iTunes Connect that you can
enter.
That you can put url in for your
own server.
Your server does have to adhere
the app transport security
requirements but if it does, all
it is an http post that gets
sent to your server for key
status changes for
subscriptions.
Now what are these events that
we send them for.
It happens for any initial
purchase of a subscription.
If there's any subscription
cancellations by AppleCare.
So if a user gets a refund, you
get notified of that.
It happens for any subscription
downgrades.
So any time a user elects to
downgrade their subscription,
you can find out about that and
update their subscription state
on the server accordingly.
And also that example that we
just saw, when there's a
successful renewal or a
re-purchase for an expired
subscription so that you can
unblock those users immediately
and give them access to their
subscription.
Now the payload of the
notification includes the latest
transaction for the actual
transaction in question that's
taken place that you've missed
out on.
So when you're doing this it
means that you don't need to
polling the verify receipt
nearly as often as you used to.
You still might need to call
verify receipt using that
polling but you can be a bit
smarter about when you do it.
Maybe an App Store notification
wasn't able to reach your
server.
So you still need to maybe use
this to actually retrieve and
poll information about the
subscription state but as I
said, you can a bit smarter
about when you do it.
Maybe you want to do it the day
before or the day of a user's
expiry instead of having to do
it every five minutes.
So these are coming later this
year and we think it's going to
drastically improve and reduce
that subscription churn that you
might be seeing.
So let's bring up these
questions again that I asked
just before.
The new notifications is going
to do a great job of reducing
subscription churn.
You know via that technique that
we just saw but there's a lot of
information here that we still
don't have answers for
particularly about users before
they've expired.
So in order to give you access
to this specific information,
today we're announcing new
fields in the verify receipt
endpoint.
Now these new fields are going
to provide you with the
information specifically about
users along these key
subscription events.
So if they turn off auto renew
in the settings, you can now
know this ahead of time that
they've elected to not be
subscribed at the end of this
billing period or maybe they
cancel a receipt or refund at
the end and they won't have
their subscription continuing.
So you can act on this
information now ahead of time
and make key business decisions
about this information.
So let's look at the new fields
that we're including.
So this is that same request,
the verify receipt endpoint.
We're including now an auto
renew status.
So when a user elects to turn
off auto renew for a
subscription, you can find this
out now ahead of time before
they've actually expired their
subscription.
We're including an auto renew
preference.
So if a user elects to downgrade
or change their subscription
preference, you can now know how
they're going to have -- what's
going to happen at the end of
that particular billing period.
We're including a price consent
status.
So if you're rolling a price
increase to a bunch of users,
now you can find out that I
don't know let's look at an
example.
Maybe 80% of your users haven't
agreed to a price increase and
they're actually going to be
unsubscribed at the end of the
billing period.
Previously you didn't know how
many users were going to be
rolled off.
So you can make key business
decisions based off that now.
Maybe you'll decide to not go
ahead with the price increase
based on the fact that you're
going to lose too many
subscribers.
We're including a subscription
billing retry flag.
So if a user falls into the
category of having some kind of
billing error like we saw before
and App Store is trying to
recharge their credit card to
get a successful transaction,
you can see if a user's in that
window.
And we'll see a couple of
examples about how to use these
in just a moment.
An expiration intent.
So why a user actually expired.
Was it because of a billing
error or some other reason?
You can now find this
information out about a user.
We're also including an
cancellation reason.
So previously if a user got a
refund from AppleCare, you were
going to kind of blind as to why
that was the case.
Now you can know if the user had
a problem with your app or an
in-app purchase or if it was
some personal reason the user
had in order to get a refund.
So let's look at a couple of
examples about how you can
actually use these fields in
order to address the
subscription turn that we talked
about.
Firstly, let's address
involuntary expiration.
So this is the case that a user
hasn't even elected to
unsubscribe.
So we think there's a lot we can
do to address involuntary
expiration.
And so we're going to do what we
can on our end to address this.
And that includes expanding that
retry window for billing retry
to up to 60 days now.
So previously, we would only try
for a period of a few hours to
recharge a credit card if there
was any kind of issues.
Now we're expanding that right
out to be up to 60 days.
We think that's going to catch a
lot of unsubscribes that occur.
On your end, there's a couple of
things that you can do to
address these scenarios.
You can use that expiration
intent field and the
subscription retry flag to do a
few key things.
Now if there's anything that you
can get from this talk, let it
be these three points because if
you can go ahead and implement
these things that I'm about to
outline, you'll drastically
reduce your involuntary
subscription turn.
So firstly, you can use these
two fields to provide messaging
to your user.
If you see that they've had a
billing error, you can now tell
them to go ahead and update
their billing info in the app
store.
Number 2, you can offer a
downgraded or temporary
experience to users who are in
this retry window.
So if you see that they're in
billing retry window, maybe you
give them access to browse your
catalog or videos but you don't
let them watch them.
So give them some kind of
temporary experience in the
middle there.
And number three, use these new
server notifications.
Use the verify receipt endpoint
or any other technique to
unblock users as soon as their
subscription renews.
Now these sound like pretty
obvious examples but if you can
do these three things, there's a
lot of involuntary expiration
that you will save because of
these three things.
So there's some things you can
do for the voluntary case as
well.
So when a user has actually
voluntarily elected to
unsubscribe from your app, you
can use this information to help
you here as well.
There's that expiration intent
field that we're including now
and you can use this as a way to
offer messaging to those
particular users.
So let's say that a user
canceled.
You can maybe think well, let's
apply some kind of win back.
Maybe you rolled out a price
increase and the user expired
because they didn't consent to
it.
Well now you can offer maybe an
attractive downgrade option
because you know that it was
really about the price
difference that caused the user
to unsubscribe.
So you can see how you can use
just in these couple of
examples, these fields to now,
you know, make key business
decisions and how you interact
with your users and save
subscription churn.
These new fields are arriving
later this year along with the
server notifications and we
think this is going to give a
much better experience for all
users for your subscriptions and
for you developing it as well.
[ Clapping ]
They fit in this diagram as
another set of tools that you
can use for server side
subscription management
alongside the status polling
that we talked about.
But of course, you still need to
be relying on this flow of
updating and finishing
transactions on a user's device.
So while we're talking about
subscriptions, I just want to
touch on free trials for a
moment.
Free trial is when a user can
begin a subscription without
actually paying for anything.
And they are not billed until
the free trial period is
actually over.
So previously, we had this
pretty convoluted looking table
and you'd have an associated
free trial duration for a
subscription length.
And you had to choose which
trials you could offer based on
the subscription length that you
were offering users.
Now we made some changes
recently to make this much
simpler.
So you can now have any
subscription length available
for any free trial duration.
So we think is a much better
improvement and this includes
two new free trial durations as
well, which is the three-day
trial and the two-week trial.
These are two new trial
durations that you can offer to
your users.
So that's a bit about
maintaining subscription state
and talking about managing auto
renewable subscriptions in the
server.
I'd like to touch now on
developing in the sandbox
environment.
So how you can use these
technologies while you're
developing.
So what is the sandbox?
Well it's not to be confused
with the sandbox on your
application, on a user's device
that guards access to
application resources.
This particular sandbox is the
test environment that we offer
for you to test out in-app
purchases in.
And we select it based on the
certificate that's actually used
to sign your application.
It's how StoreKit knows whether
to be in a sandbox mode or not.
So if you build and run your app
from Xcode [phonetic].
It's signed using your developer
certificate and StoreKit knows
that it needs to be talking to
the sandbox environment.
Of course, if you distribute it
using the App Store, well
StoreKit knows that it needs to
talk to the production
environment based on the
certificate used to sign your
app.
And how do you know when you're
actually working with app which
environment you're in?
When you make your in-app
purchase inside your
application, you get this
payment sheet that we saw in
this morning's session.
And we have this indication here
that you're in sandbox mode.
So this is going to inform you
that the payment that's about to
take place is actually a sandbox
payment and no real money is
going to be changing hands.
So the key differences between
the sandbox and the production
environment, well the biggest
one, of course, is that there's
no real money being changed
hands here.
There's no actual charge
happening.
So you don't need to be charging
your personal card 10-cent
transactions all the time.
There's a different endpoint as
well when it comes to
server-to-server validation.
We provide a different url for
that verify receipt endpoint.
And you can also request expired
and revoked certificates in the
sandbox environment to be able
to handle them a little
differently.
The other thing that is
different is a time contraction
for auto renewable
subscriptions.
So instead of having to wait a
full year for a subscription to
renew to be able to test out
that scenario, we can track
these time intervals.
So the rule of thumb is that one
hour of time in the sandbox
world equals one year of time in
the real world.
And this is how those relate for
the various different
subscription durations.
The other thing that we do when
you're operating in a sandbox
environment is that if you are
subscribed to an auto renewable
subscription, we only renew it
after six times per eight-hour
window.
Then we let it expire.
So you can handle the case where
a user has actually let their
subscription lapse and you can
handle that in your application
accordingly.
When it comes to setting up this
test environment, it's done
through iTunes Connect.
You create test users in iTunes
Connect and you can just those
in-app purchase products that
you've already got for sale and
then you just build and sign
your app using XCode.
So it's built and signed using
the developer certificate.
And you just go ahead and buy
products in your application.
And when you're prompted to sign
in, you'll be able to sign in
using that test user that you
made in iTunes Connect.
One note if you are developing
for the Mac, you may need to
launch your app once from Finder
just in order to make sure that
the receipt gets fetched.
This is because that exit code
that we mentioned earlier on in
the talk where you exit 173 on a
Mac, well XCode catches that if
you're building and running
straight from XCode the first
time.
You need to make sure that you
launch the app once that binary
from Finder so that StoreKit can
catch that exit code and handle
it appropriately.
In terms of using the sandbox
from the server, I mentioned
that we have a different
endpoint for the verify receipt
url.
This is what it looks like in
the development environment.
You'll probably have your
developer signed app probably
talking to your test server and
that test server can talk to the
App Store sandbox by the
different url.
In production, you'll have
something like this.
Your production app will talk to
your production server and that
can talk to the production App
Store server but there is one
particularly case where there's
a bit of a mismatch.
And that's when your app is in
app review.
And why is it a mismatch?
It's because the app review team
actually uses a sandbox user to
be able to test your in-app
purchases.
So this is what that looks like.
You have your production signed
app talking to your production
server but you need to be able
to verify transactions for a
sandbox user just to get through
the app review scenario.
So how do you handle this
particular mismatch?
Well we have a way of doing
this.
Firstly, when you're in the
production environment try the
production App Store url first.
Now if the receipt is for the
sandbox, you'll receive a
specific error code, 21 double 0
7.
That's an indication that you
need to then to try against the
App Store sandbox instead.
So you can leave that in your
production environment and this
will just mean that your app is
able to sail through app review
without any problems in this
regard.
When it comes to the new server
to server notifications, this is
handled slightly differently.
So we don't actually have a
separate url in iTunes Connect
for a sandbox -- or for your own
test server.
We handle this sandboxing by
parameter in the actual payload
of the notification.
So there's an environment key
that you can use that'll tell
you whether or not the
notification is for a sandbox
subscription or whether it's for
a production one.
So that's a bit about developing
now in a sandbox.
So we touched on a few things
today.
There's been a lot of
information.
Let's just go through again what
we talked about.
We talked about receipt
validation in detail.
How to do this on a user's
device and how to check that
document for authenticity and
read out transactions from it.
We talked about maintaining a
subscription state across a
server environment.
How to update devices and act on
that verify receipt endpoint.
We have new notifications that
we're introducing that's going
to unblock and save a lot of
that involuntary subscription
churn.
Provide a much better experience
for your users.
We're also introducing those new
receipt fields.
So you can make key decisions
based on business information
about your users and now message
them much more directly.
Remember those three easy steps
to retain subscribers.
Three steps to success.
So if you do these three things,
this will, I kid you not, it'll
save you a ton of involuntary
subscription churns.
So please go ahead and do these
when these fields come out later
this year.
And finally we talked about
sandbox development.
Being able to use these
technologies in the sandbox
environment.
So for more information on this
session and to see the slides
and follow any links, this is
session 305.
You can check it out on the
developer website.
We did have some related
sessions earlier this week.
We're kind of at the end of the
week now.
But we are still here in the
labs all afternoon this
afternoon.
So we have engineers from both
the client and from the service
side from all across the
organization down in the
StoreKit labs, both this
afternoon and tomorrow
afternoon.
So please come and say hi and
bombard us with questions.
And we're happy to help you out
and talk about how you're
architecting your solutions.
But until then, thanks for
coming today.
Thanks for your time.
Enjoy your afternoon.
[ Clapping ]