[ Applause ]
>> Hello. Good afternoon.
Welcome. My name's Kieron
Seenya.
I'm an Xcode engineer at Apple.
I'm really excited to share with
you some of the new source
control features of Xcode 9.
In fact, I'm so excited about it
it's now a first class citizen
of Xcode.
Today you're going to learn
about some of the great concepts
of SCM and how they fit in with
Xcode 9.
So let's get started.
So I've got a lot of work to get
done today.
The first thing I need to do is
to get my project and to do that
I need to clone it.
Next up I'm going to review some
recent changes that happened in
the project.
So I'm going to look at some
commits.
After that I've got some feature
work I need to do.
So I'm going to create a branch
to make sure my changes aren't
affecting the rest of my team.
And then I'm going to release my
app to the App Store.
So I'll create a tag to make
sure I know when that happened.
The first thing I need to do
though is clone the project.
So let's take a look at what
that is, if you're unfamiliar.
In most cases you're going to
have a single, centralized copy
of your source code.
This is known as a remote
repository.
And this stores all the history
of your projects and all the
changes that make up that
history.
And just like it sounds, cloning
creates an exact copy of all the
code and brings it down onto
your MacBook and you can start
working.
So how does this fit into Xcode
9?
Well, with your GitHub account
connected we've introduced an
entirely new clone workflow.
When you've added your GitHub
account you'll get a list of
your personal repositories.
You'll also get a list of the
starred ones and all of those
belonging to your organization.
And it is really easy to find
what you're looking for from
here.
Immediately I can see all of my
repositories.
There's also a detail pane at
the bottom.
So I can see more information
about those repositories.
And from here I can even star an
interesting repository.
So I can come back to it later.
There's full search capability
in here.
So using the address bar at the
top, I can enter some search
criteria and search across
GitHub.
This saves you having to jump to
GitHub to find the repository
you're looking for.
So I go ahead and select this
TOTP app, but I can also clone
any other repository that's not
part of GitHub by just entering
the URL of it in that address
bar there.
So when I've found what I'm
looking for I hit the "clone"
button and it asks me where I
want to save it.
I choose here, click clone, and
it just goes ahead and clones
it.
It's that simple.
Now in the mornings when I'm
sipping my cup of earl gray I
need to get access to my
repository.
I don't want to flip back to
Xcodes to do that.
I don't want to have to search
for it.
So now we work closely with
GitHub so you can clone your
Xcode projects right from
github.com.
You find the repo you're looking
for, hit the clone or download
button, and here you'll see an
"open in Xcode" button.
It's really easy.
It's really handy.
[ Applause ]
So that's cloning in Xcode 9.
So next up I want to review some
changes that have happened
recently.
So I'm going to look at some
commits.
Now if you're unfamiliar let's
take a look at this.
And this star represents a
single commit.
It is a snapshot of all the
changes that have happened in my
project at that point in time.
Committing changes to a project
is something you're probably
going to do many times a day and
each commit adds history to your
project.
And this history's invaluable
for keeping track of your code
base, knowing who is changing
what and why.
Now every commit has an author.
This lets you know who to blame.
It also has a description so you
know why that change happened.
There's also a date just to let
you know when it happened.
And finally something called a
shar, which is the unique
identifier for that commit.
It lets you reference it later
on if you need to.
So, as this information, along
with the changes captured by the
commit, this makes up the rich
history of your project.
So how does this fit into Xcode
9?
Well, we can see here.
In Xcode 9 there's entirely new
feature set for source control
allowing you to see your
history.
On the left hand side we've
introduced an entirely new
navigator.
This'll list the working copies
that are part of your project.
When you select one of those
working copies you'll get this
new history view.
This lists all of your commits
and we've been using it in
Xcode's code base.
We have around a quarter of a
million commits and we can
scroll through really smoothly.
It's really great.
For each of these entries there
is those details you saw before;
the author, the description.
This is really useful
information, but with your
GitHub account connected we now
go and get your avatar.
So you can put a face to the
name or the name to the face.
So let's say I'm looking for a
specific commit, something I
know my colleague Eric [assumed
spelling] committed recently and
I'm not entirely sure what I'm
looking for.
So we can now search by token.
So here I specify I'm looking
for Eric.
Now that gives me a big list of
commits.
I still need to narrow it down a
bit further.
So let's find out what happened
the last day because I know it
was that recent.
So I use this scope bar and
search for the last 24 hours.
I still got four results.
I'm a bit lazy.
I don't want to read through the
commit messages.
So I know it has something to do
with cofeeing.
[laughing] So it narrows the
result down to that individual
result, and that's the one I was
looking for.
And these search results come
back instantly.
It's really fast.
You've got to try it out.
So that's commit in Xcode 9.
So now that I've cloned my
project and I've reviewed commit
it's time I worked on something
that's a bit risky maybe.
To do that I want to create a
branch and this will help
isolate my changes from the rest
of the team's so they don't get
affected.
So let's go back to this commit
docs we saw earlier.
Now my master branch is in
pretty good shape.
Everything's stable.
My bot's passing their unit
test.
So I'm going to go ahead and
create a branch from there.
So it goes to new navigator.
I hit "new branch" from master
and Xcode goes ahead and just
creates it.
Now my new branch is going to be
pushed to the top of the list
and marked as "current."
This lets me know what I'm
currently working on.
It's really easy to see.
And you can see in this diagram
here; history has now diverged.
This means my commit is no
longer part of master.
So my changes aren't going to
affect my team and they're going
to carry on committing and
they'll carry on committing and
it won't affect me.
And as I carry on committing
it's not going to affect them.
And this is a good place to be
when you're working on some
risky work.
So now my tests are passing on
my feature branch and I want to
land those changes back into the
master branch.
So to do that I go to the new
source control navigator, I hit
the merge button and my changes
have landed in.
The thing is though, those
changes haven't been published
to my service so the rest of the
team can't see them.
So how does this tie in with
Xcode's new navigator?
Well, let's go back to that
cloud illustration that we saw
earlier.
And as I make changes and as
others make changes we need to
synchronize those changes.
And to do that you can pull
changes from the remote
repository.
And when I've made my changes
I'll go ahead and push those.
And this is really useful when
you're working in a team
environment because you can
carry on pushing and pulling to
make sure you have each other's
changes.
So after I've merged and I need
to push those changes I have
three commits I need to push and
Xcode will automatically display
these in the new navigator so I
know my team can't see them.
And in Xcode 9 we automatically
fetch from your remote
repositories and this lets you
know if your team have been
making changes that you need to
pull.
And you'll see it with these up
and down arrows.
This is good to know because you
can't go ahead and push until
you've pulled their changes in.
So that's branching in Xcode 9.
So now I'm ready to release a
beta version of my app.
The tests are passing, I've
merged all my work into master.
So let's go back to those docs
that we saw earlier.
At specific points of time in
your project's history you'll
want to create a tag.
This lets you know all of the
changes that made it up until
that point in time.
It's a good idea to do this when
you release your app to the App
Store for example.
So you -- to help you track what
changes were made.
So we'll continue to do this and
here I'm creating my Beta 4 tag
and you'll continue to do this
as you release more versions of
your app to the App Store.
So now on Xcode 9 we have full
tagging support.
You can go to the new history
view, click on one of your
commits, and select "tag," and
you'll see this new pane to
create your tag.
Now based on the naming
conventions of your tag, by
using forward slashes, Xcode
will automatically group your
tags to help organize them
easier.
This makes it easier to look
them up later and in this case
we're going to create a beta's
group.
And when you create your tag it
will immediately appear in the
new history view so you can see
that point in time.
If we flip open the "tags"
folder you'll see those tags.
By selecting the Beta 4 tag here
I see only the history of that
tag.
And you might wonder; why is
that useful?
To see just the history of that
tag?
Well, it lets you find precisely
what changes and features were
introduced in a particular
version of your app.
And by using the new searching
and filtering capabilities you
can find them easier.
So I've been told there was a
bug introduced and it was in
Beta 3.
So I go to the new navigator and
I select the Beta 3 tag and I
see here that only two changes
were made since the last Beta.
One was by Eric; one was by me.
And this top one here, it's
looking you know particularly
sketchy and I'm not sure if it's
something to do with the author.
At this point they cease to
become avatars and instead
become mugshots.
So I select this guy and I
double click on him and I see
this new view.
Now you might be familiar with
this view in previous versions
of Xcode.
It used to display as a sheet.
The problem with that though was
it blocked your workflow.
With this you can open a new
tab, carry on working as usual.
And with the rich assistance
support, which Eric's going to
show us later, we'll see how
easy it is to review your
changes in your code.
So here we can see there's a
force [inaudible] that I wrote,
which can crash the app of
course.
This new editor is really great
for other reasons too.
For example there's full jumper
support so you can navigate your
files really quickly.
You can collapse that list of
files for more screen space as
well.
And at the bottom you have that
detail pane, just so you know
you're looking at the right
commit.
So that's the all new tagging
experience in Xcode 9.
So combining the new, current
experience the new source
control navigator, and the great
new workflows around branching
and tags makes it easier than
ever to get real work done with
source control and Xcode 9.
So with that I'd like to
introduce Eric [inaudible] to
the stage to show us some of
these new features.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you very much, Kieran.
So as he said, I'm going to show
you some of the new features of
Xcode 9 and source control.
So I've just set up this machine
and I've installed Xcode 9 on
it, but I don't have any of my
projects yet.
I want to clone them from GitHub
and in order to do that I'm
going to need to sign into my
GitHub account.
So I'll just go to Xcode's
preferences and to the
"accounts" pane.
And here we see of course I have
no accounts.
So if I just go to the plus
button in the lower left I get
an option to add any account
that Xcode supports, such as my
Apple ID for doing provisioning
and signing, Xcode Server for
continuous integration, or
GitHub for source control.
And I want to take a moment here
and point out that we also
support GitHub Enterprise.
So if your company uses a GitHub
Enterprise server all the
features that we're showing you
that work with GitHub work just
as well with GitHub Enterprise
on your own company's server.
But for today, I'm just going to
use github.com.
Great, so I'm going to sign in
and copy my password.
Make sure that goes in the
password field.
[laughs] And I use two factor
authentication.
And Xcode 9 supports two factor
authentication with GitHub.
This is a great way to secure
your account and make sure that
only you can access your source
code.
Great! So I've signed into Xcode
-- or into GitHub in Xcode and
we see that Xcode has
automatically detected my SSH
keys.
So I can clone using either
HTTPS or SSH, whichever I
prefer.
I'm going to leave it set to
HTTPS, but before I go clone
anything let me just go to my
source control preferences and
make sure everything is set up
exactly the way I want.
So here if I go to source
control I see that I have source
control enabled and if I go
specifically to the "get"
settings we see that new in
Xcode 9 you can now configure
your "get author" and your
"globally ignored" files right
in Xcode.
So your get author, your user
name, and email are what people
will see when you make commits.
So they'll know who to go to
when they find a bug on that
line.
So I think I'm all set up here.
So let's go back to the welcome
window.
And to get to that new clone
window we saw earlier I just go
straight to "clone an existing
project" right from the welcome
window and immediately it
populates with a list of
projects that I might be
interested in.
Now this is all the projects
that I own and maintain on
GitHub as well as any projects
that I've starred on GitHub and
indicated that I have some
interest in.
Additionally, if I'm a member of
any organization that has
repositories on GitHub, such as
the Apple organization here, I
can see those repositories as
well.
Now if this isn't what I'm
looking for I can just search.
So Kieran was telling me earlier
that I should really check out
research kit.
Research kit is Apple's open
source framework for creating
medical research applications
and it's available on GitHub.
So I'll just search research kit
and I'll put that into the
search field and sure enough
what comes back is research kit.
And if I'm not sure this is the
one I'm looking for I get a
little bit more information in
the detail view.
So if we zoom in on that we see
I get the full name and if I
click that I can go right to the
GitHub page for it.
But usually everything I need's
right here.
I get the description, the
language, the number of people
who have forked the project, how
many people have starred the
project, and the read me for the
project.
So if I click the read me you
get the read me file that this
project provides on GitHub and
usually this has information
like a bit more about the
project or how to get started
with it and even some sample
code.
And one of the great things is
since a lot of these are written
in markdown, when you do clone a
project they work great in
Xcode's new enhanced markdown
support in our source editor.
So that is the one I want so
I'll go ahead and star it.
And so right in Xcode when I
click the star button we see the
star count incremented because
I'm now starring this
repository.
And if I clear out my search we
see that sure enough, right in
my default view I see research
kit now.
So every machine I sign into I
can easily get back to research
kit if I want to check that out
a little bit later.
But today I want to check out
that TOTP app.
So TOTP is a onetime password
generator.
It's actually the app you saw me
use a little bit earlier to sign
in to GitHub.
So I'll just clone that and
right away I can save it to my
documents folder.
And that's it.
It's super simple in Xcode 9 to
clone projects from GitHub.
There's no more off prompts or
any choices you have to make
once you've selected a project.
And immediately upon cloning
Xcode will open the project and
you get a very familiar view.
You get your project navigator
and your editor area.
And if we look over in the left,
sure enough next to the project
navigator we see the new source
control navigator.
So this automatically gets
populated with every working
copy that makes up your project.
In this case I only have one;
the TOTP working copy.
And I see the one branch that I
automatically cloned when I
cloned from GitHub Master.
If I select "master" I instantly
get the full history of the
project.
And here we see all the commits
that make up this project and
make it what it is.
Now Kieran was showing something
a little bit earlier that looked
like a bug and we should
probably fix that before we move
on.
So I need to find that.
So I saw that it was made by
Kieran.
So I'll just say, "author;
Kieran."
And here's all the commits
Kieran's made.
And I think it had something to
do with the generator, if I saw
correctly.
So I think it was something
where in the message he said,
"Generator."
Generator -- sorry.
Ah, that's the one.
And if I select it I get a lot
of extra information about that
commit.
So in addition to a new source
control navigator, a new source
control history view, we also
have a new source control
inspector.
And in the inspector, when I
select a commit I get additional
information about that commit
such as the full shaw, the exact
commit date and time, the
author, as well as the full
commit message.
I can also see the files that
were modified in that commit.
And if I want to review the
changes made to any file in that
commit I can click this arrow
and go straight to them.
But as Kieran mentioned earlier,
there's an even better way than
just double clicking or clicking
this arrow to get to the dif,
and that's to make use of
Xcode's assistant editor.
So many of you may be familiar
with Xcode's assistant editor,
but probably have seen it mostly
on the right.
Now I want a little bit of extra
horizontal space to view dif sen
so if I click and hold on the
"assistant editor" button I can
select to have the assistant
editor on the bottom.
And when it opens it
automatically shows the commit
details for the commit I have
selected above.
So this is great.
I can go right to the change
that Kieran made and sure
enough, there it is.
Uh, well we should probably fix
that.
While I'm here, let me just show
you -- so even if I want to look
at some other commits they show
up.
The second I click them I get
all the files and all the
changes made in those commits.
So let's close the assistant
editor and go over to the app
delegate, where I think that
change was that broke it.
Ah, here it is.
So I'll just go ahead and fix
that.
Great. I love magical code
completion that fixes bugs.
And I would normally just commit
this right onto master and be
done with it, but I think this
change should use -- could use a
little bit more testing to make
sure we've actually fixed this
bug because I want to be sure.
So if we go back to the source
control navigator and I select
my master branch and control
click it I can create a new
branch from master.
And this new branch I'll just
call "fix" because I don't have
any good names.
[laughs] So this now
automatically got checked out by
Xcode and all my uncommitted
changes are now sitting on top
of the fix branch.
So with that I'm ready to
commit.
And to do that I just go to
source control and select
"commit" and make sure my dif is
correct.
Let's see, "fixes a crash."
Great.
So now that is one of those
commits that make up the history
of my project.
And I can verify that if I go to
the "fix" branch in the source
control navigator.
Here we see that brand new
commit I just created today.
Now one of the things that I
often find when I'm making
branches and committing things
is that I forget what commits
are on what branches and I
easily lose track of them and
it's really annoying to have to
figure out whether or not a
commit you've made landed in the
right branch.
Well Xcode 9 has a great way to
figure that out.
If I select my commit and zoom
in here on the inspector we see
that there's a branches area.
And right now the only branches
listed for that commit is "fix."
So this particular commit is
only in the fix branch.
If I go back and look at an
older commit, now if we look at
it this commit is a bit older
and was before I branched.
So it's actually in both the
"fix" branch and the master
branch.
So this is a great way to figure
out exactly where your commits
are and know exactly what you're
shipping to your customers.
Now normally I create an Xcode
server bot to integrate this and
some unit tests and all that,
but since I just got a thousand
of my closest friends here to
code review my change I'm going
to just merge it into master.
So again, if I control click
"master" in the navigator I can
merge from "fix" into "master"
and in one step I have merged my
fix into master and switched to
the master branch super easily
from the source control
navigator.
And sure enough, the history
view updates.
[ Applause ]
This review updates and I can
see that my fix is now on the
master branch as well as "fix."
And if we zoom in over here, if
I need to confirm that indeed
this change made it to master,
the master branch is listed.
Now this was a crash that was
affecting a lot of our users so
I want to make sure we get this
app out quickly.
So I'm going to tag it.
And if I control click on a
commit we see that there's a
bunch of actions I can do on a
commit as well.
So just like you can do actions
on a branch in Xcode 9, you can
do particular actions on a
commit such as checking out or
branching even from an older
point in time.
But today I'm going to tag this
commit so that we know which one
we want to release as Version
1.2.
So I'll select "tag" and select
"releases/v1.2" and create that
tag.
And there we go.
As soon as I do that the tag is
automatically upended to that
commit.
And I can verify that in the
"tags" folder of the source
control navigator.
And because I've been using
slashes and names to prefix all
my tags we see Xcode creates an
automatic hierarchy for me in
the navigator, making it super
easy to organize my project.
So we'll get that onto the App
Store to get rid of those one
star reviews from all that
crashing.
But while Kieran was up here I
had another really cool idea
that I was just thinking about.
So I'm going to create a new
project.
So let's open up Xcode and let's
get started with a new Xcode
project.
And you know what I was thinking
would be really fun is if we
made some SCM centric stickers
for iOS.
So I'm going to make a sticker
pack app.
So I'll just select that and
call it "SCM Stickers."
Now every time you create a new
project in Xcode, Xcode always
offers you the option to create
a git repository right then and
there as you create the project.
Now personally I always do this,
even if I think it's just a
throwaway project or I'm testing
some code because you never know
how long you're going to keep
working on the same thing and
this way you always have history
from the very beginning of time
for your project.
So let's create that git
repository on my Mac.
And now I have my sticker app.
If we go to the source control
navigator from this app we see
that I have a working copy that
was automatically created by
Xcode and it has one branch
master which is current.
And it has the initial commit,
which is essentially just all
the template stuff from Xcode.
So now it's time to put my
stickers into my app.
So let's go over to the project
navigator and select the
"stickers" folder.
And I already have a few
stickers here that I like.
I've got one of a "tag" icon and
I've got a few emoji peeking out
from a safe.
That says "SCM."
So let's put those all into my
sticker pack and go to "commit."
So I'll go ahead and commit all
those stickers.
And now they're all part of my
history.
And if I look at my branch I
have two commits.
But if I open the "remotes"
folder I don't have a remote.
In fact this project only exists
locally.
So while git is tracking history
for my project, if I want to
check it out on another machine,
share it with somebody else, or
if I lose this machine, this is
the only copy.
So I need to make sure that I
can put it somewhere where it's
safe and easy to share with
other people.
And for that I'm going to use
GitHub again.
So if I control click on the
"remotes" folder I see that one
of the options is that I can now
create the SCM stickers remote
right on GitHub.
And if I select that a new sheet
comes down and asks me all the
things I want to set up about my
project on GitHub.
I get to choose what account
that I'm going to use.
So I'll use mine.
And I can select the owner.
So if you're a member of
organizations and have
permission to create
repositories for them you can
actually create repositories for
your organizations.
And then I get to select a name
for my project and by default
it'll just pick the project
name; "SCM Stickers."
If we look closely we see that
the owner name and repository
name combine to form the URL
where you'll be able to check
this out on the World Wide Web.
Now let's give it a little bit
of a description.
And while I would say check it
out on the World Wide Web, but I
can actually make it private so
that no one but me can see it
and commit to it because I don't
think the world's quite ready
for these yet.
If I go ahead and select
"create" that project will get
created on GitHub under my
account and all my changes will
get pushed right up to the
server.
Ah, I forgot one of the stickers
and it's my favorite one!
Let's go back to the project
navigator and select "stickers."
And I don't know if you know
this, but GitHub's logo is
actually an octo-cat.
Well, I thought I'd take my --
try my hand at making my own
octo-cat.
And so let's add that as one of
the stickers.
And let's go ahead and go commit
that.
Make sure that that gets up on
the GitHub too.
Octo-cat. Now, since I now have
a remote I can go ahead and push
all my changes right up to
GitHub where they're safe and
secure as I commit to skip a
whole bunch of extra steps of
having to do it later.
And this way I don't end up
behind from my remote branch.
So I'll just go ahead and commit
and push those files and that
sticker now will also be up on
GitHub.
If I go to my repository -- or
sorry -- my source control
navigator again and look at my
master branch it now has three
commits and I see that the
remote's origin master branch is
also at the same place.
If I want to be even further
sure that this commit made it up
onto GitHub or I wanted to look
at it on GitHub I can just
control click the commit, and
like any other object in source
control and Xcode, such as a
branch or tag or remote, I can
view it on GitHub.
And if I select that Safari will
open up straight to that commit
on GitHub and I see my beautiful
octo-cat.
[ Applause ]
Now I want Kieran to be able to
check this out to, but I made it
private.
So let's go to "settings" and
add him as a collaborator.
And we've got to make sure we're
secure.
So let's add Kieran.
There he is.
So we'll add him as a
collaborator so now he can see
this private repo too.
And I want him to check it out
as soon as possible.
So I'm going to make it really
easy for him and I'm going to go
ahead and we see on GitHub the
"clone" -- or "download" button,
just like we showed earlier the
"open in Xcode" button is right
there and I can even select that
and just share that link with
him in mail.
Let's see here.
Let's send that to Kieran.
"Check out my stickers."
We'll send that to Kieran so he
can just click this link right
on his machine as soon as he
gets it, Xcode will open, clone
it, and he can have fun with my
octo-cat.
Great. So now before he does
check that out I want to bring
him back on stage to talk a
little bit more about source
control and Xcode.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> Awesome.
Thank you, Eric.
I'll be sure to check that out
on the World Wide Web later.
It's okay; I lived through the
'90s.
So Eric showed us how easy it is
to get started with source
control and Xcode.
By adding your GitHub account
you have quick access to all of
your repositories.
With the new source control
navigator we saw how easy it is
to manage your branches, tags,
and remotes.
And finally, we saw how easy it
is to create a new project on
GitHub and push all your code
up.
So for more information check
out session 405 on
developer.apple.com.
There are also some related
sessions you can take a look at.
You're very welcome.
Have a good rest of the week.
Thanks!
[ Applause ]