[ Applause ]
>> We love music at Apple.
As Tim said yesterday in the
keynote, it's a fundamental part
of our DNA.
My name is Tim, and I'm here
today to introduce you to
MusicKit, a way for you to
integrate streaming music with
Apple Music content.
With MusicKit, you're going to
get access to artists, albums
and songs, playlists, activities
and curators.
We also provide operations for
discovery, like search, and
charts, and if the user
authorizes your app,
personalized recommendations
that are tailored to the user's
taste or their activity.
MusicKit is two things; it's a
collection of client APIs in the
iOS SDK and a set of web
services that provide
personalized and cataloged
content.
I'll be talking about the web
services part, which we call
Apple Music API.
These are some of the topics
I'll be discussing.
I'll go a little into how to
format a request, how we
represent the content with
resources and relationships,
some detail about limits and
pagination.
My colleague Joel will give a
brief demo.
I'll touch on personalized
services; and finally, talk
about how to get access to the
Apple Music API.
No talk about a Web services API
would be complete without
talking about the URL structure.
Apple Music API only supports
the secure HTTPS scheme, and
it's hosted at
api.music.apple.com.
The first element in the URL
path is the version.
Current version is V1, and if we
make significant improvements or
backwards incompatible changes,
we'll bump the version.
The next part of the path is
cataloged, and this just
indicates that this is the Apple
Music streaming content catalog.
A note that not all content is
available in every area or
region of the world, and so we
introduced the concept of
Storefront in the path.
Storefront scopes the catalog to
the area region where content is
available so that you can
provide relevant and playable
music to your users.
The next part is the API.
This just indicates the resource
you'd like to request or the
operations you'd like to
perform.
And finally, we have a set of
parameters that you can use to
filter or expand the request.
Our API is localized.
We support many localizations,
but not all localizations are
supported in every Storefront.
We provide a mechanism for you
to get which Storefront supports
which localizations.
The API supports limits in
pagination, and I'll go into
some detail later in my
presentation about exactly how
that works.
And finally, every request to
Apple Music API requires a
developer token.
Representing data is an
important consideration for any
API.
We've taken our experience
building the Apple Music app to
give you an API that takes into
consideration ease of use,
flexibility, and performance.
Here, I have the first
representation of a resource,
which we call the identity form.
It includes an ID, a type of
thing that this is, and an href,
which indicates the location in
the catalog where you can find
this content.
This isn't very useful for
display.
That's why we have this type,
which is the attributes form.
This includes the identity and a
list of attributes that you can
use to display relevant
information about the content.
This includes things like
artwork and name and
description, and if the content
is playable, it will have an
attribute called play
parameters.
Finally, we have the default
form.
If you ask the Apple Music API
for a collection of things, this
is the default form that you'll
get.
It's the attributes and
relationship form.
This is all of the attributes
required for display plus
collections of content that are
related to this particular
resource.
It's a little bit about
relationships.
Here I have an album resource.
It has three relationships.
The first is a relationship to
tracks.
This is the songs or music
videos that are attached to this
album.
The second is artists, which, of
course, is the artist that
created the song or the album;
and genres.
Genres are just the category of
music that this album belongs
in.
Now, each of these relationships
is of a different type.
The first app for tracks is an
attributes included relation.
It means if you ask for this
album, it's going to return all
of its tracks with their
attributes included.
This means that if you ask for
an album, you could get all of
the data about the songs and its
attributes.
The second type, artist, is
identifiers only.
It means we only return the
identifier form, the location,
and the kind of thing, and where
you can find it in the catalog.
And finally, we have the omitted
by default.
This is not returned in the
default representation, although
the relationship still exists.
So, let's look at this in
practice.
Here, I have a URL to an album,
and you can see that in the
adjacent response tracks have
attributes omitted, and artists
are the identifier form.
So, what if I wanted to make a
single call and get the
attributes for an artist.
I'd simply add the career
parameter, include and specify
the name of the relationship,
which I would like to omit the
attributes for.
And you can see that here we
have omitted the attributes for
the artist, along with the
attribute form for the tracks.
You'll notice in this response
that we don't include genres.
So, how would you include the
attribute form of genres?
You'd simply add genres to the
include career parameter, and
you can see that genres will be
omitted in the attribute form.
So, that's a little bit about
resources and relationships.
I'm now going to talk about some
limits and pagination.
So, here are the requests for
the tracks resource for an
album.
This will give me the collection
of songs for this album.
This album happens to have 9.
If I wanted to limit the number
of tracks that I would get back,
I would simply add the limit
career parameter, and let's say
I wanted a page size of 2.
This would give me the first two
songs in this album, and then it
would give me a Next key that
indicates where the rest of
these tracks live.
If I follow this next link, I
will get the rest of the tracks
for this album, songs 3 through
9.
If I wanted to implement a page
size of 2, I would simply add,
again, limit equals 2.
It would give me songs 3 and 4.
Again, a Next reference, with a
URL to where the rest of the
data for this album lives.
So, what does this look like in
practice?
Here it is.
You can see that the Next
reference is a sibling of the
collection of data that comes
back for these tracks.
So, I've talked a little bit
about resources, the
relationships, and pagination.
Let's talk about an operation.
Most of our operations come back
as collections of resources
grouped by the type of thing
that they are.
For example, a search for Khalid
would bring back albums,
artists, songs, and playlists.
If I wanted to limit the type of
things that came back from a
search, I would simply add the
"types" career parameter and
specify the kind of thing that I
would like to come back.
Here, I'm asking for albums, and
when I call it, I'll just get a
collection of albums.
And now, I'd like to welcome my
colleague Joel onto the stage to
do a quick Playground demo of a
Search request.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Tim.
Hi, my name is Joel, and I'd
like to show you just how easy
it is to fetch content from
Apple Music to enrich your apps
in Swift.
To do that, I'd like to show you
how to fetch some content from
this catalog search endpoint,
and here we'll be searching for
albums from Khalid.
To do so, we'll simply start
building the URL for this search
request, using URL components,
and one important part of this
URL in the path is the inclusion
of the Storefront county code
corresponding to the user.
Then, you need to add a few
query parameters to this
request, and we'll do so by
using query items, and we'll
simply set the term to "Kahalid"
and type 2 albums.
Once you have that, you can
construct a fully formed URL,
and then a URL request with
that.
And then, you need to include an
HTTP header to this URL request,
which is the authorization
header, and this is useful to
authenticate your app with Apple
Music API.
Here, we'll be using the
developer token as a part of the
value of this HTTP header with
the "Bearer" prefix.
Next stop, we can load the data,
using URL session, and with this
raw JSON data, we'll simply use
the new JSON Decoder in Swift
4.0 to parse this data, and it
really makes it easy to convert
JSON data into strongly typed
Swift structures.
You can simply define a few
Swift structures that conform to
the codable protocol, and then
you can feed such structures to
the JSON decoder.
In this case, I'll be passing
the Catalog Search Results
struct to the JSON Decoder,
along with the Search data, and
then I can take a peek into the
results.
So, here, I'll be looking for
the first album in these
results, and let's take a look
at the attributes we get.
Sure enough, we get the American
Teen Album by Khalid, including
the other related attributes.
And as you can see, we also have
some information about the
artwork, and this comes with a
URL.
But if you really take a look at
this URL, it's more of a URL
format string because it allows
you to replace a width and
height token at the end of the
URL with the desired width and
height to match the user end
face in your app.
So, to fetch the artwork for
this album, I just created the
Helper method on this artwork
structure, and it's really
simple.
We'll just replace the width
token, w with the desired width
here, and then we'll do the same
for the height.
And because most artwork for
music content is perfectly
square, we'll simply use the
same width in height.
And with that, you have a fully
formed URL.
So, here, I just constructed a
URL for this album that has a
width of 1200 pixels, and let's
just take a look at what we get.
Here it is.
This is the album artwork for
this American Teen album by
Khalid.
So, this is how easy it is to
fetch content from Apple Music.
Now, I'd like to head it back to
Tim, and he'll tell you all
about personalized requests.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Joel.
So, I'm going to talk a little
bit about personalized requests
with the Apple Music API.
The URL structure is just a
little bit different.
After the Version, you'll see
that every personalized call
starts with me.
Here, I have a URL that will
give me the recently played
items for a user's account.
So, you'll also notice that the
Storefront part of the path is
missing.
That's because a user's account
is bound to the Storefront, so
they can only play content that
is available in the Storefront,
which their account is
legitimately available for.
So, what do you need to play?
What do you need to get
personalized data?
The user must have an Apple
Music subscription, and every
call to a personalized request
requires two things, the
developer token, and a Music
User token, which Joel will show
you how to get in the latter
half of the presentation.
Now, how do I get access to the
API?
One, you have to be a member of
the Apple Developer Program.
Second thing you need is a
MusicKit private key.
You can find a MusicKit private
key in the Accounts section of
the Apple Developer Portal in
the Certificates and Identities
area.
Once you have the Music private
key, you can use that to sign
the Developer token.
The Developer token is in JSON
Web Token format, much like the
APNS token, and it's required,
as I mentioned previously, in
the authorization header for
every Apple Music API request.
Just one note about security,
keep you MusicKit private key
secure.
Don't embed it in the binaries
of your application.
What we recommend is that you
dynamically generate your
developer tokens, preferably on
a server that's within your
control and that you have
authorization access for.
Some notes about the format of a
Developer token.
Developer token has two parts,
required headers, which are the
encryption algorithm.
We only support, ES256 is ou
encryption algorithm, and the
key identifier.
When you download your MusicKit
private key, you can find this
as part of that download.
The second half is the required
claims.
We have three required claims,
an Issuer ID, which is the Team
ID, and you can find this in the
Membership section of the Apple
Developer portal.
We have an issue at time for
this Developer token, which is
in UNIX format; and finally, you
have an expiration.
Tokens can only be generated
that expire 6 months from now.
So, with that, I'm going to turn
over the rest of the
presentation to my colleague,
Joel, and he'll tell you a
little bit about using MusicKit
on iOS.
[ Aapplause ]
>> Thank you.
Thank you.
>> Thank you, Tim.
Hi again. So, I'd like to tell
you all about how you can take
full advantage of MusicKit for
your iOS apps.
And to do that, first, I will
tell you some more about how you
can get full access to Apple
Music API.
Then, I'll tell you what you're
supposed to do if you're faced
with a user who doesn't
currently have an Apple Music
subscription.
And finally, I'll tell you how
you can use the iOS SDK to
initiate and control playback of
subscription and library
content.
So, let's talk about getting
full access to Apple Music API.
The first thing you might wonder
about is authentication, but as
it turns out most users are
already signed in with an iTune
Store account on their iOS
device, and for this reason, you
really don't need to worry about
Prompt User for Credentials.
However, because privacy is such
an important concern on iOS, you
really need to get the user's
informed consent before we grant
your app access to Apple Music.
This user consent is very
similar to what ou would request
before getting access to the
user's location or the user's
contact information.
This is also something you need
to request per application and
per iOS device.
So, if your apps, app works on
both iPhone and iPad for the
same user, make sure to request
this user consent separately.
This is what the user consent
dialogue looks like in the Nike
Plus Run Club app, and it's the
standard user consent dialogue
for privacy.
And one important part of it is
the subtitle where the third
party app developer is required
to inform the user as to why it
requires access to the Apple
Music data of the user.
Requesting the user consent is
needed to get access to both the
device library as well as the
music user token.
You can read the current
authorization status for your
app to see if you've already
been granted this user consent,
and this will not prompt the
user with the dialogue I just
showed you.
However, you can more simply
request authorization, and this
will prompt the user unless your
app has already received this
authorization.
To do so, you can use a class
and distorted framework.
It's called
SKCloudServiceController, and
you can call a method on it, a
class method named Request
Authorization.
We'll call your completion
handler with a status code, and
you know you can proceed to call
Apple Music API if you get the
authorized status code.
Additionally, you will have to
set the NS Apple Music Usage
description field in your Info P
list to populate the subtitle of
the user consent dialogue.
The next important step is to
fetch the subscription status.
To determine if the user is
actually subscribed to Apple
Music, and this is important for
issuing personalized requests to
get at data such as recently
played or heavy rotation, for
example.
However, this is not necessarily
a simple yes and no type of
question.
The subscription status may be
complex because while a user may
be an Apple Music subscriber
because that user may simply pay
the monthly fee, it's also
possible a user is a subscriber
through their carrier.
Additionally, some users can
play subscription content for
Apple Music, and yet your apps
won't be able to add content to
those user's music libraries.
And this is because the iCloud
Music Library feature has to be
enabled separately.
Finally, it's possible you won't
be able to suggest to all of
your users to become Apple Music
subscribers because we don't
offer Apple Music in every
single country, and even in
countries where we do offer
Apple Music, there are settings
such as education settings or
enterprise settings where
becoming an Apple Music
subscriber is actually
restricted.
So, for this reason, we expose
three independent capabilities
you can query.
The music catalog playback
capability, the add to iCloud
Music Library capability, and
you can also tell if the user
can become a subscriber.
So, it's important that you
check these individual
capabilities in your app before
you take an action related to
Apple Music.
So, for example, if you want to
have a Play button in your app
to preview a piece of content
from Apple Music, make sure to
check the music catalog playback
capability.
Conversely, if you want to have
an Add button to add a certain
song to a playlist from the
user's library, make sure that
the Add to iCloud Music Library
capability is enabled.
Fetching the subscription status
information requires the user's
consent, and you can do it in
code using, again,
SKCloudServiceController.
Here, we'll be calling an
instance method called Request
Capabilities, and we'll call
your completion handler with an
Option set of capabilities.
You can check inside of that
Option set for the presence of
the Music Catalog Playback
capability to check if the user
can play subscription content or
for the presence of Add to Cloud
Music Library to see if your app
can add songs to the Cloud
Library of this user.
Next stop, you might need to
know the Storefront Country
Code.
This is particularly important
for requesting content from the
catalog end points of the Apple
Music API because, as you know,
the Storefront Country Code is
an important part of the past of
those URLs.
To fetch this Storefront Country
Code, you'll be able to use
another instance method of
SKCloudServiceController.
This time it's called Request
Storefront Country Code, and
we'll invoke your Completion
Handler with a two-letter
country code, which you can then
use to build out the URL for
your catalog end point request.
In this case, we're trying to
build the top songs URL, and
this is the particular line that
is relevant where we use the
Storefront Country Code in the
middle of the path of this URL.
Finally, to unlock the full
power of Apple Music API, you
will need to get the music user
token, which is very important
to issue requests for
personalized content, such as
recently played or heavy
rotation.
This is derived from your
developer token, and because
fetching the music user token is
a somewhat expensive operation,
we recommend you cache the music
user token once you've fetched
it.
You can do so using user
defaults, for example, but make
sure not to transfer the music
user token across devices
because you might be violating
user consent if you do so.
Since you'll be caching this
music user token, you should
also be aware of when you should
invalidate this cache and fetch
the music user token again, and
this is typically whenever you
get a forbidden status code from
any of the Apple Music API
endpoints; that is the (403)
HTTP status code.
This could happen in a number of
scenarios, For example, the user
might change the password
associated with the iTunes store
account, or the user might
actually decide to revoke the
user token associated with your
app, or, finally, the user token
could expire naturally.
In all of these cases, make sure
to refetch the music user token
after checking the capabilities
again, just in case the active
iTunes store account has
changed, meanwhile.
So, to fetch the music user
token, we'll be using store
kits, SKCloudServiceController,
once more.
Here, we have another method.
Request user token for developer
token.
You'll pass the developer token
as a parameter, and then we'll
invoke our completion handler
and hand you the music user
token.
You can then use that to
properly populate the relevant
HTTP headers in your URL request
and specifically the music token
HTTP header.
Once you've gotten the User
Token and User Consent, you have
full access to Apple Music API,
so you can proceed to build
amazing user experiences for
your apps that keep your users
engaged.
However, sometimes, you'll be
faced with another edge case
when a user is not already an
Apple Music subscriber.
When that's the case, you might
want to show a subscription view
to suggest to the user to join
Apple Music so they can take
part in our trial period, get
access to over 40 million songs,
and also unlock the full
potential of your apps.
Additionally, it's particularly
relevant for you as developers
because you can get rewarded for
bringing in Apple Music
subscribers by taking part in
our Affiliate Program.
So, when exactly are you
supposed to show the
Subscription View?
You should do so whenever you
detect that the user cannot
currently playback subscription
content.
But the user can become an Apple
Music subscriber.
In terms of the capabilities we
discussed previously, that means
you need to make sure the music
catalog playback capability is
currently disabled while the
music catalog subscription
eligible capability is enabled.
As a side note, in the very rare
occurrence that the user doesn't
have an active iTunes Store
account on this device, you will
see that status reported the
exact same way, and we will make
sure to include a Sign In button
as part of the Subscription
View.
A subscription view is quite
configurable and, namely, you
can choose the main message we
convey to the user.
By default, we'll tell the user
Join Apple Music.
But by passing an optional
message identifier, you can
choose a more tailored message
based on the next action you
want to take in your app.
So, we have other values you can
choose from for the message
identifier, such as Connect, and
we'll tell the user connect to
Apple Music.
We also have Add Music, and well
tell the user add all the music
you want.
And we finally have Play Music.
So, make sure to pick the best
message identifier that
corresponds to the next action
you want to take in your app, so
we can choose the right message
that will make the most sense to
the user.
You can also make the
subscription view contextual by
highlighting a certain piece of
content, such as a song, album,
playlist, or radio station.
You can do so by passing an
iTunes item identifier option
which requires a value of tight
string, and that corresponds to
the ID field of the JSON
representation of an Apple Music
API resource.
There are a few more options you
need to be aware of for this
subscription view.
You will have to set the action
to subscribe, and you can also
pass optional affiliate tokens
and campaign tokens if you are
taking part in our Affiliate
Program.
Putting it all together, this is
how you can show the
Subscription view.
We'll instantiating a view
controller from Store Kits SK
CloudServiceSetupViewController,
and you can set yourself up as a
delegate for this
ViewController.
Then, you need to build the list
of options we just discussed.
In this case, we will be setting
the action to subscribe and the
message identifier to play
music, and you need to call the
load with options method to load
all the content of the
subscription view.
And this is because it's a
server driven view that requires
us to load a certain amount of
content.
Because this process is
asynchronous, we recommend you
show a spinner in your app while
we're loading this content, and
you can do so using
UIActivityIndicatorView.
Once we're done loading all the
content, we'll invoke the
completion handler, and you can
proceed to show the subscription
view.
If it did succeed Boolean, it's
set to true by simply calling
the PresentViewController method
from UIKit.
And that's how you show the
subscription view.
Additionally, if the user
decides to become a subscriber
as a result of this, you can
detect that by observing the
capabilities did change
notification from
SKCloudServiceController, and
you can also detect that the
subscription view was dismissed
using the belated delegate
method.
So, with that, you have all the
tokens you need to have Apple
Music API, fetch Apple Music
content, and you made sure the
user is a subscriber.
So, we can have some more fun
and actually do some playback of
subscription or library content.
And to do so, we'll switch gears
a little bit and take a look at
another framework in the iOS
SDK, the MediaPlayer framework.
You'll find the MediaPlayer
framework a class named MP
MusicPlayer Controller, which
offers two distinct players that
allow you to control music
playback for two different types
of use cases.
To highlight that, let's start
with an example.
Let's say you're building a
social networking app.
You want to make it easy for
your users to share music
content with their friends, and
so it's important that the
friend receiving such a piece of
content is able to preview that
song or album from your app.
However, you should make sure
that the friend receiving this
piece of content can then
benefit from the full feature
set of the music app, allowing
the friend to go back to the
music app and maybe share the
song further, using Connect or
AirDrop.
For such applications, the
system user player might be the
right fit.
However, if you need more
control over the playback
experience, you might want to
take a look at the application
queue player, and a good example
here might be a fitness app.
It's possible you want to have
some music playing in the
background while your user is
running outside, and so you
might want to make sure that the
music matches the pace of the
runner.
You might also want to insert a
power song in the middle of the
playback queue and have your own
customized playback controls.
The application queue player
will allow you to do all of
those things.
Both of these players will do a
lot for you automatically.
They will make sure to populate
the control center in lock
screen.
However, things will be recorded
a bit differently, depending on
the player you pick because the
music app will be recoded as a
Now Playing app with the system
music player, whereas it's going
to be your app recorded as the
Now Playing app if you choose
the application queue player.
And this is because with the
System Music Player, your app is
acting as a simple remote
control of the music app.
Whereas if you use the
application queue player, your
app fully owns the playback
queue completely independent
from the music app.
Both of these players allow you
to control the playback queue
with simple operations such as
completely replacing the
playback queue with a Set Queue
command, and you can also use
the Up Next functionality by
setting content to Play Next or
Play Later.
But with the application queue
player, you can go one step
further by inserting items in
the middle of the playback queue
over moving items that are
already in the playback queue.
To achieve some of those
playback queue manipulation
tasks, you'll be using a concept
we call queue descriptors.
We offer three different types
of queue descriptors based on
the type of content you're
dealing with.
The first one is the media item
queue descriptor, and this is
useful if you have an instance
of MPMediaItem or
MPMediaItemCollection, which you
would like to start playback
with.
And typically, you get a hold of
such instances by making device
library queries using
MPMediaQuery, or by presenting
the media picker to allow the
user to select a piece of
content from his library.
For catalog playback, we also
have the store queue descriptor,
and here the data you need to
use the store queue descriptor
is a store ID, and that's a
string that corresponds to the
ID field of the JSON
representation of an Apple Music
API resource.
And this is typically useful for
catalog content such as from
catalog search.
We also have a new queue
descriptor, the playback, the
play parameter's queue
descriptor, and this does
everything the store queue
descriptor does, in addition to
handling personalized content,
such as content from recently
played or heavy rotation, and it
also supports playback of radio
stations.
Here, the data you'll need to
use for the play parameters
queue descriptor is the value
associated with the play params
field in the JSON representation
of an Apple Music API resource.
So, let's take a look at how you
can use those queue descriptors
to control playback in your
apps.
Here, we'll do some simple
playback queue manipulation
tasks, and we'll choose to use
the SystemMusicPlayer.
Both players support simple
playback tweaks you can apply to
them such as setting the repeat
mode to all.
But you can also change the
shuffle mode if you like.
The first thing we'll do is
change the playback queue,
replace it completely with a
local album represented with an
MPMediaItemCollection.
Because that's the type of data
we have, we'll be using the
MPMediaItem, I'm sorry, the
MediaItemQueueDescriptor.
You can also decide to start
playback with the fourth song of
the album by setting the start
item with the fourth item of the
album.
And you can use that to call the
setQueue method on the player.
You can also use Up Next to add
a song to Play Next using the
prepend method on the player.
And here, we're trying to add a
catalog song to Play Next.
It's represented with a Store
ID, and for this reason, we have
to use the store queue
descriptor.
But you can also add songs from
recently played, for example, to
the queue, and they'll typically
be represented with play
parameters you can find in the
JSON representation of Apple
Music API resources.
And because that's the data we
have, we'll be using the play
parameters queue descriptor.
Then, in this case, we'll choose
to use it with the append method
of the player to add this song
to Play Later.
If your app requires more
control over the playback queue,
however, you can switch to the
ApplicationQueuePlayer to unlock
some more features.
Mainly, you can call the perform
queue transaction method on the
ApplicationQueuePlayer.
It requires two closures as
parameters.
The first one is the queue
transaction.
We'll be passing a mutable queue
object, which represents the
current state of the playback
queue.
You can call a few methods on
this mutable queue, such as the
remove method to remove the
third item currently in the
playback queue.
You can also call the insert
after method, which we're
calling here to insert an item
after the fifth item of the
playback queue.
Once we're done applying all of
those modifications to the
playback queue, we'll call your
completion handler to let you
know.
And that's an overview of
everything you can do in terms
of playback with Apple Music,
and we can't wait to see the
experiences you'll build in your
apps.
So, let's talk about timeframe.
When can you adopt these APIs in
your apps?
As it turns out, a lot of these
APIs trickled in throughout
several releases, and many of
them are available on iOS 10.3
with a few caveats.
We will begin generating music
user tokens for iOS 10.3 devices
later this fall.
You'll also have to use an
alternate method to get to the
storefront country code, and you
can use, for example, the
current locale's region code as
an approximation.
However, you'll be able to
initiate playback with catalog
content using the store queue
descriptor right on iOS 10.3.
On iOS 11, with beta you have
available to you today, you can
do everything we just discussed
with the exception of play
parameters, queue descriptors,
which will come in a later beta.
And because play parameters
queue descriptors support
everything the store queue
descriptor supports, in addition
to radio stations and
personalized content, if you're
targeting iOS 11 and later, you
should really use that primarily
instead of the store queue
descriptor.
So, to summarize, Apple Music
offers a breadth of content,
over 40 million songs and
personalized recommendations for
your users, and you can use
that, leverage this content to
create immersive experiences in
your apps to keep your users
engaged.
To do that, you'll have to use
StoreKit framework to get the
user's consent and the Music
user token to unlock the full
capabilities of Apple Music API.
And you can call Apple Music
API, fetch the relevant data,
parse it from JSON, and use
MediaPlayer framework to control
playback of this piece of
content.
For more information on
MusicKit, feel free to check out
our developer portal with this
URL.
You also have a few related
sessions.
We just had the What's New in
Audio session in this room.
We'll also have tomorrow
morning, What's New in
Foundation, where you can learn
all about using the new JSON
decoder in Swift 4.0 and on
Thursday, you can learn about
AirPlay 2 as well.
Thank you very much, and enjoy
the rest of the conference.
[ Applause ]