Good afternoon.
It's so great to see so many of
you here today.
for session 505, "What's New in
Photos API."
My name is Eric Hanson, I'm the
Photos Platform evangelist and
I'm joined here this afternoon
by two of my colleagues from the
Photos engineering team to talk
to you about a whole lot of
great things new in Photos for
iOS and for macOS High Sierra.
So, obviously, we're all here
because we care about
photography.
And our users as I'm sure most
of you know, care deeply about
photography.
Every day around the world
millions and millions of photos
are captured on iOS devices.
Leading to ever-growing
libraries filled with tremendous
amount of memory and meaningful
moments that delight users when
they reexperience them.
And so, we want to talk to you
about creating great experiences
in your apps and integrating
with the Photo library.
And we've got some great new API
to make this easy for you.
We also want to talk to you
about doing this in a way that
is high-performing within your
app.
Ensuring that the responsiveness
of your application is the best
it can possibly be.
So, we're going to talk to you
about that as well.
And finally, we want to do this
in a way that we're not
violating the trust with the
user.
We're not forcing the user to
give up privacy just because
they want to integrate with your
application and with their
photos.
We're going to talk to you about
that too.
And on this last point, I'd like
to welcome to the stage, my
first colleague in the Photos
Engineering Team, Hasan Adil.
Hasan.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Eric.
Hello, everybody.
It's great to see you.
UI Image Picker Controller is a
simple and easy to use API for
selecting photos and videos in
your app.
In iOS 11, we have some great
improvements and new features
that I'm really excited to share
with you today.
At Apple, we care deeply about
our users' privacy and security.
Therefore, whenever you
presented the
UIMessagesViewController, we
require you to get the users'
authorization for their entire
library in order to select a
single photo or video.
I'm sure you all well aware,
familiar with this alert.
This cause friction in your app.
As well as the user giving up a
level of privacy that perhaps
they didn't really mean to.
As well as apps that will fail
to perform even though there are
great features, because the user
didn't want to give them access.
Well, we thought we could do
better.
So, in iOS 11, we have revamped
the privacy and security
fundaments of
UIMessageViewController.
We started off with three goals.
Put the user in charge of their
content.
Create a great user experience
in your apps.
And third, give a higher level
of privacy to our users.
So, I'm happy to announce that
in iOS 11, this alert is no
longer needed.
It just works.
[ Applause ]
Let's look at a demo and we'll
get into it.
So, here's an app I've just
downloaded from the app store.
I'm really excited to use it.
I've filled out, I'm having a
great day at WWDC, a little bit
nervous, but that's OK.
But I'd like to attach a photo.
Now, let's see what presenting
UIMessageViewController in iOS
11 looks like.
It just works.
UIMessageViewController in iOS
11 is now an auto process API.
What that means is that we
present the contents of our API
from an auto process sandbox and
secure environment.
And apps no longer get access to
users' photo library.
Only the user is able to
interact with
UIMessageViewController UI.
When the user makes a selection,
we take that photo or video and
send it over to your app.
We feel that this removes
friction from your app.
As well as gives users a really
high level of privacy.
Because no authorization is
granted, none is asked for.
We hope you'll like it.
Using it is really easy.
You have to make no additions.
It will just work.
Photos contain rich metadata
within them.
This includes the created date.
The format of the photo.
As well as other various
metadata.
And we've made it really easy to
get to this in iOS 11.
We now provide you a brand0new
key with every result of
UIImagePickerController.
The key is called
UIImagePickerControllerImageURL.
This URL is a file URL, which
points to a file in the
temporary of your app.
So, if you would like to work
with us later, we suggest you
move the file to a more
permanent location so it stays
there.
You can us a URL as is, or you
can read the NSDate into your
app and process as needed.
In iOS 11 we have introduced a
new format called HEIF for
photos.
Now we realize that it will take
some time for the ecosystem to
adopt HEIF fully.
And we made it really easy to do
so with UIImagePickerController.
We have a new property called
imageExportPresent.
It could be set to two types.
It could be compatible mode, or
we can set it to current mode.
Let's look at them.
In compatible mode, if the
source photo that the user
selected exists as a HEIF
formatted photo we will
transport a Jpeg and give you a
Jpeg version of it.
This is also the default value
for the property.
And if you don't need anything
different, you don't need to do
anything.
However, if you would like the
photo as we have it, set the
value to current and we'll give
you the photo as we have it in
Photo library and you might get
HEIF and you can deal with that.
We have some great changes when
it comes to selecting videos.
But let me step aside for a
second, the AVFoundation is
Apple's framework for rich
editing as well as playback of
photos.
And AVFoundation has a rich set
of export presets, or formats
you can say.
And I'm happy to announce
UIImagePickerController supports
all of them.
We have a new property called
videoExportPreset.
You can use this as a way to
tell us what format would you
like selected with you to be
given to you.
Let's look at an example.
After importAVFoundation you
will create an instance of
UIImagePickerController and tell
us what format you like.
Here, I'm asking you to give me
the highest quality video.
And then you present the picker.
When the user makes a selection
regardless of what format it
was, we're cross coded to a
matching format and give you
back the video.
This is especially great for
getting the videos back in the
original format that they
existed in.
For a full list of available
presets, please see this
interface called
AVAssetExportSession, or come
see us in the lab and we'd be
happy to help you.
To my earlier point about
increasing the privacy, we also
took a deep look at what it
takes to add content into a
photo library.
Now, since we've made picking
seamless, we thought we would
make adding awesome also.
So, in iOS 11, if you are to use
either of these two methods for
saving a photo or a video into
the user's library, we have a
new security model and a
permission level.
The permission level for either
of these two methods, the
UIImagePickerController one is
called UIImageWriteToSave
ForusAlbum.
And the other one is
UISaveVideoAtPath
ToSavedPhotoAlbum.
These require add only
authorization.
These are really library
questions to get from the user.
Because these will allow you to
add in library and not read.
So, we feel like users are going
to be very likely, will give you
this authorization.
And like before, come see us in
the lab if you have any
questions.
For our users of PhotoKit, we
have something great.
Now, with every result of
UIImagePickerController, if
you're a PhotoKit user, we also
give you back PHAsset object
matching the user selection.
This makes it really seamless to
integrate PhotoKit across APIs.
Let's look at an example.
So, here's I've implemented the
delicate method of
UImagePickerController delegate.
And when I get the result
dictionary, I have a brand new
key, the key is called
UIImagePickerController,
PHAsset.
You get the value of that key
and this key will be the asset
object and you are free to use
it.
Now, going along with this, we
had previously deprecated the
ALAssets laboratory framework
and now the ALAssets Library
reference URLS, which we used to
pass to you using a key called
UIImagePickerController
referenceURL has now be
deprecated also.
Yeah, PhotoKit is great and you
will love it.
We feel that with these changes
to enhance the user privacy,
features to make
UImagePickerController a
powerful and full feature API,
that this will satisfy the needs
of the majority of apps out
there.
However, there are times when
you do need deep integration
with the Photos frameworks.
And for that we recommend
PhotoKit.
To tell you what's new in
PhotoKit in iOS 11, I'd like
welcome my colleague, Andreas
Karlsson.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you Hasan.
So, apps related to photography
are consistently some of the
most popular apps on the App
Store.
It takes, both great features
and a great user experience to
succeed in that market.
I'm very excited to be here
today to talk about improvements
we have made in PhotoKit that we
hope enable you to write both
exciting new features and makes
it easier to improve the user
experience of your apps.
So, let's jump right in.
Let's look at live photo effects
that were announced in the
keynote on Monday.
So, live photo effects include
these loops, which are created
by carefully analyzing the video
and seamlessly stitching them
together into these endless
loops.
Also, include bounce which works
in a similar way, but as you can
see, it works better with dogs.
And finally, there is long
exposure, which analyzes the
video frames in a live photo to
create these amazing looking
stills.
So, we believe users are going
to have a lot of fun with these,
and we're also really excited
for what you come up with in
your apps when integrating with
these new kind of media types.
So, let's look at how you would
do that.
Let's look at some code.
So, these are the PhotoKit Media
types that currently exist.
They're great, they describe
what Asset is, but what's even
more important is how the asset
gets presented.
And let me explain what I mean
by that.
So, if a user shot a video, they
would really like to see and use
that asset as a video in your
app.
If they shot a live photo, they
care equally about the still
part and the video part.
So, they would like to see that
asset as a live photo in your
app.
To do this currently, you would
look at these three media types.
Image, video and photo live to
do the right thing.
With live photo effects this
become a bit more muddy and to
make this really easy to get
right, since it's so important,
this year in iOS 11, we're
introducing a new property of
PHAsset called PlaybackStyle.
Now, PlaybackStyle is the single
property you can look at to
determine which kind of image
manager API to use, what kind of
view to present it in, and what
kind of UI limits should
accompany the view.
So, the PhotoKit has been
updated to cover all these new
playback styles, but I'd like to
go into detail on three of them
that relate to life photo
affects here in this session.
So, let's start with image
animated.
So, new this year, the built in
Photos app is afford for
animated GIF playback.
[ Applause ]
To playback GIFs in your own
apps, you would request the
image data from the image manger
and then use image iO and core
graphics for playback.
Now, the sample app, does
include a sample of how to do
this.
So, please have a look there in
case you would like to do GIF
playback.
Next, is live photo.
So, live photos, users care a
lot about live photos.
So, getting them presented in
your app in the right way is
really important, but also
really easy.
So, in this case you would
request a live photo from the
image manager and then you say
PHLivePhotoView for playback.
You set the live photo, you'll
get back on the view and users
can then use three touch to
playback a live photo.
Users [inaudible] in the built
in photo's app inside your app.
PHLivePhotoView can also be used
with live photos outside the
user's photo library.
For example, if you transfer
them over web service or
something similar.
Finally, there is looping video.
And these include both the
bounds and loop live photo
effects that were introduced
this year.
Now, to play these back in your
apps, it's very similar to
regular video.
So, you would request the player
item, and use AVFoundation for
play back.
But you would use an
AVPlayerLooper to get the
looping effect.
So, I hope you have seen how
easy it is to present the user's
media how they really wanted to
be presented.
And we cannot wait to see what
you guys come up with in your
apps related to these new media
kinds.
Next, I'd like to talk about
iCloud Photo Library.
So, iCloud Photo Library is
really great because users can
now put their entire photo
library in their pocket.
And this is really great for
some users who have really large
libraries.
Some users have more than
100,000 photos in their photo
library, and they're not that
uncommon actually.
So, what kind of user has that
many photos?
Well, to get 100,000 photos, you
have to take 28 photos per day,
every day for 10 years straight.
So, these users obviously love
to use the camera and camera
apps, but they also tend to
download and use a lot of
photography-related apps.
These users are really important
to all of us in this room.
Now imagine one of these users,
after taking their daily 28
photos, they go to the App Store
to find an interesting app to
use.
They find your app.
They decide to download it and
give it a try.
And the first thing they see
when they start using your app,
is this.
Now, spinner for multiple
seconds are not a great user
experience.
And this user might uninstall
your app right away, or even
worse, leave a bad review.
So, you might be thinking, well
my app wouldn't do that, or if
it does, I'm using PhotoKit and
this user has a really large
library.
So, maybe this is to be
expected.
PhotoKit was designed from the
beginning to be really fast and
efficient with large photo
libraries.
But there are some common
mistakes clients make that can
mean the difference between
operation taking 10
milliseconds, and 10 seconds.
So, how do I fix this?
Well, since it's so easy to end
up with something taking a long
time, step number 1 is to test
your app with a large photo
library.
Now we already covered, it's
kind of difficult to get that
many photos using the camera
app.
So, this year we want to make
that really easy.
So, we're providing a sample app
that you can download called
photo library filler.
Download this app and install it
on your test device.
It will quickly generate a large
library for you to use for
testing.
So, great.
[ Applause ]
So, great you have a large
library, you test your app.
Chances are you might start
seeing some delays.
So, I'd like to talk about two
common problems clients have
with PhotoKit and their
solutions.
So, let's look at some code.
So, this is how you fetch assets
from the users' photos library.
There are two parts to this.
There is the database fetching
part, and then dealing with a
result.
Let's focus on the database
fetching part first.
So, here we're fetching all
assets on the library, but we're
filtering with a filter
predicate on favorite assets.
And we're sorting by creating
day.
If you're doing this kind of
custom fetches, they are
definitely supported, but if you
start seeing delays in these
kind of custom fetches, it's
definitely worth trying to
simplify the predicate or
simplify the sort descriptor.
And that can mean the difference
between this query taking 10
milliseconds and 10 seconds.
The reason for this drastic
difference is that you might end
up outside the optimized path in
the database and trying to get
back into the optimized path can
really pay off.
So, even better than doing these
kind of custom fetches, is to
avoid them if it's possible.
So, in this case we can actually
fetch the user's favorite smart
album and then fetch the assets
inside of the smart album.
That gives both the predicate
and the sort descriptor for
free.
And you're guaranteed to end up
in the optimized path in
PhotoKit.
So, next, let's look at the
result you get back from one of
these kinds of fetches.
So, this object is a PHFetch
result.
Now in a PHFetch result looks a
lot like an array and you can
use it a lot like an array.
You can ask for object and
index.
You can ask for its count, and
you can enumerate it.
But internally, a fetch result
works very differently from an
array, and is part of the reason
PhotoKit can be so fast and
efficient with large libraries.
So, let's look at how it works
internally.
So, initially it just contains a
list of identifiers.
And this means you can get back
one fairly quickly.
But as you start using it,
additional work has to be
performed.
So, let's look at enumeration as
an example.
And here we're starting
enumeration at index 0.
So you only have an identifier
so far, so we need to fetch
metadata form the database in
order to create a PHAsset object
to return to you in the block.
Now, the fetch result is pretty
smart.
It's actually going to create a
batch at the same time.
So, as we continue enumeration,
index 1 and 2 are already in
memory.
And then enumeration continues
and you get the idea.
It's going to access the disk to
get the metadata for subsequent
assets.
So, for this kind of small fetch
result this doesn't matter.
But I would image this fetch
result has 100,000 assets in it.
Each batch takes a couple of
kilobytes of memory.
But when you have 100,000 of
them you're looking at hundreds
of megabytes of memory usage.
And even worse, each batch take
a couple of milliseconds to
fetch.
But when you have 100,000 of
them, you're looking at 10
seconds to enumerate a large
fetch result.
So, enumeration is clearly
something we should try to avoid
if at all possible.
We have found that it's almost
always possible to avoid
enumeration.
And I would like to look at one
example of how it can be
avoided.
So, in this case, we're trying
to find the index of an asset
that inside a fetch result.
Now, we could enumerate the
fetch result and compare the
objects we get back using is
equal.
But as we saw enumeration can be
quite slow.
So, even better is to actually
use high level API.
In this case, we can use index
of object.
And that is able to internally,
in the fetch result be really
smart and compare the
identifiers with the object
you're looking for.
And array will define this index
without any additional disk
access or database fetching at
all.
Same goes for contains object.
So, I hope you have seen how
easy it is to get a large
library to test your app with.
And how easy it can be to really
make a huge different in the
performance of your app.
Small fixes can mean multiple
seconds of time savings.
If you do have questions on
PhotoKit performance, please
come see us in the lab tomorrow
morning.
If you do encounter issues that
you're not able to resolve,
please file [inaudible].
And if there's one thing you
remember from this part of the
session, please test your app
with the large photo library and
take really good care of these
really important users.
Next, I'd like to welcome Eric
Hanson back to the stage to talk
about Photo Project Extensions.
Eric [applause].
>> Thank you Andreas.
Thank you very much.
I am really, really excited to
finally be able to talk about
something we've been working
really hard on this year in High
Sierra.
So much so that I need a sip of
water, sorry.
All right.
So, we're going to talk about
Photos project extension.
And I think to kick this off we
have to talk about what are
projects.
You know Apple has been allowing
users to create these really
rich creative photo centric
projects in the photos apps for
a very long time.
Actually, going all the way back
to iPhoto 1.0 when we first
released photobooks.
But this year, we wanted to do
something different.
Because during that time, 14
years, you as developers have
been building up some really
great experiences yourself with
your own apps.
And we thought, you know, let's
bring this together.
Let's give you an opportunity to
actually create something that's
a fantastic experience directly
within the Photos app.
And that's exactly what we've
done with the extensions.
We started working on the API,
engage just a few developers to
kind of see what they would do
with it.
Companies like Shutterfly, who
are going to be launching with
their own photobooks and photos
in the fall.
A company called WhiteWall that
allows you to do these gallery
quality framed prints.
Wix.com that created a brand-new
feature allowing users to easily
create web photo albums.
Animoto, that allows users to
create these really beautiful
movies that are server hosted
and integrated with social
media.
And a company called ifolor that
did something really novel.
They kind of started from the
ground floor and looked at this
as an opportunity for you know
what could they build that
really tied into the photos
ecosystem and really created
some magic for the user.
And I think rather than explain
it.
I want to show you a quick demo.
So here we are in the photos app
on High Sierra.
And I'm in memories.
And I've got this favorite
memory here, together that I'm
just going to select.
And I can hover over my project
section in the side bar and you
see this little button.
And you'll notice that in
addition to the Apple offerings
we currently have, photos has
automatically discovered that I
have another application
installed, called ifolor wall
dcor.
So, this extension is now
exposed to me.
I simply select that and I'm
presented with some choices.
Now these choices are coming
from the extension itself.
So, before we've even loaded the
extension, the extension is
notifying us that you know,
before you push a project to me
I want the user to make a
choice.
I want to be able to fork my own
code.
So, they give us the title and
the description and the image.
Photos actually lays it out
beautifully in the sheet.
And I'm just going to pick that
first option.
I hit the create button, and
now, their extension, their view
controller is going to be pushed
directly into photos.
Full view, but this is their UI,
this is their experience inside
photos.
Now, they've leveraged the
memory in this case and taken
the hints we provided to lay out
this grid.
But they've also taken hints we
provided to let me get at all of
the images that were considered
when the memory was created.
So, you'll notice over here on
the bottom right, if you can see
it, you can't because it's
behind me, 283 images.
And what's was really cool about
that is I can actually
customize.
So, I'll switch this to unused
images, because there's a photo
that I like a little bit better.
I'll take this one, that I think
would be a really great hero
shot.
So, I can just drag that up and
customize this layout.
And they went a step further
than that.
They let me customize the grid
itself in a really novel way.
So, I want to give a little more
emphasis to this row.
And maybe move this down.
And I'll move this down to line
it up and you know let's do one
more.
And I really like that.
So, I could just hit the buy
button now, still within photos.
Choose my size, this would show
up in the mail.
And I have this memory hanging
on the wall in my den.
It's pretty cool.
That's just a really quick tour
of ifolor.
[ Applause ]
So, what you want to know is how
does this all work.
If you're familiar with the
editing extensions in Photos,
you already have a good sense of
how this works.
We've added a new extension
point to Photos;
com.apple.photo-project.
And we've added a new template
within Xcode that lets you
easily create one of these
extensions in your own app.
As you saw, in the demo, we
automatically discovered your
extension, raising the
discoverability of your app on
the system.
But we took discoverability a
step further.
By offering users a direct link
to the App Store that brings up
the App Store window, but
doesn't require them to search
for an app with that extension.
It automatically shows only the
apps that support that extension
point.
And we think this is really
going to heighten the ability
for users to discover your apps
and quickly download them, and
start working with them.
So much so that we put a similar
App Store link in edit.
And so, if you're already doing
image editing extensions, users
will have a direct link into the
App Store to immediately
discover you editing extensions.
It's pretty cool.
So, your extension lives within
the app, within your app.
And that's really a great
opportunity for you.
Because you may already have an
app in the App Store that's got
a lot of app specific code, but
you probably have some resources
and some other sharable code
that you could easily move kind
of into this extension space and
leverage those.
You obviously also have some
extension specific code that you
would need to write.
A very small amount.
And finally, you just need to
add a view controller that
implements this protocol.
The PH project extension control
protocol.
With all that in place, Photos
can immediately discover your
extension.
Let the user choose to you know
to create a product with that
and we simply call this protocol
method begin project.
And when we do we send over a
couple bits of data.
So, in addition to the photos
we're sending you, the project
extension context, and we're
sending you an object called
PHProjectInfo.
You can consume that in whatever
way you want.
And then you just quickly call
back the completion closure that
we hand you.
And that let's Photos know it
can install your view
controller, full view inside the
Photos app.
And from that point, as you saw,
it's totally your UI.
It's your experience.
You have all of that API
available to you on macOS to
leverage from and build a really
killed experience for your
users.
So, the protocol itself is
really simple.
There's an optional property for
supported project types and you
saw this in the demo I just did.
And this lets you quickly
describe the choices you want a
user to make.
And you can opt out of this if
you want, you just want to
straight into the extension.
That's totally possible as well.
And then there are few required
functions you need to implement
in your view controller.
The first is begin project.
That's where we hand you the
context.
And we hand you the product
info.
And that's what we call the
first time a project is created
with your extension.
Now, if a user is coming back to
your extension for a project
they already created, we instead
call resume project.
And again, hand you this
extension context.
And finally, if a user is in
your extension and they decide
to switch away to do something
else within photos, we're simply
going to call finishProject.
Allowing you to clean up any
kind of data you're holding
onto.
Maybe quiet down any processor
intensive tasks or animations
thing like that that you might
be doing.
So, PHProject extension context
is a container for two really
important objects.
One is PHProject, and the other
PHPhotoLibrary, which is the
library from which you're going
to fetch all the assets.
PHProject itself is just a
subclass of PHAsset collection.
You may already be familiar with
PHAssetCollection.
It's a container.
It's got an array of assets.
It's got a title.
It's got a key asset, key photo.
And what we've done in sub
classing that, creating
PHProject, is we've added just
one property.
But it's a really, really
important property for you.
And that is the
projectExtensionData.
So, this is where you, the
extension can save any data you
need to that represents the
project the user created.
So, it's really intended for
that critical project data.
That is your list of the
assetIdenfiers that you're using
and that maybe is some basic
layout information configuration
information.
That's not for images and you
know cache, thumbnails, and
rosters, things like that.
Because you can create those on
the fly or cache those away
somewhere else.
So, we want that to be small,
but useful.
And we settled on this limit of
1 megabyte.
Because we think you know, an
array of assetIdenfiers
compressed is really, really
easy.
They're just strings.
And we think you can live within
1 megabyte.
And by doing that, we're not
bloating user's libraries as
they create project after
project and explore all these
amazing extensions that you're
going to create.
So, setting the data, really
easy.
We have an object called
PHProjectChangeRequest that you
simply instantiate and then once
you do, you can all this perform
changes and weight function on
the Photo library.
Inside that, set the data to
whatever you want it to be.
In this case, I'm just using an
NSKeyedArchiver archive an array
of identifiers.
And that's it, it's simple.
So, let's get into some fun
stuff.
I want to talk about where the
magic begins.
So, you saw in the ifolor demo
they really leveraged the
memory's feature.
The memory's feature is really,
really popular.
Users love this.
Right, while you're sleeping,
Photos is working hard all
night, going through kind of
your photo library, learning
sort of about you, right on your
device.
It's all happening right there
locally.
And it's building this graph of
kind of the events that are
meaningful to you and the people
in your life that are relevant
to you.
And through that it's able to
serve up these great memories
that users just consume on a
daily basis.
And so we wanted to make sure
you had access to that level of
data, right .
These extensions aren't
interesting if we just give you
an array of photos.
We've got to give you context
from which you can create
something great.
And that's what we've done with
PHProjectInfo.
So, ProductInfo at the top level
is broken into sections.
We give you this array of
PHProject section objects.
And for a given section, we tell
you the type.
So, you think about a memory,
we've got like a key photo at
the top.
And we call that type cover.
And then we've got this
editorial grid that we call type
content.
And then we give you this array
of content.
It will look something like
this.
And inside the contents we
actually give you access to the
elements, and the asset
identifiers and some layout
information.
And you might be asking yourself
when you look at this construct,
why the array and then the
array, right.
Why this kind of nested
structure.
But if you think about the
memory feature it makes sense,
right.
We allow users and memories to
toggle between showing a summary
of photos and showing all
photos.
The memory itself is built up
from a large pool of assets.
We call these curation levels.
And we wanted to make sure you
had access to these different
levels of information, right?
We've already done all this hard
work.
We've run all this intelligence.
Let's just share it with you and
let you build something on top
of it.
So, that section content array,
is an ordered array, where you
always know the object at index
0 is going to be the best of the
best.
The most premium.
The most condescended summary of
that collection of assets,
whereas the object at the very
end of the array is going to be
the most.
It's going to be everything we
considered.
And you get to decide what you
want to use.
The fewest, the most, everything
in between.
Maybe you want to offer your
users a choice.
You want to give them the
ability to switch between these.
And you can do that with the
context we're giving here.
Next up, cloud asset
identifiers.
This is kind of a new concept.
If you're familiar with PhotoKit
on iOS, you've not seen this
before because it's new.
But, we've never had a construct
where we wanted you to save data
into a user's photo library.
Data that represents assets but
data that might be synced to
other devices, that might appear
somewhere else at some point.
We want to make sure that the
data you're saving is meaningful
wherever it shows up.
And so, we've introduced a new
object called the
PHCloudIdentifier.
And you can think of this as a
global identifier for the asset.
But it's not as simple as just a
global string.
You know, dealing with the cloud
and sync states and all that is
really, really complicated.
And we've solved all that for
you.
The only thing you have to do
with this is just make sure
you're always converting from a
global identifier to a local
identifier before you fetch.
And for that we've just given
you a convenience method inside
PHPhotoLibrary to do that
conversion both ways; from
global, from pod identifier to
local identifier, and vice
versa.
Next, I want to talk about
layout.
So, we didn't just want to give
you assets and some constructs
around the curation.
We wanted to give you some hints
about how we present those
assets to a user right.
Help you with some of the
difficult problems of things
like grid layout.
All right, you look at a memory
and we've done a lot of hard
work already in laying out this
curated grid in a really
interesting way that's pleasing
to the user.
Wouldn't it be great if you had
access to that layout.
And you do.
But to do that, we had to
establish first kind of set of
rules, a coordinate system for
you.
So, if you look at the memory,
you notice everything aligns to
a very specific grid.
It's grid of 4x3 aspect ratio
cells.
But that's an odd, non-square
kind of dimension to share back
and forth.
That's a weird multiplier for
you.
So, we simply divided that yet
again.
And in this case, this layout is
really comprised of 20 uniform
columns.
What we call our grid spaces.
And once we have this coordinate
system established, you can
scale this however you want.
It's just a multiplier for you,
for whatever your output is.
Right? If you're rescaling on a
resizable window, or working
with web browsers of different
size, you can use this data to
know how to layout the content.
And it also lets us communicate
to you placement information.
So, in this example, I have this
photo that wants to live in the
upper left-hand corner.
So, I can now easily tell you
it's at position 00.
It's 8 grid spaces wide and it's
9 grid spaces tall.
Next thing I want to talk about
are elements.
So, inside the section constant
we give you an array of
elements.
And all the elements are
subclasses of PHProjectElement.
And there's two really important
properties there.
One, is placement, which we just
talked about and the other is
something called weight.
So, again going back to the
memories feature.
We talked to you about, like all
the intelligence that we're
doing, right?
And ascertaining the most
relevant photos in a large pool
of assets.
And so, our scoring system.
And we wanted to share that with
you.
And so, we do that by given
elements weight, right.
it's a normalized weight from 0
to 1.0, the default value is 0.5
meaning it's not horribly
significant, but is not horribly
insignificant either, if that
makes any sense.
But you know it's this
normalized score across the
entire section.
And you can do amazing things
with that, right?
Just really easily, right?
Sort your assets by that.
Decide where you want to chop
off, you know a large array of
assets and only work with the
significant ones.
Right? Present those as choices
to a user where you're serving
up the higher weighted assets
first.
And predicting that that's
probably what they're looking
for, what they want.
And there's one other bit here.
And this is specific to one of
the elements, which is the
PHProjectAssetElement.
We have this concept of regions
of interest.
You know, as you know there are
several ways already in the
macOS API to run face detection
to find faces in an image.
But form that you don't know the
relevancy of those faces.
You don't know if those faces
represent someone that is
meaningful in someone's life, or
it's a face in the crowd.
It's the person walking behind
you at a theme park, when you're
trying to photograph somebody in
your family.
You really don't have an ability
to tell the difference.
We wanted to give you something
that let you know, and let you
trust that if we've marked, if
we said it's interesting, it's
interesting, right.
And if you leverage this, you
create magic for your users.
Without necessarily even knowing
why.
And we went one step further.
If you notice we have
identifiers on these.
And we actually repurposed those
identifiers across images.
So, if we know that this thing
that's interesting in this photo
is also representing this same
thing, or same person in this
other photo, we'll give them the
same identifier .
So, if you're doing like
animation, slideshows, things
like that, this is tremendously
useful to you.
Because you now can actually
correlated positions of images
across a large set.
S, I could keep going, in a code
walk.
But, I'd rather give you a demo.
Because I think it's really
important to show you just how
easy it is to create one of
these extensions.
So, I'm here in Xcode.
And I promise I will zoom in
where necessary, so you will be
able to read this.
So, I'm here in Xcode.
And I have a project I started,
but it actually does nothing
yet.
The only thing it has are some
assets that a designed gave me.
And what we're going to build
right now, is a slideshow.
And the slideshow is going to be
the marriage of the content that
Photos is providing and seenkit
to do a really compelling kind
of 3D animation.
So, let's begin.
So, the first thing I can do is
just, I'm on the project and I
have this little plus button
here at the bottom add a target.
And I'll just add a target here.
And you'll notice we've got this
new template, right for
PhotoProject extension.
So, I'm going to select that and
I'm going to give this a name.
Picture show.
Hit the finished button.
And yes, I want to activate that
as a scheme it makes it really
easy to run later.
And then, I mentioned that my
designer is going to need these
assets.
So, they're already in the
project, I just want them,
basically referenced from within
the extension as well.
So, I'm just going to add those
via the copy phase.
And that's the whole set of
assets.
I just hit add and with that
we're ready to write some code.
Now, if you're looking closely,
you'll notice that Xcode has
already added this group for me
for Picture Show for my target.
And inside of it, it's already
laid down a view controller for
me that conforms to the protocol
that we have to implement.
So, I'm going to go into that
and first going to add some
properties.
So, just a very small set of
properties here.
I'm holding on to the context
that's handed to me.
I have some arrays to
differentiate landscape and
portrait assets for my
slideshow.
I have an outlet for my scene
view.
And I have an animator.
And I have two expected
compilers.
I have not imported seenkit.
So, that's an easy one to fix.
And animator is my own class.
I just haven't created it yet.
So, let's go ahead and do that
right now.
So, I hit new, I want a Swift
file.
And we will call this animator.
And there's my animator.
I'm not going to walk you
through all of this.
But it's really, really simple.
So, I'll just tell you a few
things it's doing.
When I'm initializing the
animation I want to kind of
reach into the scene and get out
some specific elements of the
scene.
I want to find these tagged
photo frames in this 3D scene.
And then reach kind of inside
them, behind the glass and get
at the material that is going to
be the photo I'm showing behind
the glass of these frames.
So, that's really all I'm doing
in the initialize.
And then from that point, the
scene, I know it's just going to
be spinning around.
It's just this kind of rotation
on a table and I have a little
trickery that you're like a good
magician when you're not looking
on switching photos.
And so, I'm just doing that
through a couple of timers.
And that's basically the
animation.
So, we'll go back to the
controller and start filling in
the interesting bits.
When a user creates one of these
projects, I want to save the
data.
Because I want them to be able
to come back to this slide show
at any point in time.
So, I'm just going to add some
data methods.
And what I've got here is a
SaveProjectDataFunction that
does exactly what you saw on the
slide, right?
So, this should look very
familiar with what we just
talked about.
And then load data, I'm simply
reading that back.
I'm getting the Cloud asset
identifiers by unarchiving my
data.
And I'm just converting to local
identifiers.
And from that point, I'm able to
do a PHAsset fetch assets
request with those local
identifiers.
All right.
Let's go back up to the top and
start filling in the rest.
So, viewDidLoad.
I just need to initialize my
animator.
We talked about that.
Supported project types.
In this case, I don't need to
ask the user for anything.
So, I won't fill that in.
It's just a slide show.
But begin project, obviously,
I've got some work I want to do
here.
So, we'll fill that in.
And what I'm doing in this case
is I'm getting at the actual
sections array.
And I'm looking for the first
section of typed content.
Right? I'm really designing this
around a memory, like we just
talk about.
And form that, I want the most
curated assets.
I want the top-level summary.
And so, I asked for the first
object in that array.
From that, get the
cloudAssetIdentifiers and I'm
good to go.
Now, in the background, I am
just saving the project data so
that it's there later if the
user comes back to the slide
show.
Get into resume project, and
that's really easy.
I simply hold on to my context
load my project data, initialize
the animation.
And finally, in finish project,
I'm just suspending animation.
I don't want these timers
firing, I don't want the fans
running while user's doing
something else.
I just suspend it.
And believe it or not, that is
the entirety of the code for
this extension.
That is my slide show.
Now, what I haven't don't is
wire up the UI, which I can do
really quickly.
So, the template gives me the
view for my view controlled.
I'll just delete the default
string.
And I'm going to add a scene to
this.
And so, we add a seenkit view.
I'll just resize that and just
pop in here, set my auto resize
and I just want this to be full
view.
And the only other thing you
need to do to that is choose the
scene itself, which I already
have in the assets that we
loaded in.
And I just need to wire it to my
view controller.
So, I'll control drag form
file's owner and I see the
outlet that we've already added
in properties.
And that's it.
We're ready to run.
So, I'll hit play.
It's going to ask me to choose
the app, obviously, it's Photos
in this case.
And that will build, and
succeed.
Photos launches, and I'm just
going to pick a memory.
In this case, I want to use,
I've got this really cool trip
to Hong Kong I'm going to
choose.
Hit the plus button and look at
that, there's the extension
showing up in Photos.
I choose that.
Now, when I do, this is the very
first time I run this extension,
so I don't have permission as an
extension to the entire photo
library.
You remember the our API is
handing the entire photo library
to the extension.
So, user does have to grant that
access once.
And just hit okay.
And then the slideshow loads.
[ Applause ]
And I'm just going to show you
one additional detail, if you
look in the sidebar, there's the
project we just created, Hong
Kong Island.
This is saved inside that
library right next to all the
other projects.
So, I choose that and I can see
this was created by an extension
called Picture Show.
And I can open that.
And it will pop right back into
the same slideshow.
So, that is PhotosPojects
Extensions [applause].
Thank you.
So, we've talked about a lot in
the past 55 minutes or so.
Talking about the frictionless
photo picker in iOS.
Really, really nice advancements
there, allowing you to get at
original URLs.
Having the video quality.
Some great, great stuff there
for you.
Andreas took you through the new
media presentation types, I
can't wait to see how you're
going to consume those and the
kind of things you do within
your apps.
Allowing users to see their
content played back the way
they'd expect.
He also talked about testing
with large image libraries.
And just a reminder there is a
sample app now to let you fill
out a library with tens of
thousands of assets so that you
can test that way.
And then, finally we talked
about the project extensions.
And I'm really, really excited
to see what your all going to
create and have in the App Store
when macOS High Sierra ships
this fall.
So, for more information please
check out this link, the
developer.apple.com website.
And I want to talk about some
related sessions.
Right after this in this hall is
going to be a killer, killer
session introducing you to
vision framework.
I know you want to stick around
for that.
Later tonight over in the
executive ballroom is the first
of two sessions covering depth
in iPhone photography with some
amazing demos and you really,
really want to be there for that
as well.
And finally, tonight we're doing
something we've never done that
WWDC.
We're hosting a photography get
together.
It's going to be downstairs in
technology lab area,
specifically lab J.
And I'll be there, the other 2
speakers in this session will be
there.
All of the speakers today
talking about Cameron Photos
will be there as well as a ton
of engineers, management, and we
hope to see all of you there.
Enjoy the rest of your show.
Thank you so much.
[ Applause ]