>> Thank you.
Good morning everybody, and
welcome to SceneKit in Swift
Playgrounds.
My name's Michael DeWitt and I'm
really excited today to give you
an inside look into how we use
SceneKit to make the Learn to
Code content.
So hopefully many of you are
already familiar with Swift
Playgrounds, but let me show you
Learn to Code.
So this is an example lesson
from the Learn to Code content
that lives inside Swift
Playgrounds.
On the left-hand side we have
the lesson and the user's code.
But for this talk we're really
going to focus on the right-hand
side.
Notice the live view.
If we could actually take that
full screen to get a little
better view of it.
This character, Byte, that is
now literally sprinting around
this map to collect the gems, is
moving up and down stairs and
after Byte has collected all the
gems, we get a congratulations
sequence that lets the learner
know they've done something
great, and Byte even has a few
dance moves to let people know
it's really good.
So this is our case study today.
We're going to work through this
scene on how to use SceneKit
effectively and really bring the
richness of 3D to your
applications.
So if you're interested in 3D
but are maybe pretty new to it,
you've come to the right place
because we actually started with
something very different than
this.
We started with a simple 2D
scene.
And one of the best parts about
SceneKit is it allowed a couple
of 2D programmers to take this
scene on an existing timeline
and make the rich 3D content
that we shift in Learn to Code.
So that's what we're going to
talk about today.
We've got 40 minutes and we've
broken it down into three
sections.
First, I'll talk about
prototyping and how we refined
the idea to make sure it was
really good.
In iterating I want to go over
when you're actually getting
some real assets from your
vendor, how you can establish an
effective pipeline.
And then Lamont will come on
stage to talk about tuning and
getting your scene ready to
ship.
First up is prototyping.
This is coming at a phase right
after we decided on the idea for
Learn to Code and we're really
ready to start building
something.
So you saw this graphic before,
but here it is in context.
We started off with gems that
came from the emoji tray and
assets we had lying around
because we just needed to get
something up and running as
quickly as possible to test the
interaction model in this new
app.
So we learned a lot from this.
It didn't matter what the assets
looked like, but through this
prototyping process we started
to get some early feedback.
Some of those comments were
about the graphics.
It was requests like could we
change the gem color, could we
add a border around the scene,
or could we pivot the camera at
the end to give a little bit of
visual interest.
While this is good feedback, it
really is very iterative, and
when you're prototyping, you
shouldn't be afraid to throw the
whole thing away.
And so if we go back and look at
the scene in context, you can
see it just is very flat on this
page.
So all of the feedback we're
getting is about the visual
look.
We need to just re-evaluate our
strategy.
So we had been working the
SpriteKit and now we started
exploring SceneKit.
And for many of you who are
familiar with SpriteKit, you'll
know that it has these concepts;
basically a scene to do your
update logic, a node to place
things in view, and actions to
move those objects around.
Now, the benefit of having
SceneKit also developed at Apple
is that it has a lot of those
same concepts.
So this gave us enough
confidence, a simple prefix
switch, to get started with
SceneKit and start diving in.
So like many of you out there,
we watched a WWDC presentation
from 2015.
It's a great talk given by the
SceneKit Team on how to build a
simple scene like the one you
see here, and not only that, but
we got to use some of the assets
from the sample and recreate our
scene.
So now we got to this stage and
immediately we could tell this
is just way better.
I mean, it's far more immersive,
you can freely pan the camera
and it actually helps you solve
the levels.
But the point of this slide is
that even though we've
definitely bumped up the visual
quality, when you're
prototyping, you still want to
keep that visual fidelity low.
So when we're adding new game
mechanics like these portals,
we're doing it with SceneKit
primitives because we don't want
to get too hung up on making
sure the scene looks absolutely
great.
We want to make sure it's a good
idea first.
So if I had to throw this up on
a Business Tool 101 chart, you
basically look at the whole
timeline of your project.
You want to allocate a large
chunk of that to prototyping
because it's the phase with
which you can make the biggest
changes and the effort to change
is low, especially when you're
working in 3D.
When you start to get real
assets, and in this next section
that we're going to talk about,
the effort to change goes way
up.
So be mindful of that when
you're prototyping.
So in summary, really, you want
to work on testing your
interaction model when you're
prototyping.
It's not about the assets.
You want to interpret the
feedback you receive, but don't
look for incremental changes.
Look to make sure the idea is
valid.
And then finally, take the
insights from this section,
believe the code.
I think one of the best
decisions we made was to
actually start file-new-project
when moving forward past this
point, which brings us to
iterating.
So now we've got the idea and
we're ready to get some real
art, so we started working with
an artist and we received this
early 2D comp.
So you can start to see it
resembles Byte's world now.
It looks way better.
And I want to break down this
world into four parts.
The first thing we'll talk about
is how it's constructed and some
strategies to do that
effectively.
Next, we'll look at how you can
accomplish complex animations in
your app by looking at how we
made Byte move up the stairs.
We'll look at how you can add
visual interests with water and
other scenery elements.
And then we're really focused on
the visuals in this talk, but
there's a whole other area of
your users that actually won't
be able to benefit from the
visuals of a 3D scene, so we're
going to spend some time talking
about accessibility support, and
VoiceOver specifically.
All right.
First up, modeling this world.
So as you can sort of see by the
stencil we built this out of
blocks.
We had individual assets.
There was a couple reasons to do
this.
We needed to not only iterate on
the asset design, but also on
the lesson design.
So we were putting together very
simple puzzles like this to make
sure that learners had a smooth
path through the curriculum.
But rather than placing these
individual blocks in a Scene
Editor, which would be pretty
tedious, we actually wrote some
code to do this.
So much like learners use in
Learn to Code 2 when they're
building their own worlds, we
wrote some code to generate this
and it looks like this.
So to build that world you first
give it a size, 5 by 5.
You place items into it, like
actor, or Byte in the scene you
saw before.
And then you can add additional
elements, such as gems or the
water that you saw in the
center.
But the reason I'm showing you
this code is not because, wow,
we wrote an API to build a
world, that's cool, but it's
really because this is totally
independent from the graphics.
Right. This code will be just as
valid in 2D as it is in 3D.
And let me show you actually
what I mean by that.
I have a short video here for
you.
So here we have Byte moving
around this world and we're
going to add in a few nodes.
The green and red nodes you see
in the scene actually represent
the data that we're
reconstructing gameplay with.
And then really, that data is
all we need.
We've actually separated the
visuals of the scene from the
data that's used to reconstruct
gameplay.
There are a couple of big
benefits to this, and I want you
to think about it when you're
modeling a 3D world.
So separate the data from
visuals.
First is it allows you to swap
out assets easily.
Remember, we're still iterating
on this stuff.
We will get a new version of the
block any day, and we don't want
to have to rebuild those maps,
so we're dynamically generating
them.
It also allows you to take that
data and send it elsewhere.
Maybe you need to send it across
a network or send some gameplay
logic across process, like we
were doing in some playgrounds.
And later on down the road it
will also allow you to optimize
the geometry.
And Lamont will get into that in
more detail, but it's really key
that you're not dependent on the
actual nodes and scene for this
to work well.
And I have one caveat.
You need some debugging tools to
make this work really well.
We found that out early on.
You can't just look at the world
anymore and see how gameplay
will be reconstructed, and so we
actually built a pretty simple
Mac app.
This app can actually load in
all the levels that we have, and
more than that, it has
scene-specific knowledge.
So in this case this is the tool
that allows us to show those
debugging nodes you saw before,
and it also can run hard-to-hit
cases in our game, like rotating
around the world when you hit
the congratulations sequence.
We want to make sure that works
on every map, but we don't want
to test every map all the way to
the end just to see that work.
So that's our first stop.
That's how we put the world
together.
We separated the data from
visuals and we used tools.
Now on to animations.
So if we look closely at the
stairs, you can see this is
actually a fairly complicated
piece of geometry.
Right. Not only are there
individual steps, but there are
little cutouts from the step.
So we want to be super precise
about where our character's foot
lands on each step.
So we considered a couple
different strategies, and one
thing that's pretty common for
3D scenes to use is just swap
this out for a ramp because
ramps are easy.
You have a character, you move
that character forward, you
figure out how far up they need
to move, and you just translate
them from point A to point B
while running the walk cycle.
For stairs, not so great.
So here's Byte trying to walk up
the stairs, and if you look
closely, Byte hasn't even gotten
to the first step and he's
already floating in midair.
So we need to do something a
little bit better.
The second thing we considered
is using a built-in type in
SceneKit.
It's actually part of SceneKit's
constraint system to be able to
do inverse kinematics.
Now, inverse kinematics allow
you to be super precise about
where you want the character's
foot to land.
So we would specify each step
where we wanted the character to
take, but it comes with a
sacrifice of some personality in
the character.
Right. We're not able to control
the eye movement or the upper
body as detailed as we'd like.
So we actually went with a third
option, and that's to bake the
displacement into the animation.
And so because this is the one
we went with, let me break it
down for you in a little bit
more detail.
Usually, most games you have a
node, which represents a
position, and you have geometry,
which is what you're actually
seeing in the scene.
Now, it's common for these two
things to move together, so you
translate the node and the
geometry, while playing the walk
cycle, it moves the character
from point A to point B.
But for the stairs we did
something different.
We leave the node alone and we
apply an animation, which
actually has displacement in it.
So this moves the geometry away
from the node and then when that
animation is complete, we
synchronize the node's position
and remove the animation.
We do that with a type in
SceneKit called an
SCNTransaction.
And SCNTransactions allow you to
make sure that update happens in
one frame.
So let me show you what that
looks like.
You set up the transaction with
the begin and commit calls, and
in our case we want an animation
duration of zero because we need
it to happen in the exact same
frame.
We move the character to the new
position and we remove the
animations, making Byte ready
for the next round of
animations.
So let's see this in action.
Got to stretch it out first,
walks up the stairs, and you can
see now, because we're allowing
our animator the freedom to put
the displacement in the
animation, we can be far more
precise about Byte's movements.
Byte's head turns while it walks
up and down the stairs.
So this is a much better
solution and something you
should consider for complex
animations in your scenes.
On to train stop number three,
and that's to look at how we did
the scenery elements, because
it's not all about the
character.
You also need to make sure the
world feels alive.
So let's take a close look at
the water.
Now, you saw before we have been
using maps like this, right,
fairly basic, just enough to
reconstruct the puzzle with, but
we want to get to a point where
our maps look like this.
And the way we did that is to
actually save the original map
out to an SCN file so we can add
in those additional elements.
Right. So instead of writing
code to place each scenery
element, we can do it in the
Scene Editor now because it
makes much more sense.
So if we look at that in the
SceneKit Scene Editor, it looks
great, but now we're investing a
ton of time and effort into each
individual map.
You can see that by the node
hierarchy on the left there.
So the problem is you still want
to keep some amount of
flexibility.
Make sure if the artist comes in
next week and says I have a new
waterfall that would look so
much better, you're not changing
out at 81 maps.
And the way to do that, if we
look closely at the waterfall,
is to use a technique called
reference nodes.
So these are the water nodes in
our scene and the arrow
indicates that they're being
referenced out to a single SCN
file.
So you update that file in one
place and it propagates through
all your maps.
Now, that's not all there is to
water.
If we take a closer look at that
SCN file, water kind of also has
to move for it to be
interesting.
Right. The artist did a great
job here, the texture looks
amazing, but it's not real.
So in order to accomplish moving
the water, we're using a
technique, a geometry modifier,
actually writing a shader, and
you access that by the button
down in the lower right here.
I'll zoom in on it for you a
little bit.
It's going to be hard to see.
And that will bring up a tray,
new in Xcode 9, where you can
modify -- or you can specify
your geometry modifier built off
this SCN shader geometry type
provided to you by SceneKit.
Now, all this is doing is moving
the texture around the
waterfall, but it adds a great
effect.
So let's check it out in action.
There we go.
So now the water actually is
flowing, you can just see the
textures moving around and it
adds this great effect.
And we use that same technique
for the vines that sway in the
scene and for the grass that
blows in the breeze.
So this can add a lot of life to
your scene and it's a great
technique for you to try out.
That's three.
And we've really been focused on
the visuals.
We've taken a number of stops to
figure out how you can make that
great, but there's a whole other
aspect you have to consider and
that's what the scene would look
like to a visually-impaired
user.
So when you're trying to design
a great experience in VoiceOver,
you want to focus on things
other than the visuals
obviously, but without
describing everything we did, I
first want you to just listen to
the experience.
[ Music ]
>> VoiceOver on.
Landscape.
The world is five columns by
five rows.
Column 0, row 0, [inaudible] at
height 0 facing north.
Double attach to switch
characters.
Column 0, row 1, gem at height
0.
[ Music ]
>> So we did a number of things
to support VoiceOver in Learn to
Code, but the first thing I want
you to notice is we're actually
focusing on a great nonvisual
experience.
By adding music, by adding
character noises, you make the
scene auditorily rich.
There's other things we added to
VoiceOver, and to go for a deep
dive on those techniques, you
can check out a great talk this
year about how to make your
media and games accessible.
The one that was really
important for us is actually
describing the important
locations using VoiceOver, and
the reason I want to show you
this in more detail is because
it's surprisingly easy to do.
So just like in your UIKit apps
we're overriding an
accessibility element so that we
can provide a custom label.
In this case we're providing a
label which is updated with the
current contents of the world.
So this is basically the same
technique you're already used to
in UIKit, and it really is that
simple.
You create one of those
elements, you specify its frame,
we're using projectPoint from
SceneKit to get from 3D to 2D,
and you add that element to the
view.
So my point is even though 3D
seems really tough to make
accessible, it's quite easy and
it's already techniques you're
familiar with.
So there are really three main
reasons to support it.
One, it's great for your users.
It's probably one of the most
rewarding aspects, that I
thought, of working on this
project.
One of the aspects that I
thought was most rewarding.
Excuse me.
Two, is that it's just easy to
do.
It's many of the familiar things
you're used to from UIKit
development.
And three, just like there are
no excuses for not making your
apps in UIKit accessible, there
really should be no excuses for
doing so in 3D.
So if you want to see this code
in full detail, you can always
check out the source for Learn
to Code by diving into the
auxiliary sources in the
Playground book, and this file
actually sits in
Accessibilityextensions.swift.
So that is iterating.
We talked about how you should
separate your data from the
visuals of your scene.
Right. We did that for modeling
the world, but also how we did
the stair animation.
You should value flexibility
even at this phase.
So when you're putting all that
time and effort into your
levels, make sure you're doing
things like using reference
nodes so that you still have
some flexibility.
And then finally, make sure you
audit that accessibility support
early.
It's not something that can be
bolted on at the end, and it's
surprisingly easy to do if you
plan for it.
Now to talk about how we took
these design time assets and
really tuned them up to make
them super performant, I'm going
to invite Lamont up to the
stage.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Michael.
That's great [applause].
Hello everyone.
I'm Lamont.
I'm an engineer on the Swift
Playgrounds' Content Team, and
today I'm going to talk to you
about how you can improve the
performance of your SceneKit
apps in terms of frame rate and
user experience.
When we first started developing
Learn to Code, one of the things
that was critical for us was to
have a really rich and detailed
world, and as you can see here,
that's exactly what we have.
The waterfalls look realistic,
the shadows behind the
staircases look pretty good, the
colors are rich and vivid.
We even have nice statues hidden
in the waterfalls there.
But as you know, a good-looking
application isn't the only
aspect of a great experience.
It's also performance.
So what does that actually mean?
To have a good experience we
actually want to have a really
responsive frame rate.
Your users are interacting with
your application, they're
pinching, they're gesturing,
they're adding things to the
scene, removing things.
You want this to be really fast
and very fluid.
So I'm going to show you how we
actually increased the
performance of our application
in Learn to Code.
Let's take a look at one of our
geometrically complex scenes.
And when I say geometrically
complex, what I mean is this
scene is comprised of thousands
of individual geometry parts.
Now, each of these parts have to
be rendered separately by the
GPU.
So let's take a look at what the
performance of our application
is.
SceneKit has a really useful
tool called the Debug Statistics
View and I want to zoom in on it
now and take a look at it.
Now, you can enable this in your
applications by simply setting
the showStatistics property on
your view to true.
If we take a look at some of the
more interesting numbers on this
debug view, you'll notice we
have a low frame rate, 29 frames
per second.
That's not very great.
What we actually really want is
60 frames per second minimum.
This allows us to get that fluid
interaction as the users are
pinching and gesturing around.
Well, what contributes to this
low frame rate?
Well, let's break it down.
What are we doing on each frame?
This number here, the rendering
number, is the amount of time
we're taking to render one
complete frame.
It looks like we're taking 20.4
milliseconds.
That's pretty slow.
If you do the math, if you want
to hit 60 frames per second, you
have to be under 16
milliseconds.
So what are we doing that's
taking 20 milliseconds?
Well, to aid in that, one thing
we can look at is the number of
draw calls, as you can see
highlighted by this diamond.
Now, what's a draw call?
A quick refresher.
When you want to draw objects in
a scene, the CPU has to tell
GPU, hey, draw this mesh.
The CPU draws this mesh or a
geometry object, and that's one
draw call.
It looks like we have 877 of
them.
That's quite a bit of draw
calls.
So what are some of the things
we could do to actually increase
the performance of our app?
Well, I'm going to share with
you one tip.
The theme throughout the rest of
the talk is how do we reduce our
draw call count.
I'm going to talk to you about
that in three distinct phases;
geometry, which are those meshes
that comprise the scene;
materials, which give our scene
a nice look; and lighting, which
kind of brings our scene to
life.
Let's take a look at an example
level that we showed earlier.
Now, this scene has lots of
individual parts.
I want to focus in on one type,
the grass.
Now, if you look closely, and
you're good at math, you can
count, there are roughly 30
individual tiles in this screen,
each have their own mesh, so the
CPU has to tell the GPU to
render these things one-by-one,
so we get 30 draw calls.
Now, this is a small scene.
Imagine if you wanted to have
like a huge expansive world with
thousands of these tiles.
Now we're going to have
thousands of draw calls.
Imagine what happens to our
frame rate then.
One thing you might notice is
these grass tiles may not
actually move, so if they don't
move, why are we drawing so many
of them?
Could we draw perhaps one big
mesh?
That's possible.
There's one rule I want you to
remember, is when you're talking
to the GPU, there's one draw
call per mesh.
You have a thousand meshes, you
have a thousand draw calls.
So if we look at our grass tile
and we want to actually combine
them somehow, that sounds like a
reasonable technique.
I'm going to show you how we can
do that.
Let's say we have two geometry
objects in our scene.
On our left we have a grass
tile.
On our right we have another
grass tile.
They both reference the same
material, they have the same
look, they're just displaced and
they have different locations in
3D space.
When you send this to the GPU,
you're going to get two draw
calls.
If we merge the two together
through a process called
flattening, what we're doing is
saying let's take all the points
out of mesh A and combine them
with the points in mesh B into
one super-Godzilla mesh.
The beauty of this is now all
these points reference just that
one material and when the CPU
talks to the GPU, all it has to
do is say, hey, draw this one
thing.
Done. Now, this sounds pretty
trivial and it's really easy to
use.
You can use it in your
applications by a method on
SCNNode called flattenedClone,
and what you want to do here is
just make sure that there's a
parent node that contains the
nodes that you want to flatten,
and the return of this is a new
flattened mesh that you can
composite in your scene and
replace the other nodes.
Now, this simple technique was
used throughout Learn to Code.
So if we take our level that I
showed you earlier, I'm going to
break down the sections at which
we were able to run this
flattening logic.
I'm going to highlight in red
the areas that were flattened
together.
So you can see here, our water
now -- the grass tile is much
fewer draw calls.
And each of these red sections
equates to one draw call,
instead of an individual draw
call.
So we were able to greatly
reduce the number of draw calls
in our scene.
We went from over 550 draw calls
to less than 16.
This is huge.
[ Applause ]
Thank you.
Now, you have to use a bit of
discretion here because you
don't want to just go all
willy-nilly and, you know,
flatten all the things.
The reason why is, as Michael
showed you earlier, he made the
water look really realistic by
adding that simple shader
modifier that gave us this
really great effect.
So if we were to flatten
everything, the whole world
would kind of drip away.
That's not what we want.
So we were selective in choosing
what things to flatten.
So we flattened the waterfalls
altogether.
In your worlds or games that you
create you may choose to have an
object that disappears or moves
or scales or rotates, or somehow
it gets modified.
So I think the takeaway here is
based on how you want to use
your geometry, if there's
something dynamic about it, you
may want to keep flattening it
with other things that move in
the exact same way.
So I'm going to give you a
couple of tips on working with
flattening.
One is you want to store your
nodes that you want to flatten
in the same group, parent group,
parent node.
And it doesn't have to be the
same type of geometry like we're
using grass tiles here, but
let's say you're modeling a
living room and you have a sofa
and a chair and a table, and
they don't move relative to each
other.
They're all good candidates to
put in one node group and
flatten by itself.
So you want to be really
aggressive here and anything
that doesn't move relative to
something else, flatten it and
you'll reduce your draw call
count significantly.
Now, there is a caveat here.
Learn to Code's world is pretty
static in terms of it's a small
world that's always visible on
the screen, but for your world,
you may do something really
expansive where you have to go
into a building or you're on a
large terrain or you have
levels.
So what you want to do here --
what you don't want to do is
atlas everything all willy-nilly
because what's going to happen
is if you have an atlas of this
entire world, of which only a
portion is visible in the scene
at any one time, you're going to
pay the performance cost of
rendering all these points and
all the meshes, and that's not
what you want.
A simple technique here is to
simply subdivide your world into
discrete chunks and then run
this process on each of those
chunks, and as you move from
chunk-to-chunk, as the camera
moves from chunk-to-chunk,
you're actually getting the
benefits of flattening without
paying the overhead of rendering
everything in your scene at
once.
Next I'd like to talk to you
about materials.
Now, materials have an even
bigger impact on your draw call
count, and I'll get into why.
Here's a still frame from that
movie I showed earlier, where we
show that we flattened this
aspect of the scene, the top of
the world mostly, into one mesh.
So this is one draw call.
But the astute observers of you
out there that may notice, hey,
there are multiple materials
here, like obviously those
stonehenges don't have the same
materials as the staircase, and
surely not the stones
themselves.
So what's going on here?
Let's talk about reducing
materials because that's what we
did to get this down to one draw
call.
So again, we have our two
geometry objects on the screen;
one on the left, one on the
right.
One uses the sand texture, one
uses this more sand/grass
looking texture.
If we run the logic that I
showed you before, flattening,
we actually get that one
combined, Godzilla mesh, but
we're still referencing two
materials.
So when the CPU has to talk to
the GPU, it's going to say, hey,
take this mesh and draw the sand
material with it.
Great. Okay.
Now, take this mesh again and
draw the parts of it that uses
the grass material again.
You still get two draw calls.
There's an opportunity here to
reduce this.
And you may have heard of
texture atlasing, but maybe you
don't understand exactly what
that is.
It's a very simple process.
Your artist, and their 3D tools,
would take your materials and
combine them into one texture
atlas and under the covers
they'll update your geometry so
that it's pointing to the right
bits inside your textures, but
the net result is you have one
draw call.
Now, this works if you have a
few objects or thousands of
objects.
In Learn to Code I'll give you
an example of one of the atlases
for the world that I just showed
you.
This is what our atlas looked
like.
We had over 70 materials that we
were able to condense down into
one.
That's a huge savings.
There's another benefit here
that you may not be aware of.
When you have a material in your
scene, when your scene loads,
there's a shader that has to be
generated behind the scenes and
you can't start your scene until
that shader's actually finished
compiling.
If you have 70 materials, you
have 70 shaders.
You have a really rich level
with hundreds of objects,
hundreds of materials, now all
of a sudden your load time --
you're stuck waiting for the
scene to load.
By combining it into one
material, or fewer materials,
you're reducing the number of
shaders that need to get
compiled, boosting your startup
time, not to mention lesser I/O
in terms of hitting a disk.
So next I want to talk about
lighting.
Now, lighting's very interesting
because lighting is what allows
you to add rich, vivid detail to
your world.
You can take a scene and it
looks kind of static, kind of
boring.
You add lights, now it gets a
little interesting.
So we let our artists put a few
lights in the scene and give us
this visual effect.
We add a spotlight so that when
the characters went around the
world, they're casting shadows
as they move along the water or
the grass.
It's a nice effect.
We added omni-directional lights
scattered throughout the scene
to add a little visual pop.
So you can see the staircases in
the foreground are highlighted a
little bit more than the
staircases in the background.
And lastly, we added an ambient
light, which makes sure that
everything in the scene is
visible; otherwise, you'd have
really super dark areas where
the other lights don't hit.
And you can see this sort of
great effect if you look in the
shadows of where the water is.
It's really neat.
Now, there's a performance cost
to this.
Lights are not free.
Remember I told you that draw
calls, the more you have the
less performant you are, your
application is?
Well, whenever you have a light
that hits a mesh, that's an
extra draw call.
So you have five lights in your
scene, you just increased your
draw call count by five.
There's a way to get around
this, and it's called a light
map.
Now, what this is, is your
artist, and their 3D tool, will
basically run a process that
calculates where the lights are.
They can go to town, put all the
lights they want in there, light
all the things, and it would
actually precompute the
intensity of the light hitting
your scene and it would store it
in a material, not unlike the
textures we showed you earlier.
The beauty of this is that this
process is not CPU or GPU
intensive.
As a matter of fact, it's free.
It's taking me more energy to
talk about it than the CPU would
actually spend applying this.
So we are able to take our light
count down to zero if we wanted.
Now, we didn't.
We left one spotlight in there
because we distinguished between
lights that don't change every
frame, why should we render
these lights again, we did it
the last frame and nothing
changed, but the spotlight does
change.
As you rotate the world the
spotlight's going to hit the
objects in a different way.
When you have your character
walking around the world, its
shadow is going to cast on the
rest of the world in a different
way.
So we kept it, but we made sure
that we were specific as to what
it would apply to, the
characters or certain parts of
the scene.
And the good thing about this is
it works in tandem with all the
flattening that I showed you
earlier, because obviously
lights act like a multiplier in
terms of your draw calls.
Well, guess what.
We reduced the first term.
We reduced the number of meshes
that have to be lit.
So if we actually really wanted
to put another light in there,
the effect wouldn't be as bad as
when we started.
So after making all of these
changes, let's take a look at
our performance and see where we
are now.
Let's zoom in.
Actually, I want to take a
moment to just appreciate how
good the light maps look.
If you take a look behind the
first staircase, you see that
little dark shadow and the
crevices and even behind the
waterfall slightly is a little
darker, around the rocks and the
curved areas in the stonehenge,
it looks really great.
And you know what, you're not
paying anything for it.
It was done all offline using
material.
Our artist went crazy with
lights and their 3D tool.
Now I'll zoom in on the
performance.
Wow, we're hitting 60 fps now.
Our users won't be closing our
app and going to go do something
else.
Let's look at our rendering
time.
We're at 2.3 milliseconds.
Now, that's fantastic, for a
number of reasons.
Number one, remember we said you
have to get under 16
milliseconds to be able to
actually render at 60 fps?
Well, that new iPad that just
came out, if you want to take
advantage of 120 hertz
technology refresh rate, you
want to get that number under 7.
We're under 2, so we're good.
Crank it up.
So let's talk about headroom.
The beauty of this low number is
if you want to add more things
to your scene, maybe you want to
add a little bit more gameplay
logic using GameplayKit, or you
wanted to do some networking or
you wanted to just make your
scene rich, tell your artist,
hey, crank it up, let's make
some more objects in our scene,
make it more detailed, or you
just want to enjoy your better
battery life, you can do that.
Finally, let's look at that draw
call count.
Wow, 73. If you remember, the
earlier number was over 700.
We're using less than a tenth of
the draw call amount than we had
before.
We're sipping power instead of
guzzling it like we were before.
This is great.
Our app is very fluid.
And when I talk about headroom
again, you have to remember
you're going to be doing other
things in your app other than
just rendering.
In our case, we have the Swift
Compiler running on the left,
potentially.
The users were editing code and
clicking on menu items, and
things like that.
And in your application maybe
the user's doing something like
pinching or doing some selection
or, you know, anything that
would actually take more
processing time in terms of
logic in your application.
So that's great.
So to recap, we've talked about
flattening geometry, how this is
the low-hanging fruit of
performance optimizations in
terms of reducing your draw call
count.
We talked about using a texture
atlas, which is something that
you get your artist to do and
you just take advantage of that
will reduce the number of
materials that you use, which
has an impact on loading time,
making your app start up much
faster, and also an impact on
disk I/O, making it less objects
to load.
And lastly, it works in tandem
with the geometry flattening to
make sure that you have the
fewest amount of draw calls
possible.
And lastly, using light maps to
add that rich visual detail to
your scene and not pay any
performance penalty for it on
the GPU.
Let your artist go crazy.
We have a few related sessions
for you.
Thanks, and have a great WWDC.
[ Applause ]