My name is John Blackwell.
And I'm an engineer on the Core
Motion framework.
Today, we're going to be talking
about creating immersive
applications with the Core
Motion framework.
And we're also going to discuss
a number of best practices along
the way.
So today we're going to be
covering a number of things.
The first is a brief overview of
what Core Motion provides.
Next, we're going to talk about
authorization, a frequent pain
point for many of our
developers.
Then we're going to look at some
new additions to Historical
Accelerometer.
And then we're going to dig into
DeviceMotion, the sensor fusion
that we provide in Core Motion.
And finally, we're going to look
at Badger with Attitude, a game
where we'll take some of the
concepts that we've talked about
in DeviceMotion and put them
into practice.
And with that, let's take a
closer look at the Core Motion
framework.
The Core Motion framework
provides access to the
accelerometer, the gyroscope,
the magnetometer, and the
altimeter.
And through the framework, you
can access raw forms of the
sensor data as well as processed
forms and use these in your
applications.
Now, there are a number of
interfaces available through
Core Motion.
The first is CMMotionManager,
which provides access to the raw
sensor data as well as the
sensor fusion in the form of
DeviceMotion.
CMAltimeter provides access to
relative altitude updates for
the device.
CMPedometer provides access to
step counts as separate related
information as well as work out
pause and resume events.
MotionActivityManager provides
access to the activity context
for the device, for example,
walking, running, or automotive,
etcetera.
And CMSensorRecorder provides
access to historical
accelerometer data.
So that's a brief overview of
what the Core Motion framework
provides.
Next, let's take a closer look
at authorization.
So of the APIs that I just
mentioned, these following four
are sensitive due to the nature
of the private information that
they expose about the user.
So to handle this, we have a
prompt that appears the first
time you invoke one of the
sensitive APIs.
Keep in mind that the first time
you invoke the sensitive APIs, a
prompt will appear for your
users.
But after that first time, your
users will need to go into
settings to change the
authorization state for your
applications.
Now, let's take a look at what
it looks like the first time you
call one of these APIs.
At this point, your users will
need to decide if they want to
grant access to the motion and
fitness data or deny access.
And, as a developer, you're
going to want to handle the case
where they deny access.
Now, in the past we've asked you
to do something like this where
you call any of our APIs that
are sensitive, in this case
we're calling
QueryPedometerData, and then you
ignore the result that you get
back from the API and only look
at the error code.
And if the error code is not
authorized, at this point you
know your application has been
denied access to that motion and
fitness data.
Now, we realize that this is
less than ideal.
You need to jump through hoops
to get access to your
authorization state.
And once you get it, you can't
tell exactly why your app has
been denied access and that's
why, this year, we're providing
an Authorization Status API.
This API is available in the
same four classes that I
mentioned before, and it's
available on iOS and watchOS.
Let's take a closer look at the
CMAuthorizationStatus value that
you'll get back from this API.
The first state not determined
represents the state before the
user has been asked about
authorization in your
application.
Restricted represents the state
where the user is unable to
change the authorization state
for your application
specifically.
And this can happen when motion
and fitness is disabled in
privacy.
The next state, denied, means
what it sounds like.
You're application has been
specifically denied access by
the users.
And authorized means your app is
ready to access the users motion
and fitness data.
Now, let's come back to the
authorization check that we were
looking at before.
One of the first best practices
that I want to talk about is
making sure that you check for
the availability of a given API
first before you ask for the
authorization status.
In this case, we're asking for
isStepCountingAvailable.
And the next thing that you're
going to want to do is query for
the authorization status.
And at this point, it's up to
you, as a developer, to decide
how you want to handle the
authorization that you get back
from the framework.
You now have a simple mechanism
for doing this on both iOS and
watchOS.
I encourage you to consider how
you can use the authorization
app, authorization status API in
your applications, and you
should definitely use it.
Next, we're going to talk about
Historical Accelerometer.
Historical Accelerometer, also
known as CMSensorRecorder,
provides 50Hz accelerometer
data.
And we can record this for your
applications while your apps are
in the background.
You can request up to 36 hours
of accelerometer data.
And this data will be stored on
your behalf for up to three
days.
Now, Historical Accelerometer is
currently available on Apple
Watch.
And today, I'm excited to
announce that it's now available
on iPone 7 and 7 Plus.
This opens up a whole new set of
use cases for your applications.
And to get you thinking about
how you can use Historical
Accelerometer on iPhone, let
walk through one sample
application now.
So let's say you're a big
automotive enthusiast.
And you want to build an
application to enable you to
track your car's performance
over a long track day.
How would we go about building
this?
Well, the first thing that we
want to figure out is when the
user is driving.
And for that, we can use Motion
Activity.
Motion Activity provides an
automotive state.
And we can use this to determine
the periods in which the user is
driving.
Now, I want to take a brief
minute to talk about the
automotive detection.
In iOS 11, the automotive
detection has received special
attention to ensure
best-in-class performance.
This automotive state in Motion
Activity is the same state
that's being used to power Do
Not Disturb While Driving and is
also available for you to use in
your applications if, say, you
wanted to personalize your
applications UI while the user
is driving.
Now, coming back to our
automotive performance tracking
application, the next thing we
want to do is we want to gather
the accelerometer data.
And for that we can use Sensor
Recorder.
We can gather the accelerometer
data for the periods in which
the user is driving and
translate that into metrics for
the user such as how many Gs
they were pulling through a turn
or maximum lateral Gs or
longitudinal Gs.
Now, there are many different
ways you could consider building
this kind of application, but by
using the Motion APIs you can
provide your users with a
low-power, all-day experience.
Now, there are a number of best
practices to keep in mind with
Historical Accelerometer.
The first is that you want to
choose the minimum duration that
makes sense for your
applications.
So for our automotive
performance tracking
application, we may not need the
full 36 hours of data, something
more like 8 to 12 hours would
make more sense.
And the next best practice to
keep in mind is to consider
decimating or dropping samples
if you don't need the full 50Hz
accelerometer data.
These two suggestions, these two
best practices will reduce the
amount of processing that your
application is doing and, in
turn, save the user's battery
life.
Now, I encourage you to consider
how you can use Historical
Accelerometer on iPhone.
Next, let's talk about
DeviceMotion.
DeviceMotion is the name for the
sensory fusion algorithm that we
provide in the Core Motion
framework.
Now, there are a number of
things that go into
DeviceMotion.
The first sensor that we use in
DeviceMotion is the
accelerometer.
And the accelerometer enables us
to measure the accelerations
imparted by the user as well as
the acceleration imparted by
gravity.
The gyroscope enables us to
precisely measure the rotation
rate of the device.
And the magnetometer allows us
to measure local fields around
the device as well as the
Earth's magnetic field.
Now, when dealing with the raw
sensors, there's a number of
challenges to keep in mind.
With the accelerometer, it can
be difficult to distinguish from
the accelerations imparted by
the user and from those
accelerated -- from those
imparted by the force of
gravity.
With the gyroscope, we can have
bias in the measurements over
time.
And with the magnetometer, it
can be difficult to distinguish
between the local fields and the
Earth's magnet field.
And this is where DeviceMotion
comes in.
DeviceMotion provides 3D
attitude tracking while the
device is undergoing free space
motion.
And it does this by fusing
together all of the sensors to
give the advantages of each
while minimizing the
disadvantages.
And as a developer, what this
really means is that it enables
you to focus on how you want to
use the motion data rather than
the mechanics of trying to get
the best from the sensors.
Now, we've talked about
DeviceMotion in a number of
previous sessions.
I encourage you to check them
out.
We go into details about the
sensors and the DeviceMotion
algorithms.
But today, we're going to think
about how we can use certain
aspects of DeviceMotion to
create immersive applications
for your users.
So as a developer, when you're
first getting started with
DeviceMotion, the first thing
that you need to consider are
the reference frames.
The reference frames determine
which sensors are used in the
fusion and how attitude is
calculated for your
applications.
The first reference frame,
xArbitraryZVertical fuses
together the accelerometer and
the gyroscope but does not use
the magnetometer.
And the last three reference
frames, xArbitraryCorrected,
xMagnaticNorth, and
xTrueNorthZVertical use all
three sensors.
Now, let's talk about the first
reference frame in more detail.
Let's say you've got an awesome
racing game where you're
currently using touch controls
to allow your users to steer in
the game.
This is great, but we could
provide a more immersive
experience using motion.
And what we want to do is we
want to enable our users to
steer using their device.
So when they tilt a car, tilt
their device to the left, the
car will turn left.
Now, as long as a device is
relatively static, we can use
the accelerometer to estimate
the force of gravity.
And once we have gravity, we can
use that to determine the tilt
or the angle offset from
gravity.
One thing to keep in mind,
though, is that if you were
using the accelerometer on its
own, certain gestures can be
ambiguous.
Tilting the device to the right
can look the same to the
accelerometer as sliding the
device to the left.
Now, one way you could consider
dealing with this is by
averaging over the accelerometer
signal.
In doing so, you would reduce
the short-term effects from the
user and leave only the
long-term effects such as the
force of gravity.
However, in doing this, you
would notice your application
would now respond more slowly
and this where DeviceMotion
comes in.
DeviceMotion means that your
application doesn't need to
build up filtering logic to get
great performance from sensors.
With the xArbitraryZVertical
reference frame, this is the
default reference frame that
your application will receive if
you don't explicitly specify one
when you start DeviceMotion
updates.
And this reference frame is
great for use cases where you
want to track the tip and the
tilt of the device.
And for our use case in the
game, the accelerometer and the
gyroscope are going to fuse
together to allow us some more
quickly and precisely track
gravity.
And once we have gravity we can
translate that into tilt for our
game.
Now to walk through exactly how
to do this, my co-worker Ahmad
is going to come to the stage a
bit later and show us.
This reference frame is also
great for use cases where you
want to track gestures from the
user.
I encourage you to check out our
sample application SwingWatch.
SwingWatch is an app that runs
on the watch that uses
DeviceMotion to track when
you've made a forehand or a
backhand gesture during a tennis
game.
Both the sample code and the
session are online.
And I encourage you to check
them out.
So let's say you've got another
game.
Let's say it's a shooter game
where you allow the user to aim
using virtual thumbsticks.
This is great but we could
provide a more immersive
experience using Motion.
And what we want to do is we
want to determine where the user
is pointing their device and
have that translate into aiming
in the game.
And for that we want to use
Attitude.
Attitude provides the rotation
from the reference frame fixed
when you first start
DeviceMotion updates to where
the user is currently holding
the device in 3D space.
Now, one way you could consider
getting Attitude is by taking
the integral of the raw
gyroscope signal.
Your sway will determine the
attitude.
However, this method for
determining the attitude would
drift overtime due to bias in
the gyroscope and that's where
the xArbitraryCorrectedZVertical
reference frame comes in.
This reference frame uses the
magnetometer to improve the
horizontal attitude estimation
that we provide.
And, as a developer, what this
reference frame means to you is
it provides reliable attitude
performance with a fixed center
reference.
So in the game your users can
move the device around and then
come back to a known center
location.
Now, there are many other ways
you can consider using this
reference frame.
Let's say you wanted to build a
360 degree photo and video
player application.
Your users would be able to move
their device around and then
bring it back towards the center
towards the dock overlooking the
lake.
Now, another way you could
consider using this reference
frame is for something like a
virtual reality real estate
application where you want to
allow your users to look around
at different parts of a room
just by moving their device.
Now, let's say you build this
application out and your users
love it, but they want to get a
better sense of in which
direction the windows face or in
which direction they can expect
the sun to rise and for that we
want a world reference.
Now, you could consider using
the magnetometer for this.
This would provide a world
reference and enable your
applications to orient with
respect to the world.
However, using the raw
magnetometer, you would find the
outputs susceptible to
disturbances.
Some of these are inherent to
the device, and some of these
are external to the device.
This is where the final two
reference frames come in.
These reference frames use the
magnetometer to orient the
device with respect to -- with
respect to the world.
And these reference frames
handle magnet device level
effects as well as in
challenging magnetometer
situations.
We can stabilize the output.
Now, choosing between these two
reference frames is going to be
based on the needs of your
application.
If you've already got data
that's referencing true north,
for example map data, it would
make sense to use the
xTrueNorthZVertical reference
frame.
Now, how can we consider using
these reference frames?
Well, one example is things like
star gazing applications where
you want to allow your users to
point their device at a star in
the sky and identify it.
Another way you could consider
using these reference frames are
for things like augmented
reality applications where you
want to fuse the camera data
with a world reference and for
that we encourage you to check
out ARKit.
ARKit's session follows
immediately after this one.
Now, let's come back to our
virtual reality real estate
application.
Let's say you built an
application out and your users
love it, but you want to provide
them with more features.
Let's say you want to put
landmarks on the horizon in the
direction that they actually
are.
How would we go about doing
this?
Well, what we want is Heading.
Heading gives us the direction
the device is pointing with
respect to north.
So when the device is pointing
straight towards north, Heading
would return 0 degrees.
And as the user rotates their
device around, the Heading angle
would update.
Now, one way you could consider
getting Heading is by using
CoreLocation.
CoreLocation provides a start
updating Heading API that you
could then use the heading from
and fuse that in with the data
that you're already getting from
DeviceMotion.
One thing to keep in mind,
though, is that CoreLocation's
Heading can fuse course.
Course is the direction of
travel for the device.
Now, this may make sense for
things like turn-by-turn
navigation applications, but for
things like augmented reality,
this may make less sense.
I encourage you to check out
CoreLocation session on Thursday
for more details.
Now, another way you could
consider getting Heading is by
calculating it from the attitude
estimation that we provide in
DeviceMotion.
However, getting this right in
all circumstances is
non-trivial.
And this is why, this year,
we're now adding Heading as a
first class property in
DeviceMotion.
Heading fuses together the
accelerometer, the gyroscope,
and most importantly the
magnetometer to give us the
direction the device is pointing
with respect to north.
Keep in mind that Heading is
only available on iOS where the
magnet field property is
available.
Now, let's take a closer look at
the API.
Heading is only valid for the
XMagneticNorth and XTrueNorth
reference frames.
For the other two reference
frames, you'll receive a
negative value back from
Heading.
And Heading will give you from 0
to 359 degrees from the x-axis
that you've chosen in your
application, either
MagneticNorth or TrueNorth.
Now that we have Heading, we can
use that to overlay the Golden
Gate Bridge on the horizon in
the direction that it actually
is.
Now, with DeviceMotion, there
are a number of best practices
to keep in mind.
The first is that you want to
make sure that you check for the
availability of a given
reference frame before you start
updates.
And to do that you can use the
available attitude reference
frames API.
This will return you a
CMAttitudeReferenceFrame
bit-mask that you can then and
with the reference frame that
you're interested in to
determine availability.
And the next thing to keep in
mind is that the choice of
reference frame is key for your
applications.
This is going to determine how
attitude is calculated in your
applications as well as which
sensors go into the sensor
fusion.
Now, we've talked about a number
of things in DeviceMotion, but
let's get a little bit more
practical.
Let's take some of the concepts
that we've talked about in
DeviceMotion and put them in the
practice -- into practice using
a game.
Badger with Attitude is a game
where we're going to apply
DeviceMotion to translate into
controls for the game.
And for that I'd like to invite
my co-worker Ahmad to the stage
to walk us through this.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, John.
Hello and welcome.
Today, I'm going to be taking
some of those concepts that John
just talked about and help you
put them through a practical
example.
My name is Ahmad.
And I'm an engineer on the Core
Motion team.
I'll be using the Badger app
which has been developed by our
colleagues over at [inaudible].
You may have seen this app in
last year's session.
In it, you play a cute a little
badger called Bob.
He sits in a mining cart rolling
down some tracks collecting gems
and power ups along the way.
So we're going to take this
Apple existing swipe controls
and use DeviceMotion to
transform it to motion-based
gestures.
Here's what we've got in store
for you today.
First, we're going to talk about
the existing controls and what
we're trying to accomplish.
Then we'll show you some of the
basics of using DeviceMotion.
And finally the algorithms we
use to detect those gestures.
So the Badger app allows you to
swipe your finger up across the
screen to make the badger jump
and if you swipe your finger
down, the badger ducks and hides
inside the cart to avoid
obstacles.
And swiping left or right will
make the badger swing to reach
out for those gems.
If you've worked on beautiful
graphics like these, it's a
shame to have to hide them
behind your finger while you
play the game.
So let's use the phone as our
controller here and have the
user fully immersed in the
experience that we've built for
them.
So first we'll detect if the
user has rotated the device
towards them to make the badger
jump up.
A slight bump in the device
downwards will make the badger
squat and hide in the cart.
And tilting the device left or
right will make the badger lean
either way.
Now, I want you to focus on
those couple of points and think
about them when you're looking
at the sample code later or
thinking about incorporating
motion into your application.
As John has mentioned earlier,
Core Motion allows you to
interact directly with the
sensors.
Let's take the accelerometer for
example.
That input may look fine as long
as the user is semi-stationary.
But if you start walking around
or get on a bus, then you're
going to have to account for
these additional accelerations.
So with DeviceMotion, we've
taken other sensors like the
gyro and the magnetometer that
complement the accelerometer
really well.
And we've fused those inputs for
you.
So we can minimize those
environmental factors and let
you focus on capturing those
motion controls rather than how
to process the sensor input.
The DeviceMotion APIs allow you
to query for samples in two
different ways: the push and the
pull mechanism.
Let's take a closer look at
those two.
The push mechanism is a great
way for you to detect a discrete
gesture across a small window of
time.
In the SwingWatch app from last
year's session, we used the push
mechanism so that the framework
will push to us updates as they
are available at a fixed
interval.
Then we would capture those
updates and detect if the user
swung their arm to perform a
backhand or a forehand.
This is what the API looks like.
You use the CMMotionManagers
startDeviceMotionUpdates
function.
You provide a reference frame of
interest.
Provide an OperationQueue for
your Motion Handler to run on as
soon as those samples are ready.
However, if you want to know
what the current state of the
device is then you want to use
the pull mechanism here.
As we'll show you later on in
the Badger app for the tilt
gesture, we want to make the
badger lean at the same angle
that the phone is in so we
ensure we provide the responsive
and a smooth experience for our
graphical application.
The API for the pull mechanism
is a bit simpler.
You call
startDeviceMotionUpdates and you
provide the reference frame.
And whenever you're ready, you
can pull for the latest device
motion sample from the
framework.
We'll be releasing the sample
code for you.
So you'll be able to take a look
at it later.
But let's focus on the Core
Motion parts for now.
So to get started we'll import
the CoreMotion framework and
then instantiate an instance of
the CMMotionManager.
Then we'll check if DeviceMotion
updates are available on this
platform.
And if you recall from John's
talk, the tip and tilt gestures
that we're interested in track
where gravity is in the device
frame.
So we'll check -- so we'll be
using the XArbitraryZVertical
reference frame.
And we'll check if it's
available on the platform.
You may have noticed, I did not
check for the authorization here
and that's because I'm using the
MotionManager API which does not
access sensitive data.
For the rest of the talk, we'll
assume the device is in the last
state orientation, but in the
sample code we'll show you how
to detect and handle other
device orientations.
For the first gesture, when
rotating the device towards you
makes the badger jump up, we
want to capture the magnitude of
that rotation rate along the
horizontal axis of the phone.
In this case, it's the y-axis.
So we'll be looking at the
rotation rate property from the
DeviceMotion object.
And we chose that specifically
because we're not interested in
the current angle the device is
making but rather a quick change
in that angle.
So if we use the rotation rate,
we'll be able to detect a quick
pulse and make the badger jump
accordingly.
This is a gesture that we're
detecting across a small period
of time, so we're going to be
using the push mechanism for it.
Let's see how that will look in
the code.
So start off, we'll set the
update interval to 50Hz.
And you want to be careful when
you set that.
You want the samples to be
coming in fast enough so that
you can capture that gesture but
not too fast that you're
increasing your computational
and memory requirements.
Then we'll
startDeviceMotionUpdates using
the push mechanism, provide our
XArbitraryZVertical reference
frame.
A queue, and I'm using a
standard operation queue here
and finally our motionHandler.
This is what our motionHandler
will look like.
It will get called as soon as
samples are ready.
The first thing we'll do is
check for any errors and then
grab that rotation rate from the
DeviceMotion object and look at
the y-component that we were
interested in.
Then we store that in a buffer.
And I'm using a circular buffer
here.
So as soon as the samples are
coming in, we'll accumulate more
of them.
Since we're using the SceneKit
Renderer for this application, I
chose the renderer's
updateAtTime function.
This will get called just before
you render a new scene.
And this is the ideal place for
me to check for the state of
that buffer and then update the
game.
And I'll leave it up to you to
find out where in the
application is the best place to
do that.
And then I simply check if the
mean of that buffer has crossed
a certain threshold and make the
badger jump.
Keep in mind this threshold is
tunable and adjustable to your
app's specific needs.
Next, we'll take a look at the
second control where bumping the
device downwards will make the
badger duck.
For this one, we want to measure
the user acceleration along the
gravity vector.
So we'll be looking at the user
acceleration property.
And here we chose that because
even if the device is slightly
tilted or rotated at an angle,
the user acceleration is still
going to still look the same
regardless of the attitude.
So this is one of the gestures,
again, where you're detecting
over a window of time, so we'll
use the push mechanism as well.
Since we're already set up for
the push mechanism, we'll head
back to our motionHandler where
we were storing those rotation
rates previously.
But this time we'll pull out the
gravity property out of the
device motion object and the
user acceleration as well.
We compute the magnitude of that
user acceleration along the
gravity vector and store that in
a buffer.
And once the threshold of that
-- once the mean of that buffer
crosses a certain threshold then
we'll make the badger duck down
and hide in the cart.
So we've taken a look at two
controls where we were
monitoring motion across a small
window of time.
And we used the push mechanism
for that.
Let's take a look at our final
control where our requirements
are slightly different.
For the tilt control, in the
simple case where the device is
held in a vertical position, you
can breakdown the gravity vector
into its x-component and its
y-component.
And by applying simple
trigonometry, you can arrive at
the tilt.
But since we want this gesture
to be slightly more flexible,
we're going to break gravity
into its y-component and its
component in the x-z plane of
the device.
This will allow us to tilt the
phone even if the device is
slightly rotated at an angle.
What's different about this
control is that we want to know
the current state of the device
and not the discrete motion that
occurred.
This will allow us to make the
badger lean at the same angle
the device is leaning in and
provide a very responsive
experience.
And for those reasons, we'll be
using the pull mechanism for
this control.
Since we're already set up for
the push mechanism, the
framework is ready for us to
pull for samples at any point in
time.
So we'll go back to our renderer
function.
If you recall, this is getting
called just before you render a
new scene.
That makes it a perfect place
for me to pull for the latest
sample, make a calculation, and
then update the graphics.
So we'll ask the motionManager
for the latest DeviceMotion
sample, grab the gravity
property out of that, compute
the vector in the x-z plane, and
arrive at the tilt as the
arc-tan between that
x-z-component and the
y-component.
Don't forget to let the
framework know that you're no
longer interested in
DeviceMotion updates if they
were previously active.
This is a great thing to do when
your game is paused or has ended
to make sure you're not wasting
more battery than you need.
So here you'll see the results.
The user is able to play the
game by tilting the device from
side to side to make the badger
lean either way.
And tipping the device towards
them makes the badger jump up.
And finally duck, a small push
of the device downwards will
make the badger squat and hide
inside the cart.
It's pretty cool.
We've taken an app with swipe
controls and used DeviceMotion
to replace them with
motion-based ones.
I'm excited to see how far you
can push the DeviceMotion APIs.
[ Applause ]
So to wrap up some of the key
points that we talked about
today, we encourage you to look
at the authorization API and
check for your apps
authorization if you're using
one of the sensitive APIs.
While you might have your use
case for using the sensor data
directly, we encourage you to
look at the DeviceMotion APIs
because our sensor fusion
algorithms handle the most
common case.
It eliminates those
environmental factors so that
you're able to focus on the
motion controls of your user.
The APIs provide you a smooth
and consistent experience across
all our supported devices.
And we've made enhancements this
release to make sure that when
you query for those updates you
do that in a very power
efficient manner.
Remember the two different ways
to query for updates.
Use the push when you want to
detect a gesture across a small
window of time.
And use the pull when
responsiveness is key, and you
want to know what the current
state of the device is.
Here are a couple of these
sessions that we think you might
be interested in.
Please check them out.
And if you're interested in
learning more about the Badger
app, check out last year's
SceneKit session.
If you follow this link, you'll
be able to get at the sample
code and other Core Motion
documentation.
We thank you all for being here
and have a wonderful evening.
[ Applause ]