>> Good morning.
And welcome to the modernizing
Grand Central Dispatch Usage
Session.
I'm Daniel Chimene from the Core
Darwin Team and my colleagues
and I are here today to show you
how you can take advantage of
Grand Central Dispatch to get
the best performance in your
application.
As app developers, you spent
hundreds or thousands of hours
building amazing experiences for
your users.
Taking advantage of our powerful
devices.
You want your users to be able
to have a great experience.
Not just on one device, but
across all the variety of
devices that Apple makes.
GCD is designed to help you
dynamically scale your
application code.
From the single core Apple
Watch, all the way up to a mini
core Mac.
You don't want to have to worry
too much about what kind of
hardware your users are running.
But there are problematic
problems that can affect the
scalability and the efficiency
of your code.
Both on the low end and on the
high end.
That's what we're here to talk
about today.
We want to help you ensure that
all the work you're putting into
your app to make it a great
experience for your users
translates across all of these
devices.
You may have been using GCD
API's like dispatch async, and
others to create cues and
dispatch work to the system.
These are only some of the
interfaces to the concurrency
technology that we call Grand
Central Dispatch.
Today, we're going to take a
peek under the covers of GCD.
This is an advanced session
packed full of information.
So, let's get started right
away, by looking at our
hardware.
The amazing chips in our devices
have been getting faster and
faster over time.
However, much of the speed is
not just because the chips
themselves are getting faster,
but because they're getting
smarter, and smarter about
running your code.
And they're learning from what
your code does over time to
operate more efficiently.
However, if your code goes off
core, because it's completed its
task, then it may no longer be
able to take advantage of the
history that that core has built
up.
And you might leave performance
on the table when you come back
on core.
We've even seen examples of this
on our own frameworks, when we
applied some of the optimization
techniques that we're going to
discuss today, we saw large
speed ups from simple changes to
avoid these problematic
patterns.
So, using these techniques lets
you bring high performance apps
to more users with less work.
Today, we're going to give you
some insight into what our
system is doing under the covers
with your code.
So, you can tune your code to
take the best advantage of what
GCD has to offer.
We're going to discuss a few
things today.
First, we're going to discuss
how you can best express
parallelism and concurrency.
How you can chose the best way
to express concurrency to grand
central dispatch.
We're going to introduce Unified
Queue Identity, which is a major
under the hood improvement to
GCD that we're publishing this
year.
And we're finally going to show
you how you can find problem
spots in your code, with
instruments.
So, let's start by discussing
parallelism and concurrency.
So, for the purpose of this
talk, we're talking about
parallelism which is about how
your code executes in parallel,
simultaneously across many
different cores.
Concurrency is about how you
compose the independent
components of your application
to run concurrently.
The easy way to separate these
two concepts in your mind, is to
realize that parallelism is
something that usually requires
multiple cores and you want to
use them all at the same time.
And concurrency is something
that you can do even on a single
core system.
It's about how you interpose the
different tasks that are part of
your application.
So, let's start by talking about
parallelism and how you might us
it when you're writing an app.
So, let's imagine you make an
app and it processes huge
images.
And you want to be able to take
advantage of the many cores on a
Mac Pro to be able to process
those images faster.
What you do is break up that
image into chunks.
And have each core process those
chunks in parallel.
This gives you a speed up,
because the cores are
simultaneously working on
different parts of the image.
So, how do you implement this?
Well first, you should stop and
consider whether or not you can
take advantage of our system
frameworks.
For example, accelerate has
built-in support for parallel
execution of advanced image
algorithms.
Metal and core image can take
advantage of the powerful GPU.
Well, let's say you've decided
to implement this yourself, GCD
gives you a tool that lets you
easily express this pattern.
The way you express parallels in
GCD is with the API called
concurrentPerform.
This lets the framework optimize
the parallel case because it
knows that you're trying to do a
parallel computation across all
the cores.
concurrentPerform is a parallel
for loop that automatically load
balances your computation across
all the cores in the system.
When you use this with Swift, it
automatically chooses the
correct context to run all your
computation in.
This year, we've brought that
same power to the objective C
interface dispatch apply with
the dispatch apply auto keeper.
This replaces the Q argument
allowing the system to choose
the right context to run your
code in automatically.
So, now let's take a look at
this other parameter, which is
the iteration count.
This is how many times your
block is called in parallel
across the system.
How do you choose a good value
here?
You might imagine that a good
value would be the number of
cores.
Let's imagine that we're
executing our workload on a
three-core system.
Here, you can see the ideal
case, where three blocks run in
parallel on all three cores.
The real world isn't necessarily
this perfect.
What might happens if the third
core here is taken up for awhile
with UI rendering?
Well, what happens is the load
balancer has to move that third
block over to the first core in
order to execute it, because
it's the third course taken up.
And we get a bubble of idle CPU.
We could have taken advantage of
this time, to do more parallel
work.
And so, instead our workload
took longer.
How can we fix that?
Well, we can increase the
iteration count and give the
load balancer more flexibility.
It looks good.
That hole is gone.
There's actually another hole
over here, on the third core.
We could take advantage of that
time as well.
So, as Tim said on Monday, let's
turn the iteration cup up to 11.
There. We filled the hole, and
we have efficient execution.
We're using all of the available
resources on the system until we
finish.
This is still a very simplistic
example.
To deal with the real-world
complexity, you want to use an
order of magnitude more, say
1000.
You can use a large enough
iteration count so the load
balancer has the flexibility to
fill gaps in the system and take
the maximum of your amount of
advantage of the available
resources of the system.
However, you should be sure to
balance the overhead of the load
balancer versus the useful work
that each block in your parallel
for loop does.
Remember that not every CPU is
available to you all the time.
There are many tasks running
concurrently on the system.
And additionally, not every
worker thread will make equal
progress.
So, to recap, if you have a
parallel problem, make sure to
leverage the system frameworks
that are available to you.
You can use their power to solve
your problem.
Additionally, make sure to take
advantage of the automatic load
balancing inside
concurrentPerform.
Give it the flexibility to do
what it does best.
So, that's the discussion about
parallelism.
Now, let's switch to the main
topic for today, which is
concurrency.
So, concurrency.
Let's image you're writing a
simple news app.
How would you structure it?
Well, you start by breaking it
up into the independent
subsystems that make up the app.
Thinking about how you might
break up a news app into its
independent subsystems, you
might have a UI component that
renders the UI, that's the main
thread.
You might also have a database
that stores those articles.
And you might have a networking
subsystem that fetches those
articles from the network.
To give you a better picture of
how this app works and breaking
it up into subsystems gives you
an advantage, let's visualize
how that executes concurrently
on a modern system.
So, let's say here's a timeline
that shows at the top the CPU
track.
Let's image that we only have
one CPU remaining.
The other CPUs are busy for some
reason.
We only have one core available.
At any time only one of these
threads can run on that CPU.
So, what happens when a user
clicks the button and refreshes
the article list in the news
app?
Well, these interface renders
the response to that button and
then sends an asynchronous
across the database.
And then the database decides it
needs to refresh the articles,
which it chooses another command
to the networking subsystem.
However, at this point, the user
touches the app again.
And because the database is done
off the main thread of the
application, the OS can
immediately switch the CPU to
working on the UI thread, and it
can respond immediately to the
user without having to wait for
the database thread to complete.
This is the advantage of moving
work off the main thread.
When the user interface is done
responding, the CPU can then
switch back to the database
thread, and then finish the
networking task as well.
So, taking advantage of
concurrency like this lets you
build responsive apps.
The main thread can always
respond to the user's action
without having to wait for other
parts of your application to
complete.
So, let's take a look at what
that looks like to the CPU.
These white lines above here
show the content switches
between the subsystems.
A contact switch is when the CPU
switches between these different
subsystems or threads that make
up your application.
If you want to visualize what
this looks like to your
application, you can use
instrument system trace, which
shows you what the CPUs and the
threads are doing when they're
running in your application.
If you want to learn more about
this, you can watch the "System
Trace In-Depth" Talk from last
year where the instrument's team
described how you use system
trace.
So, this concept of context
switching is where the power of
concurrency comes from.
Let's look at when these context
switch might happen and what
causes them.
Well, they can start when a high
priority thread needs the CPU as
we saw earlier, with the UI
thread pre-empting the database
thread.
It can also happen when a thread
finishes its current work, or
it's waiting to acquire
resource.
Or it's waiting for an
asynchronous request to
complete.
However, with this great power
of concurrency comes great
responsibility as well.
You can have too much of a good
thing.
Let's say you're switching
between the network and database
threads on your CPU.
A few context switches is fine,
that's the power of concurrency
you're switching between
different tasks.
However, if you're doing this
thousands of times in really
rapid succession, you run into
trouble.
You're starting to lose
performance because each white
bar here is a context switch.
And the overhead of a context
switch adds up.
It's not just the time we spend
executing the context switch,
it's also that history that the
core has built up, it has to
regain that history after every
contact switch.
There are also other affects you
might experience.
For example, there might be
others ahead of you in line for
access to the CPU.
You have to wait each time you
context switch for the rest of
the queue to drain out and so
you may be delayed by somebody
else ahead of you in line.
So, let's look about what might
cause excessive context
switching.
So, there's three main causes
we're going to talk about today.
First, repeatedly waiting for
exclusive access to contended
resources.
Repeatedly switching between
independent operations, and
repeatedly bouncing an operation
between threads.
You note, that I repeated the
word repeatedly several times.
That's intentional.
Context switching a few times is
okay, that's how concurrency
works, that's the power that
we're giving you.
However, when you repeat it too
many times, the cost start to
add up.
So, let's start by looking at
the first case, which is
exclusive access to contended
resources.
When can this happen?
Well, the primary case in which
this happens is when you have a
lock and a bunch of threads are
all trying to acquire that lock.
So, how can you tell if this is
occurring in your application?
Well, we can go back to system
trace.
We can visualize what it looks
like in instruments.
So, let's say this shows us that
we have many threads running for
a very short time and they're
all handing off to each other in
a little cascade.
Let's focus on the first thread
and see what instruments it's
telling us.
We have this blue track, which
shows when a thread is on CPU.
And the red track shows when
it's making a sys call.
In this case, it's making
[inaudible].
This shows that most of its time
is waiting for the [inaudible]
to become available.
And the on core time is very
short at only 10 microseconds.
And there are a lot of context
switches going on on the system,
which it shows you on the
context switches track at the
top.
So, what's causing this?
Let's go back to look at our
simple timeline and see how you
excess contingent could be
playing out.
So, you see this sort of
staircase pattern in time.
Where each thread is running for
a short time, and then giving up
the CPU to the next thread,
rinse and repeat for a long
time.
You want your work to look more
like this.
Where you have the CPU can focus
on one thing at a time, get it
done, and then work on the next
task.
So, what's going on here that
causes that staircase?
Let's zoom in to one of these
stair steps.
So, here we're focusing on two
threads, the green thread and
the blue thread.
And we have a CPU on top.
We've added a new lock track
here that shows the state of the
lock and what thread owns it.
In this case, the blue thread
owns the block, and the green
thread is waiting.
So, when the blue thread
unlocks, the ownership of that
lock is transferred to the green
thread, because it's next in
line.
However, when the blue thread
turns around and grabs the lock
again, it can't because the lock
is reserved for the green
thread.
It forces at context switch
because we now have to do
something else.
And we switch to the green
thread, and the CPU can then
finish the lock and we can
repeat.
Sometimes this is useful.
You want every thread that's
waiting on the lock to get a
chance to acquire the resource,
however, what if you had a lock
that works a different way.
Let's start again by looking at
what an unfair lock does.
So, this time when blue thread
unlocks, the lock isn't
reserved.
The ownership of the lock is up
for grabs.
Blue can take the lock again,
and it can immediately reacquire
and stay on CPU without forcing
a context switch.
This might make it difficult for
the green thread to actually get
a chance at the lock, but it
reduces the number of context
switches the blue thread has to
have in order to reacquire the
lock.
So, to recap when we're talking
about lock contention, you
actually want to make sure to
measure your application and
system trace and see if you have
an issue.
If you do, often the unfair lock
works best for objects,
properties, for global state in
your application that may have
taken a drop many, many times.
There's one other thing I want
to talk about when we're
mentioning locks, and that is
lock ownership.
So, remember the lock track we
had earlier, the runtime knows
which thread will unlock the
lock next.
We can take advantage of that
power to automatically result
priority inversions in your app
between the waiters and the
owners of the lock.
And even enable other
optimizations, like directed CPU
handoff to the owning thread.
Pierre is going to discuss this
later in our talk, when talking
about dispatch sync.
We often get the question, which
primitives have this power and
which ones don't.
Let's take a look at which
low-level primitives do this
today.
So, primitives with a single
known owner have this power.
Things like serial queues and OS
unfair lock.
However, asymmetric primitives,
like dispatch semaphore and
dispatch group don't have this
power, because the runtime
doesn't know what thread will
single the sub primitive.
Finally, primitives with
multiple owners like private,
concurrent queues and read or
writer locks, the systems
doesn't take advantage of that
today, because there isn't a
single owner.
When you're picking a primitive
consider whether or not your use
case involves threads of
different priorities
interacting.
In like a high party UI thread
with a lower priority background
thread.
If so, you might want to take
advantage of a primitive
ownership that ensures that your
UI thread doesn't get delayed by
waiting on a lower priority
background thread.
So, in summary, these
inefficient behaviors often
emerge in properties of your
application.
It's not easy to find these
problems just by looking at your
code.
You should observe it in
instrument system trace to
visualize your apps true, real
behavior and so you can use the
right lock for the job.
So, I've just discussed the
first cause on our context
switching list, which is
exclusive access.
To discuss some other ways your
apps can experience excessive
context switching, I'm going to
bring out my Daniel Steffen to
talk to you about how you can
organize your concurrency with
GCD, to avoid these pitfalls.
[ Applause ]
>> All right.
Thank you, Daniel.
So, we've got a lot to cover
today, so I won't be able to go
into too many details on the
fundamentals of GCD.
If you're new to the technology,
or need a bit of a refresher,
here are some of the sessions at
previous WWDC conferences that
covered GCD and the enhancements
that we've made to it over the
years.
So, I encourage you to go and
see those on video.
We do need a few of the basic
concepts of GCD today however,
starting with the serial
dispatch queue.
This is really our fundamental
synchronization primitive in
GCD.
It provides you with mutual
exclusion as well as FIFO
ordering.
This is one of these ordered and
fair primitives that Daniel just
mentioned.
And it has a concurrent atomic
in queue operation, so it's find
for multiple threads to in
queue, operations into the queue
at the same time, as well as a
single DQI thread that the
system provides to execute
asynchronous work out of the
queue.
So, let's look at an example of
this in action.
Here we're creating a serial
queue by calling the dispatch
queue constructor and that will
give you a piece of memory that
as long as you haven't used it
yet, it's just in your
application.
Now, imagine there's two threads
that come along in call D
queue.async method to submit
some asynchronous work into this
queue.
As mentioned, it's find for
multiple threads to do this, and
the items will just get in queue
in the order that they appeared.
And because this is the
asynchronous method, this method
returns and the threads can go
on their way, so maybe this
first thread eventually calls
queue.sync.
This is the way you interact
synchronously with the queue.
And because this is an ordered
primitive here, what this does
is it will in queue a
placeholder into the queue so
that the thread can wait until
it is its turn.
And now, there's this automatic
worker thread that will come
along to execute the
asynchronous work items, until
you get to that placeholder at
which point the ownership of the
queue will transfer to the
thread waiting in queue.sync so
that it can execute its block.
So, the next concept that we'll
need is the dispatch source.
This is our event monitoring
primitive in GCD.
Here we are setting one up to
monitor a default descriptive
for readability if you make read
source constructor.
You pass it in a queue which is
the target queue of the source,
which is where we execute the
event handle of the source,
which here just reads from the
default descriptor.
This target queue is also where
you might put other work that
should be serialized with this
operation, such as processing
the data that was read.
Then, we set the cancel handler
for the source, which is how
sources implement the
invalidation pattern.
And finally, when everything is
set up, you call source and
activate to start monitoring.
So, it's worth noting that
sources are really just an
instance of a more general
pattern throughout the OS, where
you have objects that deliver
events to you on a target queue
that you specify.
So, if you're familiar with XPC,
that would be another example of
that XPC connections.
And, it's worth noting that all
of everything we're telling you
today about sources really
applies to all such objects in
general.
So, putting these two concepts
together, we get what we call
the target queue hierarchy.
So, here we have two sources
with their associated target
queues, S1, S2 and the queue is
Q1 and Q2.
And we can form a little tree
out of this situation by adding
yet another serial queue to the
mix, by adding mutual exclusion
queue, EQ, at the bottom.
The way we do this is simply by
passing in the optional target
argument into the dispatch queue
constructor.
So, this gives you a shared
single mutual exclusion context
for this whole tree.
Only one of the sources or one
item in one of the queues can
execute at one time.
But it preserves the independent
individual queue order for queue
1 and queue 2.
So, let's look at what I mean by
that.
Here I have the two queues,
queue 1 and queue 2 with them
queued in a specific order.
And because we have this extra
serial queue at the bottom, and
the executes, they will execute
in EQ and there will be a single
worker thread executing these
items giving you that mutual
exclusion property, only one
item executing at one time.
But as you can see, the items
from both queues can execute
interleafed while preserving the
individual order that they had
in their original queues.
So, the last concept that we'll
need today, is the notion of
quality of service.
Here is a fairly deed concept
that was talked about in some
detail in the past.
In particular, in the power
performance and diagnostics
session in 2014.
So, if this is new to you, I
would encourage you to go and
watch that.
But what we'll need today from
this is really mostly it's
abstract notion of priority.
And we'll use the terms QOS and
priority somewhat
interchangeably in the rest of
the session.
We have four quality of service
classes on the system.
From the highest user
interactive UI to user
initiated, or IN, utility, UT to
background BG.
The lowest priority.
So, let's look at how we would
combine this concept of quality
of service with the target queue
hierarchy that we just looked
at.
In this hierarchy, every node in
the tree can actually have a
quality of service label
associated with it.
So, for instance the source 2
might be relevant to the user
interface.
It might be monitored for an
event where we should update the
UI as soon as the event
triggers.
So, it could be that we want to
put the UI label onto the
source.
Another common use source would
be to put a label on the mutual
exclusion queue to provide a
flow of execution so that
nothing in this tree can execute
below this level, so UT in this
example.
And now if anything else in this
queue fires, for instance source
1, we will be using this flow
for the tree if it doesn't have
its own quality of service
associated.
And source firing is really just
an async executes from the
kernel.
And the same as before happens,
we end queue the source handler
eventually into the mutual
exclusion queue for execution.
For asyncs from user space, your
quality of service is usually
determined from the thread that
called queueu.async.
Now, we have a user initiated
thread that makes item at IN
into the queue and for execution
into E queue eventually.
And now, maybe we have the
source 2 that flies with this
very high priority UI relevant
event that executes its event
handler, and queues its event
handler into EQ.
So, now you'll notice that we
have a priority inversion
situation.
We have three items in queue
with a very high priority item
at the end preceded by some low
priority items.
And these have to execute in
order.
The system resolves this
inversion for you by bringing up
a worker thread at the highest
priority of anything that is
currently in queue.
And it's worth keeping this
little tree on the right hand
side here in mind because it
comes up again later in the
session.
And with that let's move on to
our main topic of the section
which is how to use what we just
learned to express good
granularity of concurrency to
GCD.
Let's go back to our news
application that Daniel
introduced earlier and focus on
the networking subsystem for a
little bit.
In a networking subsystem,
you'll have to monitor some
network connections in the
kernel.
And with GCD you'll do that with
a dispatch source, and the
dispatch queue like you just
saw.
But of course in any networking
subsystem you usually not just
have one network connection,
you'll have many of them and
they will all replicate the same
setup.
So, let's focus on the right
hand side on the three
connections here and see how the
execute.
If the first connection
triggers, just like the same
thing we just saw happens, we
will end queue the event handler
for that source onto its target
queue.
Of course if the other two
connections fire at the same
time, they'll still replicated
and you'll end up with three
queues with an event handler end
queued.
And because you have these three
independent serial queues at the
bottom, you've really asked the
system to provide you with three
independent concurrency
contexts.
If all these become active at
once, the system will oblige and
create three threads for you to
execute the event handlers.
Now, this may be what you
wanted, and maybe exactly what
you were after, but it is quite
common for these event handlers
to be small and only read some
data from the network and in
queue it into a common data
structure.
Additionally, as we saw before,
you don't have just three
connections, you may have many,
many of them if you have a
number of network connections in
your subsystem.
So, this can leave to a
situation where you have this
kind of context switching
pattern, and excessive context
switching that Daniel talked
about where you execute a small
amount of work, context switch
to another thread and do that
again, and again, and again.
So, how can we improve on this
situation in this example here?
We can apply the single mutual
exclusion context idea that we
just talked about by simply
putting in an additional serial
queue at the bottom and forming
a hierarchy, you can get a
single mutual exclusion context
for all of these connections.
And if they fire at the same
time, the same thing as before
will happen, the event handlers
will get end queued onto the
target queues, but because
there's an additional serial
queue at the bottom here, it's a
single thread that will come and
execute them in order instead of
the multiple threads that we had
before.
So, this seems like a really
simple change but it is exactly
the type of change that lead to
the 1.3 X performance
improvement in some of our own
code that Daniel talked about
earlier in the session.
So, this is one example of how
we can avoid the problematic
pattern of repeatedly switching
between independent operations.
But it really comes under the
general heading of avoiding
unwanted and unbounded
concurrency in application.
One way you can get that is by
having many queues becoming
active all at once.
And one example of this is that
independent requiring source
pattern that we just say.
You can also get this if you
have independent or object
queues.
If many objects in your
application have their own
serial queues and you put
asynchronous work into them at
the same time you can get
exactly the same phenomenon.
You can also see this if you
have many work items submitted
to the global concurrent queue
at the same time.
In particular if there's work
items block.
The way the global concurrent
queue works is that it corrects
more threads when existing
threads block to give you a
continuing good level of
concurrency in your application.
But if those threads then block
again, you can get something
that we call the thread
explosion.
This is a topic that we went
into some detail in the
"Building Responses and
Efficient Apps with GCD" in
2015.
So, if this sounds new to you,
I'd encourage you to go and
watch that session.
So, how do you choose the right
amount of concurrency in your
application to avoid these
problematic patterns?
One idea that we've recommended
to you in the past is to use one
queue for subsystem.
So, here back in our news
application, we already have one
queue for the user interface,
the main queue and we could
choose one queue for the
networking and 1 queue for the
database subsystem in addition.
But what we've learned today a
more general way to think of
this is really to use one queue
hierarchy per subsystem.
This gives you a mutual
exclusion context for the
subsystem, and you can leave the
rest of the queue event sub
structing and subsystem alone
and just target that network
queue or database queue that
underlies the bottom of your
queue hierarchies.
But, that may be a bit too
simplistic a pattern for a
complex application or a complex
subsystem.
The main thing that is important
here is to have a fixed number
of serial queue hierarchies in
your application.
So, it may make sense to have
additional queue hierarchies for
a complicated subsystem, say a
secondary one for slower work,
or larger work items, so that
the first one, the primary one
can keep the subsystem
responsive to requests coming in
from outside.
Another thing that's important
to think about in this context
is the granularity of the work
submitted to those subsystems.
You want to use fairly large
work items when you move between
subsystems to get a picture like
what we say earlier in the
session, where the CP is able to
execute your subsystem for long
enough to reach an efficient
performance state.
Once you're inside the
subsystem, say the networking
subsystem here.
It may make sense to subdivide
into smaller block items and
have a finer granularity to
improve the responsiveness of
that subsystem.
For instance, you can to that by
splitting up your work and
re-asyncing to another queue in
your queue hierarchy.
And that doesn't introduce a
context switch because you're
already in that one subsystem.
So, in summary, what have we
looked at in this section?
We saw how we can organize
queues and sources into serial
queue hierarchies.
How to use a fixed number of the
queue hierarchies to give GCD a
good granularity of concurrency.
And how to size your work items
appropriately earlier in the
section for parallel work and
here for concurrent work inside
the subsystem as well as between
subsystems.
And with this, I'll hand it over
to Pierre to dive into how we
have improved GCD to always
execute the queue hierarchy on a
single thread and how you can
modernize your code to take
advantage of this.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you Daniel.
So, indeed we have completely
reinvented the internals of GCD
this year to eliminate some
unwanted context switches and
execute single queue hierarchies
like the ones that Daniel showed
on the single thread.
To do so we have created a new
kind of concepts that we call
Unified Queue Identity that let
us do that.
And we will walk you through how
it works.
So, really this part of the talk
will focus on a single queue
hierarchy, like the ones Daniel
showed earlier.
However, we'll work on
simplified ones with the sources
at the top, and your mutual
exclusion context at the bottom.
The internal GCD notes are not
quite given for that part of the
talk.
So, when you create an
[inaudible] context you use to
dispatch queue constructor, that
creates just a piece of memory
in your application that is a
note.
And one of the first things that
you may do is to dispatch recent
coded items to it.
So, you will have code in your
application that will here and
queue a [inaudible] on the
queue, when that happened before
we used to request a thread
anonymously to the system.
And the resolution of what that
was meant to do happens late
inside your application.
In this case, we change that and
what we do is that we create our
counter object, the Unified
Queue Identity that is tied to
your queue and is exactly meant
to represent your queue in the
kernel.
We can tie that object with the
required hierarchy to execute to
work, which here is backup.
And that causes the system to
ask for a thread.
The thread request, that dotted
line on the slide, may not be
fulfilled for some time, because
here that's a background thread,
and maybe the system is loaded
enough that it's not even worth
giving you a thread for it.
Later on, some other path of
your application may actually
try to en queue more work.
Here a UT [inaudible] that is
slightly higher priority.
We can use the queue identity,
the unified identity in the
catalog to look and solve the
priority inversion, and elevate
the priority of that thread
request.
It may be that is the small
nudge that the system needed to
actually give you a thread here
to execute your work.
But this thread is in the
scheduler queues not yet on
call.
Not executing.
And the reason why is because
there is another thread in your
application that is interacting
with a queue and working
synchronously at a higher
priority, even, usually shaded.
Now that we have that Unified
Queue Identity, we can actually
since that thread has to block
to en queue the placeholder that
Daniel told you about a bit
earlier, we can block the
synchronous execution of that
thread on the Unified Queue
Identity.
The same on that we use for
asynchronous work, [inaudible].
But now that we unified the
asynchronous and the synchronous
part of the queue in a single
identity, we can apply an
optimization and delicately
switch the thread that's
blocking you by passing the
scheduler queue and registering
the queue delays that Daniel
introduced while talking about
the scheduler very early.
So, that's how the unified queue
identity is used for for
asynchronous and synchronous
work items.
Now, how did we use that for
events?
Why is it useful?
So, that is the small tree that
we've been using so far, let's
look at the creation of these
sources.
When you create the source using
the makeResource factory button,
you set a bunch of events, of
favorite handlers and
properties.
But what is really interesting
is what happens when you
activating the object.
This is actually at that moment,
that we will notice that utility
are QOS, at which the handler
for your source will always
execute.
Because it's inherited from your
queue hierarchy.
We will also know now, with the
new system, that the handler
will eventually execute that in
queue execution mature exclusion
context.
And will now register the source
at front with the sync unified
identity that I just talked
about a bit earlier.
If we look at the higher UI QOS
source that we have on the tree,
the way we are treated is very
similar of the first one, except
that when you're setting the
handler here you're specifying
the QOS that you actually want.
And again, what's interesting is
what happens at activation.
That is when we the snapshot and
like before when we got the
utility QOS from your hierarchy,
here we get it from your hint.
We still recall the fact that
they will execute both the
sources on the same execution
context.
And will register that second
source up front again, which
with some unified identity in
the kernel.
So, really what we're trying to
solve with that quite complex
identity is a problem that we
had in previous phases of the
OS, where related operations
would actually bounce off the
old threads.
Let's look at how it used to
work.
So, remember that's our queue
hierarchy, and let's bring up
the timeline that you've seen a
bunch of times now in our talk.
At the top, the CPU, but now
there is a new tack, the
exclusion queue card that will
show you what is executing at
any given moment on that queue.
So, that's really how the
runtime used to work before this
phase in macOS Sierra and iOS
10.
So, let's look at what happens
if the first source fails.
Before, like I said thread
requests were anonymous.
We would ask for an anonymous
thread, deliver the event on the
thread and then we would look at
the event.
And when we look at the event
inside your application, that is
only then that we realize that
this event is meant to run on a
queue.
We would then queue the event
handler.
But since the queue is
unclaimed, the thread could
actually become that queue and
start executing given handler
for your source.
And we do so.
Now, the interesting thing is
what happens when the second
source that is higher priority
fires?
The same actually.
Since it's a hierarchy QOS here,
higher priority that's what
you're executing right now.
We would bring up a new
anonymous thread deliver that
higher priority event on the
thread.
And look at what that event
means.
And we will notice that it is
for exactly the same queue
hierarchy only then.
And then queue the handler after
the one we just pre emptied.
As you see, we closed our first
context switch.
It was of that higher priority
event.
But, we cannot make for what
progress, because unlike the
first time, that second thread
cannot take over the queue it is
already associated with a
thread.
We cannot take it over.
So, the thread is done.
Which as Daniel explained one
reason why you context switch
again.
And that's what we do, we
context switch back to the first
thread that is the one that can
actually make progress.
We execute the rest of the first
handle and finally move to the
second one.
So, as you can see, we use two
threads and two context switches
that you really didn't want for
a single execution context.
We fixed that using Unified
Identity in macOS High Sierra
and iOS 11.
We got rid of that thread.
And we also, of course got rid
of the two context switches that
we had, that were unwanted.
And of course, its important
because unlike what happened
when Daniel showed you the
pre-emption with that UI touch
event, where we could take
advantage of the fact that we
actually had two threads that
were independent to be more
responsive for application.
Here, we didn't benefit from any
of these context switches,
because these event handler, S1
and M2 had to execute in order
anyways.
So, knowing about that event
early was not useful.
And if you look at how this
actually, what the flow is
today, it looks more like this.
What happened here?
The most important thing on that
flow is that now if you look at
the thread, it's called EQ,
because that's the part of the
unified identity, the thread and
the EQ are basically the same
object.
And the kernel knows that it's
really executing a queue, which
is reflected on the CPU tab, you
don't see the events anymore,
it's just running your queue.
However, you might ask, how did
we manage to deliver the event,
that second event without
requiring a hamper.
That is actually a good
question.
When the event fires, now we
know where it will execute,
where you will handle it.
We just mark the thread.
No helper needed.
And at the first possible time,
we will notice that thread was
marked with you have pending
events.
And when we de-queue the events,
one needs to hide time, hide
after the first handler
finishes.
We can grab the events from the
kernel, look at them, and then
queue their handlers on your
hierarchy.
So, why did we go through that
quite complex explanation?
That's so that you can
understand how to best take
advantage of the runtime
behavior.
Because clearly, the runtime
uses every possible hint you're
giving us to optimize behavior
in your application.
And admittance buttons to know
how to hint and when to hint the
runtime correctly so that we
make the right decisions.
Which brings me to what should
you do to existing code bases to
take advantage of all that core
technology that we rebuilt.
Now, actually two steps to
follow to take the full
advantage of that technology.
The first one is no mutation
after activation.
And the second one is paying
extra care with extra attention
to your target queue
hierarchies.
So, what does that mean?
No mutation past activation
really means that when you have
any kind of property on a
dispatch object, you can send
them, well as soon as you
activate the object, you should
stop mutating them.
The second example, that's our
source that we've seen quite a
few times already in the talk.
That [inaudible] for the
ability.
And you're setting a bunch of
properties, handlers; the event
handler, the consent handler.
You may have registration
handlers.
You can even change them a few
times, that's fine, you can
change your mind.
And then you activate the
source.
The contact here is that you
should stop mutate your objects.
It's very tempting to,
after-the-fact, for example
change the target queue of your
source.
That will cause problems.
And the reason why is exactly
what I showed a bit earlier, at
activate time we take a snapshot
of the properties of your
objects, and we will take
decisions in the future based on
that snapshot.
And if you change the target
queue hierarchy after-the-fact,
it will hinder that snapshot
stale and that will defeat a
bunch of very important
optimization such as the
priority inversion avoidance
[inaudible] the direct handoff
that we have for the dispatch
sync that I presented earlier,
are all defensive and
deliverable optimizations that
we just went through.
And I insist on the points that
Daniel made early on, which is
that many of you probably never
had to create a dispatch source
in your application.
And this is fine, this is really
how it's supposed to work.
You probably actually use them a
lot of them through system
frameworks.
It's a shame you have a
framework that you have to then
dispatch queue to because they
are asyncing some notifications
on the queue on your behalf.
Behind the scenes, they have one
of these sources.
So, if you're changing the
assumptions of the system, you
will actually break all of these
optimizations as well.
So, I hope a made a point really
clear that to target your
hierarchy is essential and you
have to protect it.
What does that mean?
And how to do that?
The first way, which is a very
simple device, is that when
you're building one, start from
the bottom and build it toward
the top.
When you show that card from the
slide build up, as you see,
these wider holes there, they
are your target queue
relationships.
None of them have to be mutated
if you [inaudible] in that
order.
However, when you have a large
application, or you're hiding
your frameworks and you're
bending one of these queues to
another part of your engineering
company, you may want to have
stronger guarantees than that.
You may want to lockdown these
relationships, so that really no
one can mutate them
after-the-fact.
This is actually something that
you can do with the technology
that we call set a queue
hierarchy.
We introduced it last year, and
actually if you are using Swift
3, then you can stop listening
to me, because you're already in
that form and that the only
world you're living.
However, if you have an existing
cloud based, or you use older
versions than of Swift, you need
to do some extra steps.
So, let's focus on the
relationship between Q1 and EQ
here.
When you created that with
Objective-C you probably hold
code that looks like this.
You create your queue and then
in the second step, you will set
your target queue of Q1 to EQ.
That is not protecting your
queue hierarchy.
Anyone can come along and call
dispatch target queue again and
break all your assumptions.
That's not totally great.
There is a simple step to just
fix that code into a way that is
safe, which is to adopt a new
API we introduced last year,
which is dispatch queue create
with target, which in a single
automatic step will create the
queue, set the queue hierarchy
height, and protect it.
And that's it.
These were the two steps to
follow for you to really work
with the [inaudible] well.
Other, a bit like the mutated
case that Daniel walked you
through early on, finding when
you're doing one of these things
wrong is fairly challenging,
especially on the large cloud
base.
Finding that in an existing
cloud base full code inspection
is hard.
This is why we created a new GCD
performance instruments tool to
find problem spots in an
existing application.
And I will call Daniel back to
the stage to demo for you.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Pierre.
All right to start out with
please note that this GCD
performance instrument that
we'll see is not yet present in
the version of XCode 9 that you
have, but it will be available
in an upcoming seed of XCode 9.
So, for this demo, let's analyze
the execution of our sample news
application in some detail.
So, what happens here if you
click this connect button at the
bottom, is that this app creates
a number of network connections
to a server, to read lists of
URLs from, which are then
displayed in the WebViews
whenever the refresh button is
hit.
So, let's jump into XCode to see
how we are setting up those
network connections.
So, here we are in XCode in the
create connections method, which
does just that.
It's very simple.
We have a for loop, maybe just
create some sockets and connect
them to our server.
And we monitor that socket for
readability with one of these
dispatch read sources that we've
seen so many times already in
this session.
And here it is the trusted the
see API.
We then set up the event handler
block for that dispatch source
here.
And when the socket becomes
readable, we just read from it
with the read system call until
there is no more data available.
Once we have the data, we pass
it to our database, subsystem in
the application with this
process 0 method.
So, let's build and run, and
take a system trace of this
application and see how it
executes.
So here we are in instruments,
in system trace, and in addition
to the usual tacks in system
trace, we've added this new GCD
performance instrument.
When we click on there, we see a
number of performance events
that have been reported for
performance problems.
One of these is this mutation
after activation event, that we
can also see when we go and mass
over the timeline.
You can also click on one of the
other events here, such as this,
re-target after activation
event.
And the list will take us
directly there.
If you want more details on
this, we can disclose the
backtrace on the right hand side
is instruments which will show
us where exactly this event
occurred in your application.
So, here for instance it is in
our create connections method.
If we double click on this
frame, instruments will show us
directly the line of code where
the problem occurred.
This is actually a target queue
call here that indeed occurs
after activate.
Like, this is the pattern up
here just told you about.
To go and fix that, we can jump
directly into XCode with the
open file and XCode button and
instruments.
So, here we are at that dispatch
the target queue line and indeed
it, as well as the dispatch
source at event handler set up
happens after activate.
So, here in this example, it's
really easy to fix.
We just move these two lines
down below.
And we have fixed the problem.
We have activate after we set up
the source, and not before.
So, let's jump back into
instruments and see what we can
see in the system trace now.
It looks the same as before,
except when you click on the GCD
performance track, you will see
there is no more significant
performance problems detected.
And that's what you ought to see
if you use this instrument.
So, of course this was very
simple in this application.
You may have to do some work.
So, let's focus on the points
track in the application.
This shows us a number of
network event handlers.
And these are the source event
handlers in our application.
How did you manage to make these
show up in instruments?
That's actually really
interesting to understand
because it's something you can
apply to your own code to
understand how it executes in
instruments.
Well, going back to XCode in our
create connections method, when
we set up our source and its
source event handlers, we are
interested in the execution of
that event handler, and try to
understand its timing.
To see that instruments, we've
added the kdebug signpost start
function at the beginning of the
handler, and the kdebug signpost
end function at the end.
And that is all it takes for the
section of code to appear
highlighted in the points track
in instrument system trace.
So, if you switch back to
instruments, that is these red
dots at the pop in the points
track and we can see in the back
trace that it matches our event
handler for one of these events.
If you zoom in on one of these
interesting looking areas in the
points track, here, you can see
that there is a number of event
handlers that are occurring very
close together.
And by mousing over we can
actually see that they're
execute for very short amounts
of time.
The pop-up will tell us the
amount of time it has executed
and we can even see that
sometimes we have overlapping
event handlers that are all
executing concurrently at the
same time.
So, this is one of the symptoms
of potentially unwanted
concurrency in our application,
where something that didn't look
like it would cause concurrency
in your code, actually does run
in a concurrent way or multiple
threads and cause potentially
extra context switches.
So, to understand this better,
let's bring up the threads in
instruments.
And the system trace that are
executing this code.
So, here I've highlighted the
three worker threads that are
executing these event handlers.
And we can see as before that
they are executing on call
during this time.
And the time they were running.
But here we can see they were
again, running for a very short
amount of time in this area.
And we can verify that they are
making these read system calls
that we saw earlier in the event
handler.
And we can get some more detail
by looking at the back trace
again, and seeing, yes it is us
that is calling that read system
call and here it reads 97 bytes
from our socket.
And looking at the other
threads, the same pattern
repeats.
You can see it's the same read
system calls occurring there,
more or less at the same
timeframe and so on the second
thread here or on the first
thread.
They're really all doing the
same thing, and overlapping.
It would be much better for our
program if these things executed
on a single thread.
Here we don't really get any
benefit from the concurrency
because we are executing such
short pieces of code.
And we are probably getting more
harm than good from adding these
extra context switches.
So, let's apply the patterns
that we saw earlier to fix this
problem in this sample
application.
Jumping back into XCode, let's
see how we set up the target
queue for this source that we
have.
So, that's sort of when you
create this queue at the top of
this function framework and as
you can see, we do it simply by
calling this batch queue
correct.
And that creates an independent
serial queue that isn't
connected to anything else in
our application.
This is exactly like the case we
had earlier in my example of the
networking subsystem.
So, let's fix that by adding a
mutual exclusion context at the
bottom of all of these queues
for all of these connections.
And we do that by adding the, or
by switching to the dispatch
queue create with target
function up here introduced to
you earlier.
So, here we add dispatch queue,
create this target.
And we use a single mutual
exclusion queue as the target
queue for all of these.
And this is a serial queue that
we created somewhere else.
And with that, we build and run
again and look at the system
trace again.
And now it looks very different.
Here we have still the same
points track and we still see
the same network events that
occur, but as you can see,
there's no more overlapping
events in that track, and
there's a single worker thread
that executes this code.
And if we zoom in on one of
these clusters we can see this
is actually many instances of
that event handler executing in
rapid succession, which is
exactly what we expected.
And when you zoom in more on one
particular event, you can see
it's still executing for a
fairly short amount of time, and
making those same read sys
calls.
But now that is much less
problematic because it's all
happening on a single thread.
So, this may seem like a very
simple and trivial change, but
it's worth pointing out that
it's exactly this type of small
tweak that led to the 1.3X
performance improvement in some
of our own framework code that
Daniel pointed out at the
beginning of the session.
So, very small changes like this
can make a significant
difference.
All right so, let's look back at
what we've covered today.
Daniel, at the beginning went
with you over the details of how
not to go off core unnecessarily
is ever more important for
modern CPUs so that it can reach
the most efficient performance
state.
We looked at the importance of
sizing the workforce of power
workloads and for work moving
between subsystems in your
application as well as inside
those subsystems.
We talked about how to choose
good granularity of concurrency
with GCD by using a fixed number
of serial queue hierarchies in
your application.
And Pierre walked you through
how to modernize your GCD usage
to take full advantage of
improvements in the OS, in our
hardware.
And finally, we saw how we can
use instruments to find problems
spots in our application and how
to fix them.
For more information on this
session, I will direct you to
this URL where the documentation
links for GCD are as well as the
movie for the session, and we
have some related sessions this
week that might be worthwhile
going to.
Introducing Core ML already
having happened, the other two
are going to help you with
parallel and computing
[inaudible] task in your
application like we talked about
at the beginning.
And the last two are going to
help you with more performance
analysis and improvements of
different aspects of your app.
And with that, I'd like to thank
you for coming.
If you have any questions,
please come and see us at the
labs.
[ Applause ]