>> So what's new on iOS?
For this release, a major theme
has been Wayfinding.
Now Wayfinding traditionally
refers to all the ways that we
can help guide people through an
environment and orient
themselves within a physical
space.
You encounter signage and
information systems everywhere
to help you find your way from
street signs, to airports, and
even in parking garages.
So naturally, our digital
environments can benefit from
clear navigation.
Wayfinding in UI can enhance
your experience and
understanding of the space that
you're in.
Now when we design for iOS, our
goal is to highlight content
first.
But app layouts need clear
visual hierarchy so that people
know how to navigate through the
system.
UI elements in general should
not compete with content but
help you to better understand
potential functions and
interactions.
And we are constantly trying to
improve upon these themes.
So for iOS 11, we wanted to
provide more clarity for
navigation or Wayfinding
throughout the system.
We wanted to focus on overall
hierarchy through the use of
typography.
And when it would be useful, we
wanted to create greater
contrast by refining elements
within the UI.
So first, let's take a look at
navigation.
Last year we started using more
bold text in music because it's
an app with a lot of dense
content.
Text became instrumental for
organizing similar media and
orienting you while you browse
and search.
And we recognize that other apps
could benefit from the same text
treatments.
So this year, we introduce large
titles to navigation bars for
other apps that could use some
more emphasis.
This does not replace our
standard navigation but is an
opt-in version that transitions
from to the standard Nav bar
when you start scrolling.
Now you might be wondering where
these large titles should be
used and I can highlight a
couple guidelines to consider
that we found helpful when
deciding which of our apps
they'd be most appropriate for.
A good place to use large-title
navigation can be at the top
level of an app with tabs.
This helps to understand that
you're at a top level but also
that you're scrolled to the top
of the page.
Again, music is a good example
of an app that uses large titles
for all of its top levels but
also occasionally on some
secondary levels or further
down.
Since music has so much content
and multiple levels that you can
drill into, large titles are
helpful as you navigate further
into the app.
They can be used for views that
all have very similar layouts as
a quick read on where you are.
Phone is an appropriate app to
use large titles because almost
all of the tabs show content in
rows of text.
And it's important to stress
that it's not always necessary
to use large titles in
navigation.
We found that in multiple
scenarios it would hinder
usability and not help.
And a good example of that is
the clock app.
Even though it's an app with
tabs, it doesn't have multiple
content to sort through and each
of the tabs has a very distinct
layout.
So large titles in this case
would compete with content.
Now let's take a closer look at
ways that we can improve
hierarchy through type.
Typographic hierarchy is the way
to organize type in a way that
will emphasize important content
over less important content and
it can help to group things
together.
This can reduce cognitive load
or the amount of mental effort
it takes you to find something
that you're looking for.
And there are a few basic
methods for establishing
typographic hierarchy.
The position of the text can
convey importance.
Since Label 1 is on top, we can
infer that it's more important
than Label 2, but that might not
be obvious in all cases.
So another way is to decrease
the size of the secondary line
or you can vary the weight or
you can use color so that the
secondary line recedes more.
You may need to use more than
one of these at a time so you
can make sure there's clear
hierarchy between the two.
Here's a screen from photos in
iOS 10.
The most important information
here is your content, your
photos.
The section headers use two text
sizes to distinguish different
information but all of it is a
tad small and light.
So for iOS 11, we made section
headers larger in general and
increased the text weight and
used gray for supporting text.
And these changes made it easier
to isolate important in content
so that you can find a
particular photo faster.
So let's look at more examples.
Here's Calendar in iOS 10.
We increased text weights for
more emphasis and used color
more intentionally to denote the
current year, month, and date.
Here is Weather in iOS 10.
For iOS 11, we increased the
text weights and made the text
overall larger so that the
content is easier to read.
So last, let's look at ways that
we've tried to improve contrast.
To create more balance with the
larger and more bold text styles
throughout the UI, we needed to
update other UI elements to give
them greater contrast while
keeping them both functional and
minimal.
So one of the ways we did this
was to fill in the button shapes
and increase the size of the
shape itself like we did with
the search field.
And we updated the tab bars
increasing the weight of the
label from regular to medium.
And for the glyphs, we filled in
the shapes and thickened the
stroke weights.
And to make better use of space
in landscape, we moved the label
so that it's side by side with
the glyph.
This tab bar is now shorter than
before and now matches the
landscape Nav bar and toolbar
height.
And a couple other things to
note are that the glyphs are
slightly smaller and the text is
slightly larger than the
portrait equivalents.
So you'll want to make sure you
take that into account for your
own apps.
On iPad, we can increase the
text size even more while
keeping the glyphs the same as
portrait.
This is the Wallet app from iOS
10.
And typically we use material
blurs to indicate when UI has
come in on top of a page that is
still underneath.
And we wanted to remove it in
areas, like in this example,
where it had no logical reason
for being there and did not
reinforce where you are in the
digital space.
So that's a quick summary of the
design updates we've made for
iOS 11.
Keep these things in mind when
making and updating your apps.
Use large-title navigation if
areas of your app could use more
emphasis and to help orient
people.
But remember that it's not
always necessary to use
everywhere.
Consider whether your app could
benefit from refining
typographic hierarchy.
And lastly, remove superfluous
UI elements and complexity to
improve overall contrast in your
app.
We hope these updates will help
you to create great products
that are both beautiful and easy
to use.
Thank you
[ Applause ]
.