[ Applause ]
>> Let's talk about designing
glyphs, and I think a good place
to start is what is a glyph?
A glyph, traditionally, is a
topographical character, but it
could also be a symbol or a
simple shape of a real world
object, or it can be a
combination of shapes to
represent function or a concept.
But you might be thinking what
is the difference between this
and an icon.
So, to help illustrate the
difference, let's take a look at
this example of four iPhone
icons.
An icon can refer to a broad set
of assets ranging from simple
low fidelity shapes like you can
see on the left to illustrative,
colorful, and highly rendered
assets that you can see on the
right.
The two assets on the left can
also be defined as glyphs, and
that's because of their
simplicity, and for the most
part, glyphs are monochromatic
and should be colorized
programmatically.
This is the iOS wallet app icon,
and you can see a nice use of
color and some subtle shading.
And here's the app represented
as a glyph.
So, you get the idea, but let's
take a look at one more example.
This is the phone app icon, and
if we take away that iconic
shape and the color, you see
where I'm going with this, we're
left with this glyph.
So, in this case, the glyph is
actually part of what makes up
the icon.
Now, effective glyphs have some
key characteristics.
They're highly simplified in
form.
They're conceptually universal,
and they're quickly readable in
context as to their function or
purpose.
Many of us have experienced
being in a foreign place,
somewhere where we don't, you
know, relate to the culture or
another language, and it can be
quite a relief when we see a
symbol that we recognize.
So, in this case, you don't have
to know German to know the right
way to the airport, and that's
thanks to this simple universal
shape, which in this context we
understand to represent airport.
So, glyphs are a powerful
communication tool, and that's
why we make them part of our
design language in UI.
So, let's go through a quick
exercise to conceptualize an
effective glyph.
Let's say we need one to
represent delicious.
The first thing you might think
of is a cheeseburger, and you
would have no argument from me.
I do think cheeseburgers are
delicious.
But believe it or not, some
people do not like
cheeseburgers.
So, what's better than a
cheeseburger?
Pizza? I see some people shaking
their heads.
I don't know.
Okay. I think I got one that we
can all relate to.
How about ice cream?
No. Well, all right, well, I
think I could -- you got the
idea here -- not everyone
relates to these specific food
items in the same way.
So, these aren't effective.
So, let's try something a little
bit different, and what about
something to get to the core of
what delicious might make us
feel.
Something like a facial
expression.
It's cute and relatable,
expressive, but we should be
mindful here that in some
cultures using like a face, a
mouth, or a body part can be
seen as inappropriate; so, be
mindful of that.
So, what is a universal symbol
for delicious?
What about a heart?
We love cheeseburgers.
Some people like pizza.
Some people love ice cream.
The association of love with
delicious is much more universal
than our other options.
So, this is a nice effective
solution.
Okay. So, let's take a look at
some examples of where we use
glyphs on our platforms, on the
Mac, in the menu bar, in tool
bars, and in sidebars, and most
recently, in the touch bar.
On iOS, in tab bars, list views,
and home screen quick action
menus.
So, you can see, glyphs are
everywhere, and also notice that
they rarely ever stand alone.
So, that's why we need to be
mindful of some design
considerations when, you know,
we're crafting a set of glyphs.
Our goal should be to make them
feel like a family, and a family
has a shared set of
characteristics.
So, we're going to look at
optical weight, lines, and
positioning.
In this example, the set feels a
bit right heavy.
The two glyphs on the left just
are optically smaller, and
consequently they feel a bit
less significant.
So, if we turn on our guides, we
can see that we've constrained
ourselves to these vertical
bounds.
Let's turn those off and scale
the up optically, and that feels
much better.
Here's the before and the after.
Because the elliptical shape of
messages and the narrow shape of
phone have less surface area, we
can use scale to achieve this
optical balance.
And let's notice another subtle
detail in the set here that
helps the family of these
glyphs.
Look at the gap in the video
camera and the negative space in
the envelope.
They share the same line weight.
So, let's look at lines next.
Here, it looks like the glyphs
might have been scaled from
various places to fit together
at the size.
But because they don't share a
consistent line weight, some
look more emphasized than
others, and this can be
confusing, and they just don't
family well.
So, when we normalize these,
we've created a much more
coherent set.
Here's the before and the after.
A subtle change like this can
really affect the integrity of
your app.
Let's move on to positioning.
And this is a great example here
of optical positioning, which
can sometimes be overlooked, and
we can really see it when we
introduce this centered circle
around that Play glyph.
Notice, that art is perfectly
centered within that space, but
optically, it just, it just
looks off.
So, if we nudge that over a few
pixels to the right, we achieve
a much more balanced result.
So, here's the before and the
after.
And optical positioning can
apply to almost any asset that's
asymmetrical or heavier on one
side than the other.
In this example, the share glyph
is, again, perfectly centered
within that space, but it just
looks like it's sitting a bit
too low.
So, by nudging it up a few
pixels, we achieve, again, a
much more considered result.
And by the way, you can bake
this padding right into the
asset.
So, when you go to integrate,
you just center that asset
perfectly in that space, and any
adjustments that are needed be
done with a simple [inaudible]
as well.
So, when you're crafting your
glyphs, build them as sets.
Test them in context, and always
preview them on device, and this
will help you achieve these
results.
So, when you're creating
something from scratch, it can
often be hard to find a starting
point.
It could be overwhelming.
So, how do you get started?
Let's look at a couple of
considerations that can help.
When designing for spaces inside
of your app, you know, such as
list views or buttons, consider
the relationship between type
and the glyphs.
If you have a light type style,
consider matching your lines to
the weight of the type.
If you have a heavy type style,
or more weighted, or filled
glyph style, it might be more
appropriate.
Here's an example from Airbnb.
Notice the lines of the glyphs
match the fonts nicely.
Looks like they really
considered that relationship
between type and glyphs, and it
looks nice.
Now, for system spaces, such as
the Touch Bar on the Mac or Home
screen quick action menus on
iOS, and the central resource
can be the existing system
assets.
In Airbnb's Home screen quick
action menu, we can see the
consistency between their custom
glyphs and the platforms shared
glyphs.
And notice, these glyphs are a
bit larger and heavier than
their in-app counterparts.
So, this is an excellent example
of craftsmanship here by Airbnb.
Now, we have templates on the
human interface guidelines to
help you match optical weight
lines and positioning.
This will help you save time, be
harmonious with the established
design language, and you can
even output your assets directly
from these templates, which is
really nice.
All right.
So, we've gone over a bunch of
things here in a short period of
time.
Let's do a quick recap.
When conceptualizing a glyph,
simplify and think globally.
When crafting them, build them
as sets and test them in context
to make them feel like a family.
Consider the relationship of
type in your glyphs.
And finally, adapt your assets
for system spaces.
So, I hope that these tips will
help you build more effective
and delightful experiences.
But wait a minute, something
looks wrong here.
That's much better.
Thank you very much.
[ Applause ]